<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<book id="1JN" singlevoice="false" pageheader="1 SAN JUAN">
  <block style="mt" chapter="0" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="mt" chapter="0" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1JN">
      <text>1 JOHN</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <text>PRIMERA CARTA de SAN JUAN</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" book="1JN" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="c" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="0">
      <text>1 JOHN 1</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <text>1</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="1" />
      <text>That which was from the beginning, that which we have heard, that which we have seen with our eyes, that which we saw, and our hands touched, concerning the Word of life.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Les escribimos a ustedes acerca de aquello que ya existía desde el principio, de lo que hemos oído y de lo que hemos visto con nuestros propios ojos. Porque lo hemos visto y lo hemos tocado con nuestras manos. Se trata de la Palabra de vida.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="2" />
      <text>(Christ who is life was revealed to us, and we have seen, and testify, and declare to you the life, the eternal life, which was with the Father, and was revealed to us).</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>Esta vida se manifestó: nosotros la vimos y damos testimonio de ella, y les anunciamos a ustedes esta vida eterna, la cual estaba con el Padre y se nos ha manifestado.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="3" />
      <text>That which we have seen and heard we declare to you, that you also may have fellowship with us. Yes, and our fellowship is with the Father, and with his Son, Jesus Christ.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>Les anunciamos, pues, lo que hemos visto y oído, para que ustedes estén unidos con nosotros, como nosotros estamos unidos con Dios el Padre y con su Hijo Jesucristo.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="4" />
      <text>And we write these things to you, that our joy may be fulfilled.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>Escribimos estas cosas para que nuestra alegría sea completa.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="5" />
      <text>This is the message which we have heard from him and announce to you, that God is light, and in him is no darkness at all.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>Este es el mensaje que Jesucristo nos enseñó y que les anunciamos a ustedes: que Dios es luz y que en él no hay ninguna oscuridad.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="6" />
      <text>If we say that we have fellowship with him and walk in the darkness, we lie, and don’t tell the truth.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>Si decimos que estamos unidos a él, y al mismo tiempo vivimos en la oscuridad, mentimos y no practicamos la verdad.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="7" />
      <text>But if we walk in the light, as he is in the light, we have fellowship with one another, and the blood of Jesus Christ, his Son, cleanses us from all sin.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>Pero si vivimos en la luz, así como Dios está en la luz, entonces hay unión entre nosotros, y la sangre de su Hijo Jesús nos limpia de todo pecado.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="8" />
      <text>If we say that we have no sin, we deceive ourselves, and the truth is not in us.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>Si decimos que no tenemos pecado, nos engañamos a nosotros mismos y no hay verdad en nosotros;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="9" />
      <text>If we confess our sins, he is faithful and righteous to forgive us the sins, and to cleanse us from all unrighteousness.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>pero si confesamos nuestros pecados, podemos confiar en que Dios, que es justo, nos perdonará nuestros pecados y nos limpiará de toda maldad.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="10" />
      <text>If we say that we haven’t sinned, we make him a liar, and his word is not in us.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>Si decimos que no hemos cometido pecado, hacemos que Dios parezca mentiroso y no hemos aceptado verdaderamente su palabra.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" book="1JN" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="c" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="0">
      <text>1 JOHN 2</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <text>2</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="1" />
      <text>My little children, I write these things to you so that you may not sin. If anyone sins, we have a Counselor with the Father, Jesus Christ, the righteous.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Hijitos míos, les escribo estas cosas para que no cometan pecado. Aunque si alguno comete pecado, tenemos ante el Padre un defensor, que es Jesucristo, y él es justo.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="2" />
      <text>And he is the atoning sacrifice for our sins, and not for ours only, but also for the whole world.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>Jesucristo se ofreció en sacrificio para que nuestros pecados sean perdonados; y no solo los nuestros, sino los de todo el mundo.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="3" />
      <text>This is how we know that we know him: if we keep his commandments.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>Si obedecemos los mandamientos de Dios, podemos estar seguros de que hemos llegado a conocerlo.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="4" />
      <text>One who says, “I know him,” and doesn’t keep his commandments, is a liar, and the truth isn’t in him.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>Pero si alguno dice: &lt;&lt;Yo lo conozco&gt;&gt;, y no obedece sus mandamientos, es un mentiroso y no hay verdad en él.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="5" />
      <text>But whoever keeps his word, God’s love has most certainly been perfected in him. This is how we know that we are in him:</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>En cambio, si uno obedece su palabra, en él se ha perfeccionado verdaderamente el amor de Dios, y de ese modo sabemos que estamos unidos a él.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="6" />
      <text>He who says he remains in him ought himself also to walk just like he walked.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>El que dice que está unido a Dios, debe vivir como vivió Jesucristo.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="7" />
      <text>Brothers, I write no new commandment to you, but an old commandment which you had from the beginning. The old commandment is the word which you heard from the beginning.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>Queridos hermanos, este mandamiento que les escribo no es nuevo: es el mismo que ustedes recibieron desde el principio. Este mandamiento antiguo es el mensaje que ya oyeron.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="8" />
      <text>Again, I write a new commandment to you, which is true in him and in you; because the darkness is passing away, and the true light already shines.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>Y, sin embargo, esto que les escribo es un mandamiento nuevo, que es verdad tanto en Cristo como en ustedes, porque la oscuridad va pasando y ya brilla la luz verdadera.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="9" />
      <text>He who says he is in the light and hates his brother, is in the darkness even until now.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>Si alguno dice que está en la luz, pero odia a su hermano, todavía está en la oscuridad.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="10" />
      <text>He who loves his brother remains in the light, and there is no occasion for stumbling in him.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>El que ama a su hermano vive en la luz, y no hay nada que lo haga caer.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="11" />
      <text>But he who hates his brother is in the darkness, and walks in the darkness. He doesn’t know where he is going, because the darkness has blinded his eyes.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>Pero el que odia a su hermano vive y anda en la oscuridad, y no sabe a dónde va, porque la oscuridad lo ha dejado ciego.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="12" />
      <text>I write to you, little children, because your sins are forgiven you for his name’s sake.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>Hijitos, les escribo a ustedes porque Dios, gracias a Jesucristo, les ha perdonado sus pecados.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="13" />
      <text>I write to you, fathers, because you know him who is from the beginning. I write to you, young men, because you have overcome the evil one. I write to you, little children, because you know the Father.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>Padres, les escribo a ustedes porque han conocido al que ya existía desde el principio. Jóvenes, les escribo a ustedes porque han vencido al maligno.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="14" />
      <text>I have written to you, fathers, because you know him who is from the beginning. I have written to you, young men, because you are strong, and the word of God remains in you, and you have overcome the evil one.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>Les he escrito a ustedes, hijitos, porque han conocido al Padre. Les he escrito a ustedes, padres, porque han conocido al que ya existía desde el principio. Les he escrito también a ustedes, jóvenes, porque son fuertes y han aceptado la palabra de Dios en su corazón, y porque han vencido al maligno.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="15" />
      <text>Don’t love the world, neither the things that are in the world. If anyone loves the world, the Father’s love isn’t in him.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>No amen al mundo, ni lo que hay en el mundo. Si alguno ama al mundo, no ama al Padre;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="16" />
      <text>For all that is in the world, the lust of the flesh, the lust of the eyes, and the pride of life, isn’t the Father’s, but is the world’s.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>porque nada de lo que el mundo ofrece viene del Padre, sino del mundo mismo. Y esto es lo que el mundo ofrece: los malos deseos de la naturaleza humana, el deseo de poseer lo que agrada a los ojos y el orgullo de las riquezas.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="17" />
      <text>The world is passing away with its lusts, but he who does God’s will remains forever.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>Pero el mundo se va acabando, con todos sus malos deseos; en cambio, el que hace la voluntad de Dios vive para siempre.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="18" />
      <text>Little children, these are the end times, and as you heard that the Antichrist is coming, even now many antichrists have arisen. By this we know that it is the final hour.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>Hijitos, esta es la hora última. Ustedes han oído que viene el Anticristo; pues bien, ahora han aparecido muchos anticristos. Por eso sabemos que es la hora última.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="19" />
      <text>They went out from us, but they didn’t belong to us; for if they had belonged to us, they would have continued with us. But they left, that they might be revealed that none of them belong to us.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>Ellos salieron de entre nosotros; pero en realidad no eran de los nuestros, porque si lo hubieran sido se habrían quedado con nosotros. Pero sucedió así para que se viera claramente que no todos son de los nuestros.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="20" />
      <text>You have an anointing from the Holy One, and you all have knowledge.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>Cristo, el Santo, los ha consagrado a ustedes con el Espíritu, y todos ustedes tienen conocimiento.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="21" />
      <text>I have not written to you because you don’t know the truth, but because you know it, and because no lie is of the truth.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>Les escribo, pues, no porque no conozcan la verdad, sino porque la conocen; y ustedes saben que ninguna mentira puede venir de la verdad.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="22" />
      <text>Who is the liar but he who denies that Jesus is the Christ? This is the Antichrist, he who denies the Father and the Son.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>¿Quién es el mentiroso? Precisamente el que dice que Jesús no es el Mesías. Ese es el Anticristo, pues niega tanto al Padre como al Hijo.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="23" />
      <text>Whoever denies the Son, the same doesn’t have the Father. He who confesses the Son has the Father also.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>Cualquiera que niega al Hijo, tampoco tiene al Padre; pero el que se declara a favor del Hijo, tiene también al Padre.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="24" />
      <text>Therefore, as for you, let that remain in you which you heard from the beginning. If that which you heard from the beginning remains in you, you also will remain in the Son, and in the Father.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="24" />
    <text>Por eso, guarden ustedes en su corazón el mensaje que oyeron desde el principio; y si lo que oyeron desde el principio queda en su corazón, también ustedes permanecerán unidos con el Hijo y con el Padre.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="25" />
      <text>This is the promise which he promised us, the eternal life.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="25" />
    <text>Esto es precisamente lo que nos ha prometido Jesucristo: la vida eterna.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="26" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="26" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="26" />
      <text>These things I have written to you concerning those who would lead you astray.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="26" />
    <text>Les estoy escribiendo acerca de quienes tratan de engañarlos.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="27" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="27" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="27" />
      <text>As for you, the anointing which you received from him remains in you, and you don’t need for anyone to teach you. But as his anointing teaches you concerning all things, and is true, and is no lie, and even as it taught you, you will remain in him.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="27" />
    <text>Pero ustedes tienen el Espíritu Santo con el que Jesucristo los ha consagrado, y no necesitan que nadie les enseñe, porque el Espíritu que él les ha dado los instruye acerca de todas las cosas, y sus enseñanzas son verdad y no mentira. Permanezcan unidos a Cristo, conforme a lo que el Espíritu les ha enseñado.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="28" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="28" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="28" />
      <text>Now, little children, remain in him, that when he appears, we may have boldness, and not be ashamed before him at his coming.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="28" />
    <text>Ahora, hijitos, permanezcan unidos a Cristo, para que tengamos confianza cuando él aparezca y no sintamos vergüenza delante de él cuando venga.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="29" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="29" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="29" />
      <text>If you know that he is righteous, you know that everyone who practices righteousness is born of him.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="29" />
    <text>Ya que ustedes saben que Jesucristo es justo, deben saber también que todos los que hacen lo que es justo son hijos de Dios.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" book="1JN" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="c" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="0">
      <text>1 JOHN 3</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <text>3</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="1" />
      <text>Behold, how great a love the Father has bestowed on us, that we should be called children of God! For this cause the world doesn’t know us, because it didn’t know him.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Miren cuánto nos ama Dios el Padre, que se nos puede llamar hijos de Dios, y lo somos. Por eso, los que son del mundo no nos conocen, pues no han conocido a Dios.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="2" />
      <text>Beloved, now we are children of God, and it is not yet revealed what we will be. But we know that, when he is revealed, we will be like him; for we will see him just as he is.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>Queridos hermanos, ya somos hijos de Dios. Y aunque no se ve todavía lo que seremos después, sabemos que cuando Jesucristo aparezca seremos como él, porque lo veremos tal como es.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="3" />
      <text>Everyone who has this hope set on him purifies himself, even as he is pure.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>Y todo el que tiene esta esperanza en él, se purifica a sí mismo, de la misma manera que Jesucristo es puro.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="4" />
      <text>Everyone who sins also commits lawlessness. Sin is lawlessness.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>Pero todo el que peca, hace maldad; porque el pecado es la maldad.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="5" />
      <text>You know that he was revealed to take away our sins, and in him is no sin.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>Ustedes ya saben que Jesucristo vino al mundo para quitar los pecados, y que él no tiene pecado alguno.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="6" />
      <text>Whoever remains in him doesn’t sin. Whoever sins hasn’t seen him, neither knows him.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>Así pues, todo el que permanece unido a él, no sigue pecando; pero todo el que peca, no lo ha visto ni lo ha conocido.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="7" />
      <text>Little children, let no one lead you astray. He who does righteousness is righteous, even as he is righteous.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>Hijitos míos, que nadie los engañe: el que practica la justicia es justo, como él es justo;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="8" />
      <text>He who sins is of the devil, for the devil has been sinning from the beginning. And the Son of God was revealed, that he might destroy the works of the devil.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>pero el que practica el pecado es del diablo, porque el diablo peca desde el principio. Precisamente para esto ha venido el Hijo de Dios: para deshacer lo hecho por el diablo.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="9" />
      <text>Whoever is born of God doesn’t commit sin, because his seed remains in him; and he can’t sin, because he is born of God.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>Ninguno que sea hijo de Dios practica el pecado, porque tiene en sí mismo el germen de la vida de Dios; y no puede seguir pecando porque es hijo de Dios.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="10" />
      <text>In this the children of God are revealed, and the children of the devil. Whoever doesn’t do righteousness is not of God, neither is he who doesn’t love his brother.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>Se sabe quiénes son hijos de Dios y quiénes son hijos del diablo, porque cualquiera que no hace el bien o no ama a su hermano, no es de Dios.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="11" />
      <text>For this is the message which you heard from the beginning, that we should love one another.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>Este es el mensaje que han oído ustedes desde el principio: que nos amemos unos a otros.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="12" />
      <text>Do not be like Cain, who was of the evil one, and killed his brother. Why did he kill him? Because his works were evil, and his brother’s righteous.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>No seamos como Caín, que era del maligno y mató a su hermano. ¿Y por qué lo mató? Pues porque los hechos de Caín eran malos, y los de su hermano, buenos.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="13" />
      <text>Don’t be surprised, my brothers, if the world hates you.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>Hermanos míos, no se extrañen si los que son del mundo los odian.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="14" />
      <text>We know that we have passed out of death into life, because we love the brothers. He who doesn’t love his brother remains in death.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>Nosotros hemos pasado de la muerte a la vida, y lo sabemos porque amamos a nuestros hermanos. El que no ama, aún está muerto.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="15" />
      <text>Whoever hates his brother is a murderer, and you know that no murderer has eternal life remaining in him.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>Todo el que odia a su hermano es un asesino, y ustedes saben que ningún asesino puede tener vida eterna en sí mismo.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="16" />
      <text>By this we know the love of God, because he laid down his life for us. And we ought to lay down our lives for the brothers.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>Conocemos lo que es el amor porque Jesucristo dio su vida por nosotros; así también, nosotros debemos dar la vida por nuestros hermanos.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="17" />
      <text>But whoever has the world’s goods, and sees his brother in need, and closes his heart of compassion against him, how does the love of God remain in him?</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>Pues si uno es rico y ve que su hermano necesita ayuda, pero no se la da, ¿cómo puede tener amor de Dios en su corazón?</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="18" />
      <text>My little children, let’s not love in word only, neither with the tongue only, but in deed and truth.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>Hijitos míos, que nuestro amor no sea solamente de palabra, sino que se demuestre con hechos.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="19" />
      <text>And by this we know that we are of the truth, and persuade our hearts before him,</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>De esta manera sabremos que somos de la verdad, y podremos sentirnos seguros delante de Dios;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="20" />
      <text>because if our heart condemns us, God is greater than our heart, and knows all things.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>pues si nuestro corazón nos acusa de algo, Dios es más grande que nuestro corazón, y lo sabe todo.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="21" />
      <text>Beloved, if our hearts don’t condemn us, we have boldness toward God;</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>Queridos hermanos, si nuestro corazón no nos acusa, tenemos confianza delante de Dios;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="22" />
      <text>and whatever we ask, we receive from him, because we keep his commandments and do the things that are pleasing in his sight.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>y él nos dará todo lo que le pidamos, porque obedecemos sus mandamientos y hacemos lo que le agrada.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="23" />
      <text>This is his commandment, that we should believe in the name of his Son, Jesus Christ, and love one another, even as he commanded.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>Y su mandamiento es que creamos en su Hijo Jesucristo, y que nos amemos unos a otros como él nos mandó.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="24" />
      <text>He who keeps his commandments remains in him, and he in him. By this we know that he remains in us, by the Spirit which he gave us.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="24" />
    <text>Los que obedecen sus mandamientos viven en él, y él vive en ellos. Y en esto sabemos que él vive en nosotros: por el Espíritu que nos ha dado.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" book="1JN" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="c" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="0">
      <text>1 JOHN 4</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <text>4</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="1" />
      <text>Beloved, don’t believe every spirit, but test the spirits, whether they are of God, because many false prophets have gone out into the world.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Queridos hermanos, no crean ustedes a todos los que dicen estar inspirados por Dios, sino pónganlos a prueba, a ver si el espíritu que hay en ellos es de Dios o no. Porque el mundo está lleno de falsos profetas.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="2" />
      <text>By this you know the Spirit of God: every spirit who confesses that Jesus Christ has come in the flesh is of God.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>De esta manera pueden ustedes saber quién tiene el Espíritu de Dios: todo el que reconoce que Jesucristo vino como hombre verdadero, tiene el Espíritu de Dios.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="3" />
      <text>And every spirit who doesn’t confess that Jesus Christ has come in the flesh is not of God, and this is the spirit of the Antichrist. Of whom you have heard that it comes. Now it is in the world already.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>El que no reconoce así a Jesús, no tiene el Espíritu de Dios; al contrario, tiene el espíritu del Anticristo. Ustedes han oído que ese espíritu ha de venir; pues bien, ya está en el mundo.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="4" />
      <text>You are of God, little children, and have overcome them; because greater is he who is in you than he who is in the world.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>Hijitos, ustedes son de Dios y han vencido a esos mentirosos, porque el que está en ustedes es más poderoso que el que está en el mundo.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="5" />
      <text>They are of the world. Therefore they speak of the world, and the world hears them.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>Ellos son del mundo; por eso hablan de las cosas del mundo, y los que son del mundo los escuchan.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="6" />
      <text>We are of God. He who knows God listens to us. He who is not of God doesn’t listen to us. By this we know the spirit of truth, and the spirit of error.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>En cambio, nosotros somos de Dios. El que conoce a Dios nos escucha, pero el que no es de Dios no nos escucha. En esto, pues, podemos conocer quién tiene el espíritu de la verdad y quién tiene el espíritu del engaño.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="7" />
      <text>Beloved, let us love one another, for love is of God; and everyone who loves is born of God, and knows God.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>Queridos hermanos, debemos amarnos unos a otros, porque el amor viene de Dios. Todo el que ama es hijo de Dios y conoce a Dios.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="8" />
      <text>He who doesn’t love doesn’t know God, for God is love.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>El que no ama no ha conocido a Dios, porque Dios es amor.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="9" />
      <text>By this God’s love was revealed in us, that God has sent his only begotten Son into the world that we might live through him.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>Dios mostró su amor hacia nosotros al enviar a su Hijo único al mundo para que tengamos vida por él.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="10" />
      <text>In this is love, not that we loved God, but that he loved us, and sent his Son as the atoning sacrifice for our sins.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>El amor consiste en esto: no en que nosotros hayamos amado a Dios, sino en que él nos amó a nosotros y envió a su Hijo, para que, ofreciéndose en sacrificio, nuestros pecados quedaran perdonados.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="11" />
      <text>Beloved, if God loved us in this way, we also ought to love one another.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>Queridos hermanos, si Dios nos ha amado así, nosotros también debemos amarnos unos a otros.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="12" />
      <text>No one has seen God at any time. If we love one another, God remains in us, and his love has been perfected in us.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>A Dios nunca lo ha visto nadie; pero si nos amamos unos a otros, Dios vive en nosotros y su amor se hace realidad en nosotros.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="13" />
      <text>By this we know that we remain in him and he in us, because he has given us of his Spirit.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>La prueba de que nosotros vivimos en Dios y de que él vive en nosotros, es que nos ha dado su Espíritu.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="14" />
      <text>We have seen and testify that the Father has sent the Son as the Savior of the world.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>Y nosotros mismos hemos visto y declaramos que el Padre envió a su Hijo para salvar al mundo.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="15" />
      <text>Whoever confesses that Jesus is the Son of God, God remains in him, and he in God.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>Cualquiera que reconoce que Jesús es el Hijo de Dios, vive en Dios y Dios en él.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="16" />
      <text>We know and have believed the love which God has for us. God is love, and he who remains in love remains in God, and God remains in him.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>Así hemos llegado a saber y creer que Dios nos ama. Dios es amor, y el que vive en el amor, vive en Dios y Dios en él.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="17" />
      <text>In this love has been made perfect among us, that we may have boldness in the day of judgment, because as he is, even so are we in this world.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>De esta manera se hace realidad el amor en nosotros, para que en el día del juicio tengamos confianza; porque nosotros somos en este mundo tal como es Jesucristo.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="18" />
      <text>There is no fear in love; but perfect love casts out fear, because fear has punishment. He who fears is not made perfect in love.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>Donde hay amor no hay miedo. Al contrario, el amor perfecto echa fuera el miedo, pues el miedo supone el castigo. Por eso, si alguien tiene miedo, es que no ha llegado a amar perfectamente.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="19" />
      <text>We love him, because he first loved us.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>Nosotros amamos porque él nos amó primero.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="20" />
      <text>If a man says, “I love God,” and hates his brother, he is a liar; for he who doesn’t love his brother whom he has seen, how can he love God whom he has not seen?</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>Si alguno dice: &lt;&lt;Yo amo a Dios&gt;&gt;, y al mismo tiempo odia a su hermano, es un mentiroso. Pues si uno no ama a su hermano, a quien ve, tampoco puede amar a Dios, a quien no ve.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="21" />
      <text>This commandment we have from him, that he who loves God should also love his brother.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>Jesucristo nos ha dado este mandamiento: que el que ama a Dios, ame también a su hermano.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" book="1JN" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="c" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="0">
      <text>1 JOHN 5</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <text>5</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="1" />
      <text>Whoever believes that Jesus is the Christ is born of God. Whoever loves the Father also loves the child who is born of him.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Todo el que tiene fe en que Jesús es el Mesías, es hijo de Dios; y el que ama a un padre, ama también a los hijos de ese padre.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="2" />
      <text>By this we know that we love the children of God, when we love God and keep his commandments.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>Cuando amamos a Dios y hacemos lo que él manda, sabemos que amamos también a los hijos de Dios.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="3" />
      <text>For this is the love of God, that we keep his commandments. His commandments are not grievous.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>El amar a Dios consiste en obedecer sus mandamientos; y sus mandamientos no son una carga,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="4" />
      <text>For whatever is born of God overcomes the world. This is the victory that has overcome the world: your faith.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>porque todo el que es hijo de Dios vence al mundo. Y nuestra fe nos ha dado la victoria sobre el mundo.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="5" />
      <text>Who is he who overcomes the world, but he who believes that Jesus is the Son of God?</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>El que cree que Jesús es el Hijo de Dios, vence al mundo.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="6" />
      <text>This is he who came by water and blood, Jesus Christ; not with the water only, but with the water and the blood. It is the Spirit who testifies, because the Spirit is the truth.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>La venida de Jesucristo quedó señalada con agua y sangre; no solo con agua, sino con agua y sangre. El Espíritu mismo es testigo de esto, y el Espíritu es la verdad.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="7" />
      <text>For there are three who testify in heaven, the Father, the Word, and the Holy Spirit and these three are one.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>Tres son los testigos en el cielo: el Padre, la Palabra y el Espíritu Santo, y estos tres son uno.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="8" />
      <text>And there are three that bear witness in the earth, the Spirit, the water, and the blood; and the three agree as one.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>Y tres son los testigos en la tierra. el Espíritu, el agua y la sangre; y los tres están de acuerdo.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="9" />
      <text>If we receive the witness of men, the witness of God is greater; for this is God’s testimony which he has testified concerning his Son.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>Aceptamos el testimonio de los hombres, pero el testimonio de Dios es de mucho más valor, porque consiste en el testimonio que Dios ha dado acerca de su Hijo.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="10" />
      <text>He who believes in the Son of God has the testimony in himself. He who doesn’t believe God has made him a liar, because he has not believed in the testimony that God has given concerning his Son.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>El que cree en el Hijo de Dios, lleva este testimonio en su propio corazón; el que no cree en Dios, lo hace aparecer como mentiroso, porque no cree en el testimonio que Dios ha dado acerca de su Hijo.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="11" />
      <text>The testimony is this, that God gave to us eternal life, and this life is in his Son.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>Este testimonio es que Dios nos ha dado vida eterna, y que esta vida está en su Hijo.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="12" />
      <text>He who has the Son has the life. He who doesn’t have God’s Son doesn’t have the life.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>El que tiene al Hijo de Dios, tiene también esta vida; pero el que no tiene al Hijo de Dios, no la tiene.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="13" />
      <text>These things I have written to you who believe on the name of the Son of God, that you may know that you have eternal life, and that you may continue to believe in the name of the Son of God.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>Les escribo esto a ustedes que creen en el Hijo de Dios, para que sepan que tienen vida eterna.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="14" />
      <text>This is the boldness which we have toward him, that, if we ask anything according to his will, he listens to us.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>Tenemos confianza en Dios, porque sabemos que si le pedimos algo conforme a su voluntad, él nos oye.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="15" />
      <text>And if we know that he listens to us, whatever we ask, we know that we have the petitions which we have asked of him.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>Y así como sabemos que Dios oye nuestras oraciones, también sabemos que ya tenemos lo que le hemos pedido.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="16" />
      <text>If anyone sees his brother sinning a sin not leading to death, he shall ask, and God will give him life for those who sin not leading to death. There is a sin leading to death. I don’t say that he should make a request concerning this.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>Si alguno ve que su hermano está cometiendo un pecado que no lleva a la muerte, debe orar, y Dios dará vida al hermano, si se trata de un pecado que no lleva a la muerte. Hay un pecado que lleva a la muerte, y por ese pecado no digo que se deba orar.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="17" />
      <text>All unrighteousness is sin, and there is a sin not leading to death.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>Toda maldad es pecado; pero hay pecado que no lleva a la muerte.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="18" />
      <text>We know that whoever is born of God doesn’t sin, but he who was born of God keeps himself, and the evil one doesn’t touch him.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>Sabemos que el que tiene a Dios como Padre, no sigue pecando, porque el Hijo de Dios lo cuida, y el maligno no lo toca.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="19" />
      <text>We know that we are of God, and the whole world lies in the power of the evil one.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>Sabemos que somos de Dios y que el mundo entero está bajo el poder del maligno.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="20" />
      <text>We know that the Son of God has come, and has given us an understanding, that we know him who is true, and we are in him who is true, in his Son Jesus Christ. This is the true God, and eternal life.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>Sabemos también que el Hijo de Dios ha venido y nos ha dado entendimiento para conocer al Dios verdadero. Vivimos unidos al que es verdadero, es decir, a su Hijo Jesucristo. Este es el Dios verdadero y la vida eterna.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-1JN" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-1JN">
      <verse num="21" />
      <text>Little children, keep yourselves from idols.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>Hijitos, cuídense de los dioses falsos.</text>
  </block>
  <UnappliedSplits />
</book>