<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<book id="2TH" singlevoice="false" pageheader="2 THESSALONIANS">
  <block style="mt" chapter="0" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="mt" chapter="0" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-2TH">
      <text>2 THESSALONIANS</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <text>2 THESSALONIANS</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" book="2TH" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="c" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="0">
      <text>2 THESSALONIANS 1</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <text>1</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="1" />
      <text>Paul, Silvanus, and Timothy, to the assembly of the Thessalonians in God our Father, and the Lord Jesus Christ:</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Pablo, Silvano y Timoteo saludan a la comunidad de los creyentes de la ciudad de Tesalónica, que están unidos a Dios nuestro Padre y al Señor Jesucristo.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="2" />
      <text>Grace to you and peace from God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>Que Dios nuestro Padre y el Señor Jesucristo derramen su gracia y su paz sobre ustedes.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="3" />
      <text>We are bound to always give thanks to God for you, brothers, even as it is appropriate, because your faith grows exceedingly, and the love of each and every one of you towards one another abounds.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>Hermanos, siempre tenemos que dar gracias a Dios por ustedes, como es justo que hagamos, porque la fe de ustedes está creciendo y el amor que cada uno tiene por los otros es cada vez mayor.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="4" />
      <text>Therefore we ourselves boast about you in the assemblies of God. We boast of your patience and faith in all your persecutions and in the afflictions which you endure.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>De modo que nosotros mismos hablamos de ustedes con satisfacción en las iglesias de Dios, por la fortaleza y la fe que ustedes muestran en medio de todas las persecuciones y aflicciones que sufren.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="5" />
      <text>This is an obvious sign of the righteous judgment of God, to the end that you may be counted worthy of the Kingdom of God, for which you also suffer.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>Esto es una señal del justo juicio de Dios y muestra que él los ha juzgado dignos de entrar en su reino, por el cual están sufriendo.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="6" />
      <text>Since it is a righteous thing with God to repay affliction to those who afflict you,</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>Pues es justo que Dios haga sufrir a quienes los hacen sufrir a ustedes,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="7" />
      <text>and to give relief to you who are afflicted with us. This will happen when the Lord Jesus is revealed from heaven with his mighty angels in flaming fire:</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>y que a ustedes, los que sufren, les dé descanso lo mismo que a nosotros. Esto será en el día en que el Señor Jesús aparezca con sus ángeles poderosos, viniendo del cielo entre llamas de fuego.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="8" />
      <text>He will give vengeance to those who don’t know God, and to those who don’t obey the Good News of our Lord Jesus Christ,</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>Vendrá para castigar a los que no reconocen a Dios ni obedecen al evangelio de nuestro Señor Jesús.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="9" />
      <text>They will pay the penalty: eternal destruction from the face of the Lord and from the glory of his might.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>Estos serán castigados con destrucción eterna, y serán arrojados lejos de la presencia del Señor y de su gloria y poder,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="10" />
      <text>When he comes, his glory will be seen in his saints. He will receive honor from all those who put their trust in him. This includes you because you believed our testimony to you.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>cuando el Señor venga en aquel día para ser honrado entre su pueblo santo y admirado por todos los creyentes; pues ustedes han creído en el testimonio que les dimos.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="11" />
      <text>To this end we also pray always for you, that our God may count you worthy of your calling, and fulfill every desire of goodness and work of faith, with power.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>Con este fin oramos siempre por ustedes, pidiendo a nuestro Dios que los haga dignos del llamamiento que les hizo, y que cumpla por su poder todos los buenos deseos de ustedes y los trabajos que realizan movidos por su fe.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="12" />
      <text>In this way, the name of our Lord Jesus Christ may be glorified in you, and you in him. Aaccording to the grace of our God and the Lord Jesus Christ.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>De esta manera, el nombre de nuestro Señor Jesús será honrado por causa de ustedes, y él los honrará conforme a la bondad de nuestro Dios y del Señor Jesucristo.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" book="2TH" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="c" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="0">
      <text>2 THESSALONIANS 2</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <text>2</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="1" />
      <text>Now, brothers, concerning the coming of our Lord Jesus Christ, and our gathering together to him, here is what we ask:</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Ahora, hermanos, en cuanto al regreso de nuestro Señor Jesucristo y a nuestra reunión con él, les rogamos</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="2" />
      <text>Do not be quickly shaken in your mind, nor yet be troubled, either by spirit, or by word. Nor by letter as from us, saying that the day of Christ had come.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>que no cambien fácilmente de manera de pensar ni se dejen asustar por nadie que diga haber tenido una revelación del Espíritu, o haber recibido una enseñanza dada de palabra o por carta, según la cual nosotros habríamos afirmado que el día del regreso del Señor ya llegó.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="3" />
      <text>Let no one deceive you in any way. For it will not be, unless the departure comes first, and the man of sin is revealed. He is the son of destruction.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>No se dejen engañar de ninguna manera. Pues antes de aquel día tiene que venir la rebelión contra Dios, cuando aparecerá el hombre malvado, el que está condenado a la perdición.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="4" />
      <text>He opposes and exalts himself against all that is called God or that is worshiped; so that he sits as God in the temple of God, setting himself up as God.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>Este es el enemigo que se levanta contra todo lo que lleva el nombre de Dios o merece ser adorado, y llega incluso a instalar su trono en el templo de Dios, haciéndose pasar por Dios.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="5" />
      <text>Don’t you remember that, when I was still with you, I told you these things?</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>¿No recuerdan que yo les hablaba de esto cuando aún estaba con ustedes?</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="6" />
      <text>Now you know what is restraining him, to the end that he may be revealed in his own season.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>Y ahora ustedes saben qué es lo que lo detiene, para que no aparezca antes de su debido tiempo.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="7" />
      <text>For the mystery of lawlessness already works. Only there is one who restrains now, until he is taken out of the way.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>Pues el plan secreto de la maldad ya está en marcha; solo falta que sea quitado de en medio el que ahora lo está deteniendo.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="8" />
      <text>Then the lawless one will be revealed, whom the Lord will kill with the breath of his mouth, and destroy by the manifestation of his coming.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>Entonces aparecerá aquel malvado, a quien el Señor Jesús destruirá con el soplo de su boca y reducirá a la impotencia cuando regrese en todo su esplendor.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="9" />
      <text>The coming of the lawless one will be in accordance with the working of Satan with all power and signs and lying wonders.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>En cuanto a ese malvado, vendrá con la ayuda de Satanás; llegará con mucho poder, y con señales y milagros falsos.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="10" />
      <text>Those who are lost in sin will be deceived by the things he can do because they didn’t receive the love of the truth, that they might be saved.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>Y usará toda clase de maldad para engañar a los que van a la condenación, porque no quisieron aceptar y amar la verdad para recibir la salvación.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="11" />
      <text>Because of this, God sends them a working of error, that they should believe a lie.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>Por eso, Dios deja que el error los engañe y que crean en la mentira,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="12" />
      <text>They will all be judged because they didn’t believe the truth, but had pleasure in unrighteousness.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>a fin de que sean condenados todos los que no han querido creer en la verdad, sino que se complacen en la maldad.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="13" />
      <text>But we are bound to always give thanks to God for you, brothers loved by the Lord, because God chose you from the beginning for salvation through sanctification of the Spirit and belief in the truth.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>Pero nosotros siempre tenemos que dar gracias a Dios por ustedes, hermanos amados por el Señor, porque Dios los escogió para que fueran los primeros en alcanzar la salvación por medio del Espíritu que los hace santos y de la verdad en que han creído.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="14" />
      <text>He called you to this through our Good News, for the obtaining of the glory of our Lord Jesus Christ.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>Para esto los llamó Dios por medio del evangelio que nosotros anunciamos: para que lleguen a tener parte en la gloria de nuestro Señor Jesucristo.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="15" />
      <text>So then, brothers, stand firm, and hold the traditions which you were taught by us, whether by word, or by letter.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>Así que, hermanos, sigan firmes y no se olviden de las tradiciones que les hemos enseñado personalmente y por carta.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="16" />
      <text>Now our Lord Jesus Christ himself, and God our Father, who loved us and gave us eternal comfort and good hope through grace,</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>Que nuestro Señor Jesucristo mismo, y Dios nuestro Padre, que nos ha amado y nos ha dado consuelo eterno y esperanza gracias a su bondad,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="17" />
      <text>comfort your hearts and establish you in every good work and word.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>anime sus corazones y los mantenga a ustedes constantes en hacer y decir siempre lo bueno.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" book="2TH" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="c" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="0">
      <text>2 THESSALONIANS 3</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <text>3</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="1" />
      <text>Finally, brothers, pray for us, that the word of the Lord may spread rapidly and be glorified, even as also with you;</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Por último, hermanos, oren por nosotros, para que el mensaje del Señor llegue pronto a todas partes y sea recibido con estimación, como sucedió entre ustedes.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="2" />
      <text>and that we may be delivered from unreasonable and evil men; for not all have faith.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>Oren también para que seamos librados de los hombres malos y perversos, porque no todos tienen fe.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="3" />
      <text>But the Lord is faithful, who will establish you, and guard you from the evil one.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>Pero el Señor es fiel, y él los mantendrá a ustedes firmes y los protegerá del mal.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="4" />
      <text>We have confidence in the Lord concerning you, that you both do and will do the things we command.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>Y en el Señor tenemos confianza en que ustedes hacen y seguirán haciendo lo que les hemos ordenado.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="5" />
      <text>May the Lord direct your hearts into the love of God, and into the patience of Christ.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>Que el Señor los ayude a amar como Dios ama y a tener en el sufrimiento la fortaleza de Cristo.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="6" />
      <text>Now we command you, brothers, in the name of our Lord Jesus Christ. Withdraw yourselves from every brother who walks in rebellion, and not after the tradition which they received from us.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>Hermanos, les ordenamos en el nombre de nuestro Señor Jesucristo, que se aparten de cualquier hermano que lleve una conducta indisciplinada y que no siga las tradiciones que recibieron de nosotros.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="7" />
      <text>For you know how you ought to imitate us. For we didn’t behave ourselves rebelliously among you,</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>Pues ustedes saben cómo deben vivir para seguir nuestro ejemplo: nosotros no llevamos entre ustedes una conducta indisciplinada,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="8" />
      <text>neither did we eat bread from anyone’s hand without paying for it. In labor and travail we worked night and day, that we might not burden any of you.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>ni hemos comido el pan de nadie sin pagarlo. Al contrario, trabajamos y luchamos día y noche para no serle una carga a ninguno de ustedes.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="9" />
      <text>We did this, not because we don’t have the right, but to make ourselves an example to you, that you should imitate us.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>Y ciertamente teníamos el derecho de pedirles a ustedes que nos ayudaran, pero trabajamos para darles el ejemplo que ustedes deben seguir.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="10" />
      <text>For even when we were with you, we commanded you this: “If anyone will not work, neither let him eat.”</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>Cuando estuvimos con ustedes, les dimos esta regla: El que no quiera trabajar, que tampoco coma.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="11" />
      <text>For we hear of some who walk among you in rebellion, who don’t work at all, but are busybodies.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>Pero hemos sabido que algunos de ustedes llevan una conducta indisciplinada, muy ocupados en no hacer nada.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="12" />
      <text>Now those who are that way, we command and exhort in the Lord Jesus Christ, that with quietness they work, and eat their own bread.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>A tales personas les mandamos y encargamos, por la autoridad del Señor Jesucristo, que trabajen tranquilamente para ganarse la vida.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="13" />
      <text>But you, brothers, don’t be weary in doing well.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>Pero ustedes, hermanos, no se cansen de hacer el bien.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="14" />
      <text>If any man doesn’t obey our word in this letter, note that man, that you have no company with him, to the end that he may be ashamed.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>Si alguno no hace caso a lo que decimos en esta carta, fíjense en quién es y no se junten con él, para que le dé vergüenza.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="15" />
      <text>Don’t count him as an enemy, but admonish him as a brother.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>Pero no lo tengan por enemigo, sino amonéstenlo como a hermano.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="16" />
      <text>Now may the Lord of peace himself give you peace at all times in all ways. The Lord be with you all.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>Y que el mismo Señor de la paz les dé la paz a ustedes en todo tiempo y en todas formas. Que el Señor esté con todos ustedes.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="17" />
      <text>The greeting of me, Paul, with my own hand, which is the sign in every letter: this is how I write.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>Yo, Pablo, les escribo este saludo de mi puño y letra. Así firmo todas mis cartas; así escribo.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="18" />
      <text>The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with you all. Amen.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>Que nuestro Señor Jesucristo derrame su gracia sobre todos ustedes.</text>
  </block>
  <UnappliedSplits />
</book>