<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<book id="JUD" singlevoice="false" pageheader="CARTA de SAN JUDAS">
  <block style="mt" chapter="0" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-JUD" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="mt" chapter="0" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-JUD">
      <text>JUDE</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <text>CARTA de SAN JUDAS</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" book="JUD" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-JUD" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="c" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="0">
      <text>JUDE CHP 1</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <text>1</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-JUD" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-JUD">
      <verse num="1" />
      <text>Jude, a servant of Jesus Christ, and brother of James, to those who are called, sanctified by God the Father, and kept for Jesus Christ:</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Judas, siervo de Jesucristo y hermano de Santiago, saluda a los que Dios el Padre ama y ha llamado, los cuales son protegidos por Jesucristo.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-JUD" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-JUD">
      <verse num="2" />
      <text>Mercy to you and peace and love be multiplied.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>Reciban ustedes abundancia de misericordia, paz y amor.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-JUD" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-JUD">
      <verse num="3" />
      <text>Beloved, while I was very eager to write to you about our common salvation, I was constrained to write to you exhorting you to contend earnestly for the faith which was once for all delivered to the saints.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>Queridos hermanos, he sentido grandes deseos de escribirles acerca de la salvación que tanto ustedes como yo tenemos; pero ahora me veo en la necesidad de hacerlo para rogarles que luchen por la fe que una vez fue entregada al pueblo santo.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-JUD" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-JUD">
      <verse num="4" />
      <text>For there are certain men who crept in secretly, even those who were long ago written about for this condemnation: ungodly men, turning the grace of our God into indecency, and denying our only Master, God, and Lord, Jesus Christ.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>Porque por medio de engaños se han infiltrado ciertas personas a quienes las Escrituras ya habían señalado desde hace mucho tiempo para la condenación. Son hombres malvados, que toman la bondad de nuestro Dios como pretexto para una vida desenfrenada, y niegan a nuestro único Dueño y Señor, Jesucristo.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-JUD" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-JUD">
      <verse num="5" />
      <text>Now I desire to remind you, though you already know this, that the Lord, having saved a people out of the land of Egypt, afterward destroyed those who didn't believe.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>Aunque ustedes ya lo saben, quiero recordarles que el Señor, después que sacó de Egipto al pueblo de Israel, destruyó a los que no creyeron.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-JUD" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-JUD">
      <verse num="6" />
      <text>Angels who didn't keep their first domain, but deserted their own dwelling place, he has kept in everlasting bonds under darkness for the judgment of the great day.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>Y a los ángeles que no conservaron su debido puesto, sino que dejaron su propio hogar, Dios los retiene en prisiones oscuras y eternas para el gran día del juicio.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-JUD" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-JUD">
      <verse num="7" />
      <text>Even as Sodom and Gomorrah, and the cities around them, having, in the same way as these, given themselves over to sexual immorality and gone after strange flesh, are set forth as an example, suffering the punishment of eternal fire.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>Lo mismo que esos ángeles, también Sodoma y Gomorra y las ciudades vecinas se entregaron a la prostitución, y se dejaron llevar por vicios contra la naturaleza. Por eso sufrieron el castigo del fuego eterno y quedaron como advertencia para todos.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-JUD" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-JUD">
      <verse num="8" />
      <text>Yet in the same way, these also in their dreaming defile the flesh, despise authority, and slander celestial beings.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>A pesar de ello, también esos hombres, viviendo en sueños, contaminan su cuerpo, rechazan la autoridad del Señor e insultan a los poderes superiores.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-JUD" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-JUD">
      <verse num="9" />
      <text>But Michael, the archangel, when contending with the devil and arguing about the body of Moses, dared not bring against him an abusive condemnation, but said, </text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>El mismo arcángel Miguel, cuando luchaba contra el diablo disputándole el cuerpo de Moisés, no se atrevió a condenarlo con insultos, sino que solamente le dijo:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="Michael, archangel" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="Michael, archangel">
      <text>“May the Lord rebuke you!”</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <text>&lt;&lt;¡Que el Señor te reprenda!&gt;&gt;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-JUD" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-JUD">
      <verse num="10" />
      <text>But these speak evil of whatever things they don't know. What they understand naturally, like the creatures without reason, they are destroyed in these things.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>Pero esos hombres hablan mal de las cosas que no conocen; y en cuanto a las que conocen por instinto, como las conocen los animales sin entendimiento, las usan para su propia condenación.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-JUD" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-JUD">
      <verse num="11" />
      <text>Woe to them! For they went in the way of Cain, and ran riotously in the error of Balaam for hire, and perished in Korah's rebellion.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>¡Ay de ellos!, porque han seguido el ejemplo de Caín. Por ganar dinero se han desviado, como Balaam, y como Coré, mueren por su rebeldía.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-JUD" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-JUD">
      <verse num="12" />
      <text>These men are hidden rocky reefs in your love feasts when they feast with you, shepherds who without fear feed themselves; clouds without water, carried along by winds. They are like autumn leaves without fruit, twice dead, plucked up by the roots.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>Son una vergüenza en las fiestas de amor fraternal que ustedes celebran, en las que ellos comen y beben alegremente, sin mostrar ningún respeto. Son pastores que cuidan solamente de sí mismos. Son nubes sin agua, llevadas por el viento. Son árboles que no dan fruto a su tiempo, dos veces muertos y arrancados de raíz.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-JUD" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-JUD">
      <verse num="13" />
      <text>They are like wild waves of the sea, foaming out their own shame; wandering stars, for whom the blackness of darkness has been reserved forever.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>Son violentas olas del mar, que arrojan como espuma sus acciones vergonzosas. Son estrellas que han perdido su rumbo y están condenadas a pasar la eternidad en la más negra oscuridad.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-JUD" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-JUD">
      <verse num="14" />
      <text>About these also Enoch, the seventh from Adam, prophesied, saying,</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>También Henoc, que fue el séptimo después de Adán, habló proféticamente cuando dijo acerca de esa gente:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="Enoch" multiBlockQuote="Start" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="Enoch" multiBlockQuote="Start">
      <text>“Behold, the Lord came with ten thousands of his holy ones,</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <text>&lt;&lt;Vi al Señor, que venía con miles y miles de sus ángeles</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="Enoch" multiBlockQuote="Continuation" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="Enoch" multiBlockQuote="Continuation">
      <verse num="15" />
      <text>to execute judgment on all, and to convict all the ungodly of all their works of ungodliness which they have done in an ungodly way, and of all the hard things which ungodly sinners have spoken against him.”</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>a juzgar a todos los hombres y a condenarlos por todo el mal que cometieron en su maldad y por todas las palabras insolentes que como malvados pecadores dijeron contra él.&gt;&gt;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-JUD" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-JUD">
      <verse num="16" />
      <text>These are murmurers and complainers, walking after their lusts (and their mouth speaks proud things), showing respect of persons to gain advantage.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>De todo se quejan, todo lo critican y solo buscan satisfacer sus propios deseos. Hablan con jactancia, y adulan a los demás para aprovecharse de ellos.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-JUD" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-JUD">
      <verse num="17" />
      <text>But you, beloved, remember the words which have been spoken before by the apostles of our Lord Jesus Christ.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>Pero ustedes, queridos hermanos, acuérdense de que los apóstoles de nuestro Señor Jesucristo</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-JUD" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-JUD">
      <verse num="18" />
      <text>They said to you that “In the last time there will be mockers, walking after their own ungodly lusts.”</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>les habían dicho: &lt;&lt;En los últimos tiempos habrá gente burlona, que vivirá de acuerdo con sus malos deseos.&gt;&gt;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-JUD" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-JUD">
      <verse num="19" />
      <text>These are they who cause divisions, and are sensual, not having the Spirit.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>Esos son los que causan divisiones; siguen sus deseos naturales y no tienen el Espíritu de Dios.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-JUD" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-JUD">
      <verse num="20" />
      <text>But you, beloved, keep building up yourselves on your most holy faith, praying in the Holy Spirit.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>Pero ustedes, queridos hermanos, manténganse firmes en su santísima fe. Oren guiados por el Espíritu Santo.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-JUD" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-JUD">
      <verse num="21" />
      <text>Keep yourselves in the love of God, looking for the mercy of our Lord Jesus Christ to eternal life.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>Consérvense en el amor de Dios y esperen el día en que nuestro Señor Jesucristo, en su misericordia, nos dará la vida eterna.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-JUD" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-JUD">
      <verse num="22" />
      <text>Be merciful to those who doubt.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>Tengan compasión de los que dudan.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="narrator-JUD" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="narrator-JUD">
      <verse num="23" />
      <text>Snatch others from the fire and save them. To others show mercy mixed with fear, hating even the clothing stained by the flesh.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>A unos sálvenlos sacándolos del fuego, y tengan compasión de otros, aunque cuídense de ellos y aborrezcan hasta la ropa que llevan contaminada por su mala vida.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="narrator-JUD" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="narrator-JUD">
      <verse num="24" />
      <text>Now to him who is able to keep them from stumbling, and to present you faultless before the presence of his glory in great joy --</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="24" />
    <text>Y a aquel que es capaz de guardaros sin caída, y presentaros sin mancha delante de su gloria con gran alegría -</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="narrator-JUD" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="narrator-JUD">
      <verse num="25" />
      <text>to God our Savior, who alone is wise, be glory and majesty, dominion and power, both now and forever. Amen.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="25" />
    <text>a Dios nuestro Salvador, quien es el único sabio, sea gloria y majestad, imperio y potencia, ahora y siempre. Amén.</text>
  </block>
  <UnappliedSplits />
</book>