<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<book id="1CH" singlevoice="false" pageheader="1 Chronicles">
  <block style="mt" chapter="0" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1CH">
    <text>1 Chronicles</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" book="1CH" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1CH">
    <text>1</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Adam, Seth, Enosh, </text>
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>Kenan, Mahalalel, Jared, </text>
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>Enoch, Methuselah, Lamech, </text>
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>Noah, Shem, Ham, and Japheth.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>The sons of Japheth: Gomer, and Magog, and Madai, and Javan, and Tubal, and Meshech, and Tiras.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>The sons of Gomer: Ashkenaz, and Diphath, and Togarmah.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>The sons of Javan: Elishah, and Tarshish, Kittim, and Rodanim.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>The sons of Ham: Cush, and Mizraim, Put, and Canaan.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>The sons of Cush: Seba, and Havilah, and Sabta, and Raama, and Sabteca. The sons of Raamah: Sheba, and Dedan.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>Cush became the father of Nimrod; he began to be a mighty one in the earth.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>Mizraim became the father of Ludim, and Anamim, and Lehabim, and Naphtuhim, </text>
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>and Pathrusim, and Casluhim (where the Philistines came from), and Caphtorim.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>Canaan became the father of Sidon his firstborn, and Heth, </text>
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>and the Jebusite, and the Amorite, and the Girgashite, </text>
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>and the Hivite, and the Arkite, and the Sinite, </text>
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>and the Arvadite, and the Zemarite, and the Hamathite.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>The sons of Shem: Elam, and Asshur, and Arpachshad, and Lud, and Aram, and Uz, and Hul, and Gether, and Meshech.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>Arpachshad became the father of Shelah, and Shelah became the father of Eber.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>To Eber were born two sons: the name of the one was Peleg; for in his days the earth was divided; and his brother's name was Joktan.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>Joktan became the father of Almodad, and Sheleph, and Hazarmaveth, and Jerah, </text>
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>and Hadoram, and Uzal, and Diklah, </text>
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>and Ebal, and Abimael, and Sheba, </text>
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>and Ophir, and Havilah, and Jobab. All these were the sons of Joktan.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="24" />
    <text>Shem, Arpachshad, Shelah, </text>
    <verse num="25" />
    <text>Eber, Peleg, Reu, </text>
    <verse num="26" />
    <text>Serug, Nahor, Terah, </text>
    <verse num="27" />
    <text>Abram (the same is Abraham).</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="28" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="28" />
    <text>The sons of Abraham: Isaac, and Ishmael.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="29" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="29" />
    <text>These are their generations: the firstborn of Ishmael, Nebaioth; then Kedar, and Adbeel, and Mibsam, </text>
    <verse num="30" />
    <text>Mishma, and Dumah, Massa, Hadad, and Tema, </text>
    <verse num="31" />
    <text>Jetur, Naphish, and Kedemah. These are the sons of Ishmael.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="32" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="32" />
    <text>The sons of Keturah, Abraham's concubine: she bore Zimran, and Jokshan, and Medan, and Midian, and Ishbak, and Shuah. The sons of Jokshan: Sheba, and Dedan.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="33" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="33" />
    <text>The sons of Midian: Ephah, and Epher, and Hanoch, and Abida, and Eldaah. All these were the sons of Keturah.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="34" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="34" />
    <text>Abraham became the father of Isaac. The sons of Isaac: Esau, and Israel.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="35" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="35" />
    <text>The sons of Esau: Eliphaz, Reuel, and Jeush, and Jalam, and Korah.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="36" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="36" />
    <text>The sons of Eliphaz: Teman, and Omar, Zephi, and Gatam, Kenaz, and Timna, and Amalek.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="37" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="37" />
    <text>The sons of Reuel: Nahath, Zerah, Shammah, and Mizzah.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="38" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="38" />
    <text>The sons of Seir: Lotan, and Shobal, and Zibeon, and Anah, and Dishon, and Ezer, and Dishan.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="39" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="39" />
    <text>The sons of Lotan: Hori, and Homam; and Timna was Lotan's sister.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="40" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="40" />
    <text>The sons of Shobal: Alian, and Manahath, and Ebal, Shephi, and Onam. The sons of Zibeon: Aiah, and Anah.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="41" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="41" />
    <text>The sons of Anah: Dishon. The sons of Dishon: Hamran, and Eshban, and Ithran, and Cheran.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="42" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="42" />
    <text>The sons of Ezer: Bilhan, and Zaavan, Jaakan. The sons of Dishan: Uz, and Aran.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="43" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="43" />
    <text>Now these are the kings who reigned in the land of Edom, before there reigned any king over the children of Israel: Bela the son of Beor; and the name of his city was Dinhabah.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="44" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="44" />
    <text>Bela died, and Jobab the son of Zerah of Bozrah reigned in his place.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="45" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="45" />
    <text>Jobab died, and Husham of the land of the Temanites reigned in his place.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="46" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="46" />
    <text>Husham died, and Hadad the son of Bedad, who struck Midian in the field of Moab, reigned in his place; and the name of his city was Avith.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="47" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="47" />
    <text>Hadad died, and Samlah of Masrekah reigned in his place.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="48" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="48" />
    <text>Samlah died, and Shaul of Rehoboth by the River reigned in his place.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="49" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="49" />
    <text>Shaul died, and Baal Hanan the son of Achbor reigned in his place.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="50" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="50" />
    <text>Baal Hanan died, and Hadad reigned in his place; and the name of his city was Pai: and his wife's name was Mehetabel, the daughter of Matred, the daughter of Mezahab.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="51" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="51" />
    <text>Hadad died. The chiefs of Edom were: chief Timna, chief Aliah, chief Jetheth, </text>
    <verse num="52" />
    <text>chief Oholibamah, chief Elah, chief Pinon, </text>
    <verse num="53" />
    <text>chief Kenaz, chief Teman, chief Mibzar, </text>
    <verse num="54" />
    <text>chief Magdiel, chief Iram. These are the chiefs of Edom.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" book="1CH" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1CH">
    <text>2</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>These are the sons of Israel: Reuben, Simeon, Levi, and Judah, Issachar, and Zebulun, </text>
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>Dan, Joseph, and Benjamin, Naphtali, Gad, and Asher.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>The sons of Judah: Er, and Onan, and Shelah; which three were born to him of Shua's daughter the Canaanitess. Er, Judah's firstborn, was wicked in the sight of God; and he killed him.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>Tamar his daughter-in-law bore him Perez and Zerah. All the sons of Judah were five.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>The sons of Perez: Hezron, and Hamul.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>The sons of Zerah: Zimri, and Ethan, and Heman, and Calcol, and Dara; five of them in all.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>The sons of Carmi: Achar, the troubler of Israel, who committed a trespass in the devoted thing.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>The sons of Ethan: Azariah.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>The sons also of Hezron, who were born to him: Jerahmeel, and Ram, and Chelubai.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>Ram became the father of Amminadab, and Amminadab became the father of Nahshon, prince of the children of Judah;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>and Nahshon became the father of Salma, and Salma became the father of Boaz, </text>
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>and Boaz became the father of Obed, and Obed became the father of Jesse;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>and Jesse became the father of his firstborn Eliab, and Abinadab the second, and Shimea the third, </text>
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>Nethanel the fourth, Raddai the fifth, </text>
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>Ozem the sixth, David the seventh;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>and their sisters were Zeruiah and Abigail. The sons of Zeruiah: Abishai, and Joab, and Asahel, three.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>Abigail bore Amasa; and the father of Amasa was Jether the Ishmaelite.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>Caleb the son of Hezron became the father of [children] of Azubah [his] wife, and of Jerioth; and these were her sons: Jesher, and Shobab, and Ardon.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>Azubah died, and Caleb took to him Ephrath, who bore him Hur.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>Hur became the father of Uri, and Uri became the father of Bezalel.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>Afterward Hezron went in to the daughter of Machir the father of Gilead, whom he took [as wife] when he was sixty years old; and she bore him Segub.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>Segub became the father of Jair, who had twenty-three cities in the land of Gilead.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>Geshur and Aram took the towns of Jair from them, with Kenath, and its villages, even sixty cities. All these were the sons of Machir the father of Gilead.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="24" />
    <text>After that Hezron was dead in Caleb Ephrathah, then Abijah Hezron's wife bore him Ashhur the father of Tekoa.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="25" />
    <text>The sons of Jerahmeel the firstborn of Hezron were Ram the firstborn, and Bunah, and Oren, and Ozem, Ahijah.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="26" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="26" />
    <text>Jerahmeel had another wife, whose name was Atarah; she was the mother of Onam.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="27" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="27" />
    <text>The sons of Ram the firstborn of Jerahmeel were Maaz, and Jamin, and Eker.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="28" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="28" />
    <text>The sons of Onam were Shammai, and Jada. The sons of Shammai: Nadab, and Abishur.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="29" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="29" />
    <text>The name of the wife of Abishur was Abihail; and she bore him Ahban, and Molid.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="30" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="30" />
    <text>The sons of Nadab: Seled, and Appaim; but Seled died without children.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="31" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="31" />
    <text>The sons of Appaim: Ishi. The sons of Ishi: Sheshan. The sons of Sheshan: Ahlai.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="32" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="32" />
    <text>The sons of Jada the brother of Shammai: Jether, and Jonathan; and Jether died without children.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="33" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="33" />
    <text>The sons of Jonathan: Peleth, and Zaza. These were the sons of Jerahmeel.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="34" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="34" />
    <text>Now Sheshan had no sons, but daughters. Sheshan had a servant, an Egyptian, whose name was Jarha.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="35" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="35" />
    <text>Sheshan gave his daughter to Jarha his servant as wife; and she bore him Attai.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="36" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="36" />
    <text>Attai became the father of Nathan, and Nathan became the father of Zabad, </text>
    <verse num="37" />
    <text>and Zabad became the father of Ephlal, and Ephlal became the father of Obed, </text>
    <verse num="38" />
    <text>and Obed became the father of Jehu, and Jehu became the father of Azariah, </text>
    <verse num="39" />
    <text>and Azariah became the father of Helez, and Helez became the father of Eleasah, </text>
    <verse num="40" />
    <text>and Eleasah became the father of Sismai, and Sismai became the father of Shallum, </text>
    <verse num="41" />
    <text>and Shallum became the father of Jekamiah, and Jekamiah became the father of Elishama.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="42" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="42" />
    <text>The sons of Caleb the brother of Jerahmeel were Mesha his firstborn, who was the father of Ziph; and the sons of Mareshah the father of Hebron.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="43" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="43" />
    <text>The sons of Hebron: Korah, and Tappuah, and Rekem, and Shema.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="44" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="44" />
    <text>Shema became the father of Raham, the father of Jorkeam; and Rekem became the father of Shammai.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="45" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="45" />
    <text>The son of Shammai was Maon; and Maon was the father of Beth Zur.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="46" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="46" />
    <text>Ephah, Caleb's concubine, bore Haran, and Moza, and Gazez; and Haran became the father of Gazez.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="47" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="47" />
    <text>The sons of Jahdai: Regem, and Jothan, and Geshan, and Pelet, and Ephah, and Shaaph.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="48" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="48" />
    <text>Maacah, Caleb's concubine, bore Sheber and Tirhanah.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="49" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="49" />
    <text>She bore also Shaaph the father of Madmannah, Sheva the father of Machbena, and the father of Gibea; and the daughter of Caleb was Achsah.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="50" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="50" />
    <text>These were the sons of Caleb, the son of Hur, the firstborn of Ephrathah: Shobal the father of Kiriath Jearim, </text>
    <verse num="51" />
    <text>Salma the father of Bethlehem, Hareph the father of Beth Gader.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="52" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="52" />
    <text>Shobal the father of Kiriath Jearim had sons: Haroeh, half of the Menuhoth.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="53" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="53" />
    <text>The families of Kiriath Jearim: The Ithrites, and the Puthites, and the Shumathites, and the Mishraites; of them came the Zorathites and the Eshtaolites.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="54" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="54" />
    <text>The sons of Salma: Bethlehem, and the Netophathites, Atroth Beth Joab, and half of the Manahathites, the Zorites.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="55" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="55" />
    <text>The families of scribes who lived at Jabez: the Tirathites, the Shimeathites, the Sucathites. These are the Kenites who came of Hammath, the father of the house of Rechab.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" book="1CH" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1CH">
    <text>3</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Now these were the sons of David, who were born to him in Hebron: the firstborn, Amnon, of Ahinoam the Jezreelitess; the second, Daniel, of Abigail the Carmelitess;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>the third, Absalom the son of Maacah the daughter of Talmai king of Geshur; the fourth, Adonijah the son of Haggith;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>the fifth, Shephatiah of Abital; the sixth, Ithream by Eglah his wife:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>six were born to him in Hebron; and there he reigned seven years and six months. In Jerusalem he reigned thirty-three years;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>and these were born to him in Jerusalem: Shimea, and Shobab, and Nathan, and Solomon, four, of Bathshua the daughter of Ammiel;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>and Ibhar, and Elishama, and Eliphelet, </text>
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>and Nogah, and Nepheg, and Japhia, </text>
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>and Elishama, and Eliada, and Eliphelet, nine.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>All these were the sons of David, besides the sons of the concubines; and Tamar was their sister.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>Solomon's son was Rehoboam, Abijah his son, Asa his son, Jehoshaphat his son, </text>
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>Joram his son, Ahaziah his son, Joash his son, </text>
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>Amaziah his son, Azariah his son, Jotham his son, </text>
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>Ahaz his son, Hezekiah his son, Manasseh his son, </text>
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>Amon his son, Josiah his son.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>The sons of Josiah: the firstborn Johanan, the second Jehoiakim, the third Zedekiah, the fourth Shallum.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>The sons of Jehoiakim: Jeconiah his son, Zedekiah his son.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>The sons of Jeconiah, the captive: Shealtiel his son, </text>
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>and Malchiram, and Pedaiah, and Shenazzar, Jekamiah, Hoshama, and Nedabiah.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>The sons of Pedaiah: Zerubbabel, and Shimei. The sons of Zerubbabel: Meshullam, and Hananiah; and Shelomith was their sister;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>and Hashubah, and Ohel, and Berechiah, and Hasadiah, Jushab Hesed, five.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>The sons of Hananiah: Pelatiah, and Jeshaiah; the sons of Rephaiah, the sons of Arnan, the sons of Obadiah, the sons of Shecaniah.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>The sons of Shecaniah: Shemaiah. The sons of Shemaiah: Hattush, and Igal, and Bariah, and Neariah, and Shaphat, six.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>The sons of Neariah: Elioenai, and Hizkiah, and Azrikam, three.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="24" />
    <text>The sons of Elioenai: Hodaviah, and Eliashib, and Pelaiah, and Akkub, and Johanan, and Delaiah, and Anani, seven.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" book="1CH" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1CH">
    <text>4</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>The sons of Judah: Perez, Hezron, and Carmi, and Hur, and Shobal.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>Reaiah the son of Shobal became the father of Jahath; and Jahath became the father of Ahumai and Lahad. These are the families of the Zorathites.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>These were [the sons of] the father of Etam: Jezreel, and Ishma, and Idbash; and the name of their sister was Hazzelelponi;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>and Penuel the father of Gedor, and Ezer the father of Hushah. These are the sons of Hur, the firstborn of Ephrathah, the father of Bethlehem.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>Ashhur the father of Tekoa had two wives, Helah and Naarah.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>Naarah bore him Ahuzzam, and Hepher, and Temeni, and Haahashtari. These were the sons of Naarah.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>The sons of Helah were Zereth, Izhar, and Ethnan.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>Hakkoz became the father of Anub, and Zobebah, and the families of Aharhel the son of Harum.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>Jabez was more honorable than his brothers: and his mother named him Jabez, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="Jabez's mother">
    <text>«Because I bore him with sorrow.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>Jabez called on the God of Israel, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="Jabez">
    <text>«Oh that you would bless me indeed, and enlarge my border, and that your hand might be with me, and that you would keep me from evil, that it not be to my sorrow!»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <text>God granted him that which he requested.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>Chelub the brother of Shuhah became the father of Mehir, who was the father of Eshton.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>Eshton became the father of Beth Rapha, and Paseah, and Tehinnah the father of Ir Nahash. These are the men of Recah.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>The sons of Kenaz: Othniel, and Seraiah. The sons of Othniel: Hathath.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>Meonothai became the father of Ophrah: and Seraiah became the father of Joab the father of Ge Harashim; for they were craftsmen.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>The sons of Caleb the son of Jephunneh: Iru, Elah, and Naam; and the sons of Elah; and Kenaz.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>The sons of Jehallelel: Ziph, and Ziphah, Tiria, and Asarel.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>The sons of Ezrah: Jether, and Mered, and Epher, and Jalon; and she bore Miriam, and Shammai, and Ishbah the father of Eshtemoa.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>His wife the Jewess bore Jered the father of Gedor, and Heber the father of Soco, and Jekuthiel the father of Zanoah. These are the sons of Bithiah the daughter of Pharaoh, whom Mered took.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>The sons of the wife of Hodiah, the sister of Naham, were the father of Keilah the Garmite, and Eshtemoa the Maacathite.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>The sons of Shimon: Amnon, and Rinnah, Ben Hanan, and Tilon. The sons of Ishi: Zoheth, and Ben Zoheth.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>The sons of Shelah the son of Judah: Er the father of Lecah, and Laadah the father of Mareshah, and the families of the house of those who worked fine linen, of the house of Ashbea;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>and Jokim, and the men of Cozeba, and Joash, and Saraph, who had dominion in Moab, and Jashubilehem. The records are ancient.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>These were the potters, and the inhabitants of Netaim and Gederah: there they lived with the king for his work.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="24" />
    <text>The sons of Simeon: Nemuel, and Jamin, Jarib, Zerah, Shaul;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="25" />
    <text>Shallum his son, Mibsam his son, Mishma his son.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="26" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="26" />
    <text>The sons of Mishma: Hammuel his son, Zaccur his son, Shimei his son.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="27" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="27" />
    <text>Shimei had sixteen sons and six daughters; but his brothers didn't have many children, neither did all their family multiply like the children of Judah.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="28" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="28" />
    <text>They lived at Beersheba, and Moladah, and Hazarshual, </text>
    <verse num="29" />
    <text>and at Bilhah, and at Ezem, and at Tolad, </text>
    <verse num="30" />
    <text>and at Bethuel, and at Hormah, and at Ziklag, </text>
    <verse num="31" />
    <text>and at Beth Marcaboth, and Hazar Susim, and at Beth Biri, and at Shaaraim. These were their cities to the reign of David.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="32" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="32" />
    <text>Their villages were Etam, and Ain, Rimmon, and Tochen, and Ashan, five cities;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="33" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="33" />
    <text>and all their villages that were around the same cities, to Baal. These were their habitations, and they have their genealogy.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="34" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="34" />
    <text>Meshobab, and Jamlech, and Joshah the son of Amaziah, </text>
    <verse num="35" />
    <text>and Joel, and Jehu the son of Joshibiah, the son of Seraiah, the son of Asiel, </text>
    <verse num="36" />
    <text>and Elioenai, and Jaakobah, and Jeshohaiah, and Asaiah, and Adiel, and Jesimiel, and Benaiah, </text>
    <verse num="37" />
    <text>and Ziza the son of Shiphi, the son of Allon, the son of Jedaiah, the son of Shimri, the son of Shemaiah--</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="38" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="38" />
    <text>these mentioned by name were princes in their families: and their fathers' houses increased greatly.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="39" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="39" />
    <text>They went to the entrance of Gedor, even to the east side of the valley, to seek pasture for their flocks.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="40" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="40" />
    <text>They found fat pasture and good, and the land was wide, and quiet, and peaceable; for those who lived there before were of Ham.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="41" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="41" />
    <text>These written by name came in the days of Hezekiah king of Judah, and struck their tents, and the Meunim who were found there, and destroyed them utterly to this day, and lived in their place; because there was pasture there for their flocks.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="42" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="42" />
    <text>Some of them, even of the sons of Simeon, five hundred men, went to Mount Seir, having for their captains Pelatiah, and Neariah, and Rephaiah, and Uzziel, the sons of Ishi.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="43" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="43" />
    <text>They struck the remnant of the Amalekites who escaped, and have lived there to this day.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" book="1CH" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1CH">
    <text>5</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>The sons of Reuben the firstborn of Israel (for he was the firstborn; but, because he defiled his father's couch, his birthright was given to the sons of Joseph the son of Israel; and the genealogy is not to be reckoned after the birthright.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>For Judah prevailed above his brothers, and of him came the prince; but the birthright was Joseph's:)</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>the sons of Reuben the firstborn of Israel: Hanoch, and Pallu, Hezron, and Carmi.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>The sons of Joel: Shemaiah his son, Gog his son, Shimei his son, </text>
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>Micah his son, Reaiah his son, Baal his son, </text>
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>Beerah his son, whom Tilgath Pilneser king of Assyria carried away captive: he was prince of the Reubenites.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>His brothers by their families, when the genealogy of their generations was reckoned: the chief, Jeiel, and Zechariah, </text>
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>and Bela the son of Azaz, the son of Shema, the son of Joel, who lived in Aroer, even to Nebo and Baal Meon:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>and eastward he lived even to the entrance of the wilderness from the river Euphrates, because their livestock were multiplied in the land of Gilead.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>In the days of Saul, they made war with the Hagrites, who fell by their hand; and they lived in their tents throughout all the [land] east of Gilead.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>The sons of Gad lived over against them, in the land of Bashan to Salecah:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>Joel the chief, and Shapham the second, and Janai, and Shaphat in Bashan.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>Their brothers of their fathers' houses: Michael, and Meshullam, and Sheba, and Jorai, and Jacan, and Zia, and Eber, seven.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>These were the sons of Abihail, the son of Huri, the son of Jaroah, the son of Gilead, the son of Michael, the son of Jeshishai, the son of Jahdo, the son of Buz;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>Ahi the son of Abdiel, the son of Guni, chief of their fathers' houses.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>They lived in Gilead in Bashan, and in its towns, and in all the suburbs of Sharon, as far as their borders.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>All these were reckoned by genealogies in the days of Jotham king of Judah, and in the days of Jeroboam king of Israel.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>The sons of Reuben, and the Gadites, and the half-tribe of Manasseh, of valiant men, men able to bear buckler and sword, and to shoot with bow, and skillful in war, were forty-four thousand seven hundred and sixty, that were able to go forth to war.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>They made war with the Hagrites, with Jetur, and Naphish, and Nodab.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>They were helped against them, and the Hagrites were delivered into their hand, and all who were with them; for they cried to God in the battle, and he was entreated of them, because they put their trust in him.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>They took away their livestock; of their camels fifty thousand, and of sheep two hundred fifty thousand, and of donkeys two thousand, and of men one hundred thousand.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>For there fell many slain, because the war was of God. They lived in their place until the captivity.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>The children of the half-tribe of Manasseh lived in the land: they increased from Bashan to Baal Hermon and Senir and Mount Hermon.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="24" />
    <text>These were the heads of their fathers' houses: even Epher, and Ishi, and Eliel, and Azriel, and Jeremiah, and Hodaviah, and Jahdiel, mighty men of valor, famous men, heads of their fathers' houses.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="25" />
    <text>They trespassed against the God of their fathers, and played the prostitute after the gods of the peoples of the land, whom God destroyed before them.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="26" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="26" />
    <text>The God of Israel stirred up the spirit of Pul king of Assyria, and the spirit of Tilgath Pilneser king of Assyria, and he carried them away, even the Reubenites, and the Gadites, and the half-tribe of Manasseh, and brought them to Halah, and Habor, and Hara, and to the river of Gozan, to this day.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="6" book="1CH" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1CH">
    <text>6</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>The sons of Levi: Gershon, Kohath, and Merari.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>The sons of Kohath: Amram, Izhar, and Hebron, and Uzziel.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>The children of Amram: Aaron, and Moses, and Miriam. The sons of Aaron: Nadab, and Abihu, Eleazar, and Ithamar.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>Eleazar became the father of Phinehas, Phinehas became the father of Abishua, </text>
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>and Abishua became the father of Bukki, and Bukki became the father of Uzzi, </text>
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>and Uzzi became the father of Zerahiah, and Zerahiah became the father of Meraioth, </text>
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>Meraioth became the father of Amariah, and Amariah became the father of Ahitub, </text>
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>and Ahitub became the father of Zadok, and Zadok became the father of Ahimaaz, </text>
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>and Ahimaaz became the father of Azariah, and Azariah became the father of Johanan, </text>
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>and Johanan became the father of Azariah, (he it is who executed the priest's office in the house that Solomon built in Jerusalem), </text>
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>and Azariah became the father of Amariah, and Amariah became the father of Ahitub, </text>
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>and Ahitub became the father of Zadok, and Zadok became the father of Shallum, </text>
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>and Shallum became the father of Hilkiah, and Hilkiah became the father of Azariah, </text>
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>and Azariah became the father of Seraiah, and Seraiah became the father of Jehozadak;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>Jehozadak went [into captivity], when God carried away Judah and Jerusalem by the hand of Nebuchadnezzar.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>The sons of Levi: Gershom, Kohath, and Merari.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>These are the names of the sons of Gershom: Libni and Shimei.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>The sons of Kohath were Amram, and Izhar, and Hebron, and Uzziel.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>The sons of Merari: Mahli and Mushi. These are the families of the Levites according to their fathers' [houses].</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>Of Gershom: Libni his son, Jahath his son, Zimmah his son, </text>
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>Joah his son, Iddo his son, Zerah his son, Jeatherai his son.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>The sons of Kohath: Amminadab his son, Korah his son, Assir his son, </text>
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>Elkanah his son, and Ebiasaph his son, and Assir his son, </text>
    <verse num="24" />
    <text>Tahath his son, Uriel his son, Uzziah his son, and Shaul his son.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="25" />
    <text>The sons of Elkanah: Amasai, and Ahimoth.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="26" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="26" />
    <text>As for Elkanah, the sons of Elkanah: Zophai his son, and Nahath his son, </text>
    <verse num="27" />
    <text>Eliab his son, Jeroham his son, Elkanah his son.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="28" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="28" />
    <text>The sons of Samuel: the firstborn [Joel], and the second Abijah.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="29" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="29" />
    <text>The sons of Merari: Mahli, Libni his son, Shimei his son, Uzzah his son, </text>
    <verse num="30" />
    <text>Shimea his son, Haggiah his son, Asaiah his son.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="31" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="31" />
    <text>These are they whom David set over the service of song in the house of God, after that the ark had rest.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="32" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="32" />
    <text>They ministered with song before the tabernacle of the Tent of Meeting, until Solomon had built the house of God in Jerusalem: and they waited on their office according to their order.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="33" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="33" />
    <text>These are those who waited, and their sons. Of the sons of the Kohathites: Heman the singer, the son of Joel, the son of Samuel, </text>
    <verse num="34" />
    <text>the son of Elkanah, the son of Jeroham, the son of Eliel, the son of Toah, </text>
    <verse num="35" />
    <text>the son of Zuph, the son of Elkanah, the son of Mahath, the son of Amasai, </text>
    <verse num="36" />
    <text>the son of Elkanah, the son of Joel, the son of Azariah, the son of Zephaniah, </text>
    <verse num="37" />
    <text>the son of Tahath, the son of Assir, the son of Ebiasaph, the son of Korah, </text>
    <verse num="38" />
    <text>the son of Izhar, the son of Kohath, the son of Levi, the son of Israel.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="39" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="39" />
    <text>His brother Asaph, who stood on his right hand, even Asaph the son of Berechiah, the son of Shimea, </text>
    <verse num="40" />
    <text>the son of Michael, the son of Baaseiah, the son of Malchijah, </text>
    <verse num="41" />
    <text>the son of Ethni, the son of Zerah, the son of Adaiah, </text>
    <verse num="42" />
    <text>the son of Ethan, the son of Zimmah, the son of Shimei, </text>
    <verse num="43" />
    <text>the son of Jahath, the son of Gershom, the son of Levi.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="44" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="44" />
    <text>On the left hand their brothers the sons of Merari: Ethan the son of Kishi, the son of Abdi, the son of Malluch, </text>
    <verse num="45" />
    <text>the son of Hashabiah, the son of Amaziah, the son of Hilkiah, </text>
    <verse num="46" />
    <text>the son of Amzi, the son of Bani, the son of Shemer, </text>
    <verse num="47" />
    <text>the son of Mahli, the son of Mushi, the son of Merari, the son of Levi.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="48" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="48" />
    <text>Their brothers the Levites were appointed for all the service of the tabernacle of the house of God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="49" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="49" />
    <text>But Aaron and his sons offered on the altar of burnt offering, and on the altar of incense, for all the work of the most holy place, and to make atonement for Israel, according to all that Moses the servant of God had commanded.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="50" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="50" />
    <text>These are the sons of Aaron: Eleazar his son, Phinehas his son, Abishua his son, </text>
    <verse num="51" />
    <text>Bukki his son, Uzzi his son, Zerahiah his son, </text>
    <verse num="52" />
    <text>Meraioth his son, Amariah his son, Ahitub his son, </text>
    <verse num="53" />
    <text>Zadok his son, Ahimaaz his son.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="54" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="54" />
    <text>Now these are their dwelling places according to their encampments in their borders: to the sons of Aaron, of the families of the Kohathites (for theirs was the [first] lot), </text>
    <verse num="55" />
    <text>to them they gave Hebron in the land of Judah, and its suburbs around it;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="56" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="56" />
    <text>but the fields of the city, and its villages, they gave to Caleb the son of Jephunneh.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="57" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="57" />
    <text>To the sons of Aaron they gave the cities of refuge, Hebron; Libnah also with its suburbs, and Jattir, and Eshtemoa with its suburbs, </text>
    <verse num="58" />
    <text>and Hilen with its suburbs, Debir with its suburbs, </text>
    <verse num="59" />
    <text>and Ashan with its suburbs, and Beth Shemesh with its suburbs;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="60" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="60" />
    <text>and out of the tribe of Benjamin, Geba with its suburbs, and Allemeth with its suburbs, and Anathoth with its suburbs. All their cities throughout their families were thirteen cities.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="61" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="61" />
    <text>To the rest of the sons of Kohath [were given] by lot, out of the family of the tribe, out of the half-tribe, the half of Manasseh, ten cities.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="62" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="62" />
    <text>To the sons of Gershom, according to their families, out of the tribe of Issachar, and out of the tribe of Asher, and out of the tribe of Naphtali, and out of the tribe of Manasseh in Bashan, thirteen cities.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="63" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="63" />
    <text>To the sons of Merari [were given] by lot, according to their families, out of the tribe of Reuben, and out of the tribe of Gad, and out of the tribe of Zebulun, twelve cities.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="64" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="64" />
    <text>The children of Israel gave to the Levites the cities with their suburbs.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="65" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="65" />
    <text>They gave by lot out of the tribe of the children of Judah, and out of the tribe of the children of Simeon, and out of the tribe of the children of Benjamin, these cities which are mentioned by name.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="66" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="66" />
    <text>Some of the families of the sons of Kohath had cities of their borders out of the tribe of Ephraim.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="67" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="67" />
    <text>They gave to them the cities of refuge, Shechem in the hill country of Ephraim with its suburbs; Gezer also with its suburbs, </text>
    <verse num="68" />
    <text>and Jokmeam with its suburbs, and Beth Horon with its suburbs, </text>
    <verse num="69" />
    <text>and Aijalon with its suburbs, and Gath Rimmon with its suburbs;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="70" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="70" />
    <text>and out of the half-tribe of Manasseh, Aner with its suburbs, and Bileam with its suburbs, for the rest of the family of the sons of Kohath.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="71" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="71" />
    <text>To the sons of Gershom [were given], out of the family of the half-tribe of Manasseh, Golan in Bashan with its suburbs, and Ashtaroth with its suburbs;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="72" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="72" />
    <text>and out of the tribe of Issachar, Kedesh with its suburbs, Daberath with its suburbs, </text>
    <verse num="73" />
    <text>and Ramoth with its suburbs, and Anem with its suburbs;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="74" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="74" />
    <text>and out of the tribe of Asher, Mashal with its suburbs, and Abdon with its suburbs, </text>
    <verse num="75" />
    <text>and Hukok with its suburbs, and Rehob with its suburbs;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="76" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="76" />
    <text>and out of the tribe of Naphtali, Kedesh in Galilee with its suburbs, and Hammon with its suburbs, and Kiriathaim with its suburbs.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="77" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="77" />
    <text>To the rest of [the Levites], the sons of Merari, [were given], out of the tribe of Zebulun, Rimmono with its suburbs, Tabor with its suburbs;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="78" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="78" />
    <text>and beyond the Jordan at Jericho, on the east side of the Jordan, [were given them], out of the tribe of Reuben, Bezer in the wilderness with its suburbs, and Jahzah with its suburbs, </text>
    <verse num="79" />
    <text>and Kedemoth with its suburbs, and Mephaath with its suburbs; </text>
    <verse num="80" />
    <text>and out of the tribe of Gad, Ramoth in Gilead with its suburbs, and Mahanaim with its suburbs, </text>
    <verse num="81" />
    <text>and Heshbon with its suburbs, and Jazer with its suburbs.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="7" book="1CH" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1CH">
    <text>7</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Of the sons of Issachar: Tola, and Puah, Jashub, and Shimron, four.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>The sons of Tola: Uzzi, and Rephaiah, and Jeriel, and Jahmai, and Ibsam, and Shemuel, heads of their fathers' houses, [to wit], of Tola; mighty men of valor in their generations: their number in the days of David was twenty-two thousand six hundred.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>The sons of Uzzi: Izrahiah. The sons of Izrahiah: Michael, and Obadiah, and Joel, Isshiah, five; all of them chief men.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>With them, by their generations, after their fathers' houses, were bands of the army for war, thirty-six thousand; for they had many wives and sons.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>Their brothers among all the families of Issachar, mighty men of valor, reckoned in all by genealogy, were eighty-seven thousand.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>[The sons of] Benjamin: Bela, and Becher, and Jediael, three.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>The sons of Bela: Ezbon, and Uzzi, and Uzziel, and Jerimoth, and Iri, five; heads of fathers' houses, mighty men of valor; and they were reckoned by genealogy twenty-two thousand thirty-four.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>The sons of Becher: Zemirah, and Joash, and Eliezer, and Elioenai, and Omri, and Jeremoth, and Abijah, and Anathoth, and Alemeth. All these were the sons of Becher.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>They were reckoned by genealogy, after their generations, heads of their fathers' houses, mighty men of valor, twenty thousand two hundred.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>The sons of Jediael: Bilhan. The sons of Bilhan: Jeush, and Benjamin, and Ehud, and Chenaanah, and Zethan, and Tarshish, and Ahishahar.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>All these were sons of Jediael, according to the heads of their fathers' [houses], mighty men of valor, seventeen thousand and two hundred, who were able to go forth in the army for war.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>Shuppim also, and Huppim, the sons of Ir, Hushim, the sons of Aher.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>The sons of Naphtali: Jahziel, and Guni, and Jezer, and Shallum, the sons of Bilhah.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>The sons of Manasseh: Asriel, whom his concubine the Aramitess bore: she bore Machir the father of Gilead:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>and Machir took a wife of Huppim and Shuppim, whose sister's name was Maacah; and the name of the second was Zelophehad: and Zelophehad had daughters.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>Maacah the wife of Machir bore a son, and she named him Peresh; and the name of his brother was Sheresh; and his sons were Ulam and Rakem.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>The sons of Ulam: Bedan. These were the sons of Gilead the son of Machir, the son of Manasseh.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>His sister Hammolecheth bore Ishhod, and Abiezer, and Mahlah.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>The sons of Shemida were Ahian, and Shechem, and Likhi, and Aniam.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>The sons of Ephraim: Shuthelah, and Bered his son, and Tahath his son, and Eleadah his son, and Tahath his son, </text>
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>and Zabad his son, and Shuthelah his son, and Ezer, and Elead, whom the men of Gath who were born in the land killed, because they came down to take away their livestock.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>Ephraim their father mourned many days, and his brothers came to comfort him.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>He went in to his wife, and she conceived, and bore a son, and he named him Beriah, because it went evil with his house.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="24" />
    <text>His daughter was Sheerah, who built Beth Horon the lower and the upper, and Uzzen Sheerah.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="25" />
    <text>Rephah was his son, and Resheph, and Telah his son, and Tahan his son, </text>
    <verse num="26" />
    <text>Ladan his son, Ammihud his son, Elishama his son, </text>
    <verse num="27" />
    <text>Nun his son, Joshua his son.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="28" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="28" />
    <text>Their possessions and habitations were Bethel and its towns, and eastward Naaran, and westward Gezer, with its towns; Shechem also and its towns, to Azzah and its towns;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="29" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="29" />
    <text>and by the borders of the children of Manasseh, Beth Shean and its towns, Taanach and its towns, Megiddo and its towns, Dor and its towns. In these lived the children of Joseph the son of Israel.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="30" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="30" />
    <text>The sons of Asher: Imnah, and Ishvah, and Ishvi, and Beriah, and Serah their sister.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="31" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="31" />
    <text>The sons of Beriah: Heber, and Malchiel, who was the father of Birzaith.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="32" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="32" />
    <text>Heber became the father of Japhlet, and Shomer, and Hotham, and Shua their sister.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="33" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="33" />
    <text>The sons of Japhlet: Pasach, and Bimhal, and Ashvath. These are the children of Japhlet.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="34" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="34" />
    <text>The sons of Shemer: Ahi, and Rohgah, Jehubbah, and Aram.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="35" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="35" />
    <text>The sons of Helem his brother: Zophah, and Imna, and Shelesh, and Amal.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="36" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="36" />
    <text>The sons of Zophah: Suah, and Harnepher, and Shual, and Beri, and Imrah, </text>
    <verse num="37" />
    <text>Bezer, and Hod, and Shamma, and Shilshah, and Ithran, and Beera.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="38" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="38" />
    <text>The sons of Jether: Jephunneh, and Pispa, and Ara.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="39" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="39" />
    <text>The sons of Ulla: Arah, and Hanniel, and Rizia.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="40" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="40" />
    <text>All these were the children of Asher, heads of the fathers' houses, choice and mighty men of valor, chief of the princes. The number of them reckoned by genealogy for service in war was twenty-six thousand men.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="8" book="1CH" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1CH">
    <text>8</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Benjamin became the father of Bela his firstborn, Ashbel the second, and Aharah the third, </text>
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>Nohah the fourth, and Rapha the fifth.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>Bela had sons: Addar, and Gera, and Abihud, </text>
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>and Abishua, and Naaman, and Ahoah, </text>
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>and Gera, and Shephuphan, and Huram.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>These are the sons of Ehud: these are the heads of fathers' [houses] of the inhabitants of Geba, and they carried them captive to Manahath:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>and Naaman, and Ahijah, and Gera, he carried them captive: and he became the father of Uzza and Ahihud.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>Shaharaim became the father of children in the field of Moab, after he had sent them away; Hushim and Baara were his wives.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>He became the father of Hodesh his wife, Jobab, and Zibia, and Mesha, and Malcam, </text>
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>and Jeuz, and Shachia, and Mirmah. These were his sons, heads of fathers' [houses].</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>Of Hushim he became the father of Abitub and Elpaal.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>The sons of Elpaal: Eber, and Misham, and Shemed, who built Ono and Lod, with its towns;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>and Beriah, and Shema, who were heads of fathers' [houses] of the inhabitants of Aijalon, who put to flight the inhabitants of Gath;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>and Ahio, Shashak, and Jeremoth, </text>
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>and Zebadiah, and Arad, and Eder, </text>
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>and Michael, and Ishpah, and Joha, the sons of Beriah, </text>
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>and Zebadiah, and Meshullam, and Hizki, and Heber, </text>
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>and Ishmerai, and Izliah, and Jobab, the sons of Elpaal, </text>
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>and Jakim, and Zichri, and Zabdi, </text>
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>and Elienai, and Zillethai, and Eliel, </text>
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>and Adaiah, and Beraiah, and Shimrath, the sons of Shimei, </text>
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>and Ishpan, and Eber, and Eliel, </text>
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>and Abdon, and Zichri, and Hanan, </text>
    <verse num="24" />
    <text>and Hananiah, and Elam, and Anthothijah, </text>
    <verse num="25" />
    <text>and Iphdeiah, and Penuel, the sons of Shashak, </text>
    <verse num="26" />
    <text>and Shamsherai, and Shehariah, and Athaliah, </text>
    <verse num="27" />
    <text>and Jaareshiah, and Elijah, and Zichri, the sons of Jeroham.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="28" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="28" />
    <text>These were heads of fathers' [houses] throughout their generations, chief men: these lived in Jerusalem.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="29" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="29" />
    <text>In Gibeon there lived the father of Gibeon, [Jeiel], whose wife's name was Maacah;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="30" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="30" />
    <text>and his firstborn son Abdon, and Zur, and Kish, and Baal, and Nadab, </text>
    <verse num="31" />
    <text>and Gedor, and Ahio, and Zecher.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="32" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="32" />
    <text>Mikloth became the father of Shimeah. They also lived with their brothers in Jerusalem, over against their brothers.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="33" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="33" />
    <text>Ner became the father of Kish; and Kish became the father of Saul; and Saul became the father of Jonathan, and Malchishua, and Abinadab, and Eshbaal.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="34" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="34" />
    <text>The son of Jonathan was Merib Baal; and Merib Baal became the father of Micah.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="35" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="35" />
    <text>The sons of Micah: Pithon, and Melech, and Tarea, and Ahaz.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="36" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="36" />
    <text>Ahaz became the father of Jehoaddah; and Jehoaddah became the father of Alemeth, and Azmaveth, and Zimri; and Zimri became the father of Moza.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="37" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="37" />
    <text>Moza became the father of Binea; Raphah was his son, Eleasah his son, Azel his son.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="38" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="38" />
    <text>Azel had six sons, whose names are these: Azrikam, Bocheru, and Ishmael, and Sheariah, and Obadiah, and Hanan. All these were the sons of Azel.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="39" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="39" />
    <text>The sons of Eshek his brother: Ulam his firstborn, Jeush the second, and Eliphelet the third.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="40" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="40" />
    <text>The sons of Ulam were mighty men of valor, archers, and had many sons, and sons' sons, one hundred fifty. All these were of the sons of Benjamin.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="9" book="1CH" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1CH">
    <text>9</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>So all Israel were reckoned by genealogies; and behold, they are written in the book of the kings of Israel: and Judah was carried away captive to Babylon for their disobedience.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>Now the first inhabitants who lived in their possessions in their cities were Israel, the priests, the Levites, and the Nethinim.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>In Jerusalem lived of the children of Judah, and of the children of Benjamin, and of the children of Ephraim and Manasseh:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>Uthai the son of Ammihud, the son of Omri, the son of Imri, the son of Bani, of the children of Perez the son of Judah.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>Of the Shilonites: Asaiah the firstborn, and his sons.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>Of the sons of Zerah: Jeuel, and their brothers, six hundred ninety.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>Of the sons of Benjamin: Sallu the son of Meshullam, the son of Hodaviah, the son of Hassenuah, </text>
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>and Ibneiah the son of Jeroham, and Elah the son of Uzzi, the son of Michri, and Meshullam the son of Shephatiah, the son of Reuel, the son of Ibnijah;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>and their brothers, according to their generations, nine hundred fifty-six. All these men were heads of fathers' [houses] by their fathers' houses.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>Of the priests: Jedaiah, and Jehoiarib, Jachin, </text>
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>and Azariah the son of Hilkiah, the son of Meshullam, the son of Zadok, the son of Meraioth, the son of Ahitub, the ruler of the house of God;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>and Adaiah the son of Jeroham, the son of Pashhur, the son of Malchijah, and Maasai the son of Adiel, the son of Jahzerah, the son of Meshullam, the son of Meshillemith, the son of Immer;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>and their brothers, heads of their fathers' houses, one thousand seven hundred sixty; very able men for the work of the service of the house of God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>Of the Levites: Shemaiah the son of Hasshub, the son of Azrikam, the son of Hashabiah, of the sons of Merari;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>and Bakbakkar, Heresh, and Galal, and Mattaniah the son of Mica, the son of Zichri, the son of Asaph, </text>
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>and Obadiah the son of Shemaiah, the son of Galal, the son of Jeduthun, and Berechiah the son of Asa, the son of Elkanah, who lived in the villages of the Netophathites.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>The porters: Shallum, and Akkub, and Talmon, and Ahiman, and their brothers (Shallum was the chief), </text>
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>who hitherto [waited] in the king's gate eastward: they were the porters for the camp of the children of Levi.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>Shallum the son of Kore, the son of Ebiasaph, the son of Korah, and his brothers, of his father's house, the Korahites, were over the work of the service, keepers of the thresholds of the tent: and their fathers had been over the camp of God, keepers of the entry.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>Phinehas the son of Eleazar was ruler over them in time past, [and] God was with him.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>Zechariah the son of Meshelemiah was porter of the door of the Tent of Meeting.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>All these who were chosen to be porters in the thresholds were two hundred and twelve. These were reckoned by genealogy in their villages, whom David and Samuel the seer did ordain in their office of trust.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>So they and their children had the oversight of the gates of the house of God, even the house of the tent, by wards.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="24" />
    <text>On the four sides were the porters, toward the east, west, north, and south.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="25" />
    <text>Their brothers, in their villages, were to come in every seven days from time to time to be with them:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="26" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="26" />
    <text>for the four chief porters, who were Levites, were in an office of trust, and were over the rooms and over the treasuries in the house of God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="27" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="27" />
    <text>They lodged around the house of God, because that duty was on them; and to them pertained its opening morning by morning.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="28" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="28" />
    <text>Certain of them were in charge of the vessels of service; for by count were these brought in and by count were these taken out.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="29" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="29" />
    <text>Some of them also were appointed over the furniture, and over all the vessels of the sanctuary, and over the fine flour, and the wine, and the oil, and the frankincense, and the spices.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="30" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="30" />
    <text>Some of the sons of the priests prepared the confection of the spices.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="31" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="31" />
    <text>Mattithiah, one of the Levites, who was the firstborn of Shallum the Korahite, had the office of trust over the things that were baked in pans.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="32" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="32" />
    <text>Some of their brothers, of the sons of the Kohathites, were over the show bread, to prepare it every Sabbath.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="33" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="33" />
    <text>These are the singers, heads of fathers' [houses] of the Levites, [who lived] in the rooms [and were] free [from other service]; for they were employed in their work day and night.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="34" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="34" />
    <text>These were heads of fathers' [houses] of the Levites, throughout their generations, chief men: these lived at Jerusalem.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="35" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="35" />
    <text>In Gibeon there lived the father of Gibeon, Jeiel, whose wife's name was Maacah:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="36" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="36" />
    <text>and his firstborn son Abdon, and Zur, and Kish, and Baal, and Ner, and Nadab, </text>
    <verse num="37" />
    <text>and Gedor, and Ahio, and Zechariah, and Mikloth.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="38" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="38" />
    <text>Mikloth became the father of Shimeam. They also lived with their brothers in Jerusalem, over against their brothers.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="39" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="39" />
    <text>Ner became the father of Kish; and Kish became the father of Saul; and Saul became the father of Jonathan, and Malchishua, and Abinadab, and Eshbaal.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="40" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="40" />
    <text>The son of Jonathan was Merib Baal; and Merib Baal became the father of Micah.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="41" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="41" />
    <text>The sons of Micah: Pithon, and Melech, and Tahrea, [and Ahaz].</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="42" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="42" />
    <text>Ahaz became the father of Jarah; and Jarah became the father of Alemeth, and Azmaveth, and Zimri; and Zimri became the father of Moza;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="43" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="43" />
    <text>and Moza became the father of Binea; and Rephaiah his son, Eleasah his son, Azel his son.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="44" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="44" />
    <text>Azel had six sons, whose names are these: Azrikam, Bocheru, and Ishmael, and Sheariah, and Obadiah, and Hanan: these were the sons of Azel.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="10" book="1CH" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1CH">
    <text>10</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Now the Philistines fought against Israel: and the men of Israel fled from before the Philistines, and fell down slain on Mount Gilboa.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>The Philistines followed hard after Saul and after his sons; and the Philistines killed Jonathan, and Abinadab, and Malchishua, the sons of Saul.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>The battle went hard against Saul, and the archers overtook him; and he was distressed by reason of the archers. </text>
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>Then Saul said to his armor bearer,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="Saul">
    <text>«Draw your sword, and thrust me through with it, lest these uncircumcised come and abuse me.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <text>But his armor bearer would not; for he was terrified. Therefore Saul took his sword, and fell on it.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>When his armor bearer saw that Saul was dead, he likewise fell on his sword, and died.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>So Saul died, and his three sons; and all his house died together.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>When all the men of Israel who were in the valley saw that they fled, and that Saul and his sons were dead, they forsook their cities, and fled; and the Philistines came and lived in them.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>It happened on the next day, when the Philistines came to strip the slain, that they found Saul and his sons fallen on Mount Gilboa.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>They stripped him, and took his head, and his armor, and sent into the land of the Philistines all around, to carry the news to their idols, and to the people.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>They put his armor in the house of their gods, and fastened his head in the house of Dagon.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>When all Jabesh Gilead heard all that the Philistines had done to Saul, </text>
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>all the valiant men arose, and took away the body of Saul, and the bodies of his sons, and brought them to Jabesh, and buried their bones under the oak in Jabesh, and fasted seven days.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>So Saul died for his trespass which he committed against God, because of the word of God, which he didn't keep; and also because he asked counsel of one who had a familiar spirit, to inquire [thereby], </text>
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>and didn't inquire of God: therefore he killed him, and turned the kingdom to David the son of Jesse.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="11" book="1CH" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1CH">
    <text>11</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Then all Israel gathered themselves to David to Hebron, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="Israel, all">
    <text>«Behold, we are your bone and your flesh.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="Israel, all">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>In times past, even when Saul was king, it was you who led out and brought in Israel. God your God said to you, 'You shall be shepherd of my people Israel, and you shall be prince over my people Israel.'»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>So all the elders of Israel came to the king to Hebron; and David made a covenant with them in Hebron before God; and they anointed David king over Israel, according to the word of God by Samuel.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>David and all Israel went to Jerusalem (the same is Jebus); and the Jebusites, the inhabitants of the land, were there. </text>
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>The inhabitants of Jebus said to David,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="Jebusites">
    <text>«You shall not come in here.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <text>Nevertheless David took the stronghold of Zion. The same is the city of David. </text>
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>David said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="David">
    <text>«Whoever strikes the Jebusites first shall be chief and captain.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <text>Joab the son of Zeruiah went up first, and was made chief. </text>
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>David lived in the stronghold; therefore they called it the city of David.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>He built the city all around, from Millo even around; and Joab repaired the rest of the city.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>David grew greater and greater; for God of Armies was with him.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>Now these are the chief of the mighty men whom David had, who showed themselves strong with him in his kingdom, together with all Israel, to make him king, according to the word of God concerning Israel.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>This is the number of the mighty men whom David had: Jashobeam, the son of a Hachmonite, the chief of the thirty; he lifted up his spear against three hundred and killed them at one time.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>After him was Eleazar the son of Dodo, the Ahohite, who was one of the three mighty men.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>He was with David at Pasdammim, and there the Philistines were gathered together to battle, where there was a plot of ground full of barley; and the people fled from before the Philistines.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>They stood in the midst of the plot, and defended it, and killed the Philistines; and God saved them by a great victory.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>Three of the thirty chief men went down to the rock to David, into the cave of Adullam; and the army of the Philistines were encamped in the valley of Rephaim.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>David was then in the stronghold, and the garrison of the Philistines was then in Bethlehem. </text>
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>David longed, and said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="David">
    <text>«Oh that one would give me water to drink of the well of Bethlehem, which is by the gate!»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>The three broke through the army of the Philistines, and drew water out of the well of Bethlehem, that was by the gate, and took it, and brought it to David: but David would not drink of it, but poured it out to God, </text>
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>and said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="David">
    <text>«My God forbid it me, that I should do this! Shall I drink the blood of these men who have put their lives in jeopardy?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <text>For they risked their lives to bring it. Therefore he would not drink it. The three mighty men did these things.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>Abishai, the brother of Joab, he was chief of the three; for he lifted up his spear against three hundred and killed them, and had a name among the three.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>Of the three, he was more honorable than the two, and was made their captain: however he didn't attain to the [first] three.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>Benaiah the son of Jehoiada, the son of a valiant man of Kabzeel, who had done mighty deeds, he killed the two [sons of] Ariel of Moab: he went down also and killed a lion in the midst of a pit in time of snow.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>He killed an Egyptian, a man of great stature, five cubits high; and in the Egyptian's hand was a spear like a weaver's beam; and he went down to him with a staff, and plucked the spear out of the Egyptian's hand, and killed him with his own spear.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="24" />
    <text>These things did Benaiah the son of Jehoiada, and had a name among the three mighty men.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="25" />
    <text>Behold, he was more honorable than the thirty, but he didn't attain to the [first] three: and David set him over his guard.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="26" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="26" />
    <text>Also the mighty men of the armies: Asahel the brother of Joab, Elhanan the son of Dodo of Bethlehem, </text>
    <verse num="27" />
    <text>Shammoth the Harorite, Helez the Pelonite, </text>
    <verse num="28" />
    <text>Ira the son of Ikkesh the Tekoite, Abiezer the Anathothite, </text>
    <verse num="29" />
    <text>Sibbecai the Hushathite, Ilai the Ahohite, </text>
    <verse num="30" />
    <text>Maharai the Netophathite, Heled the son of Baanah the Netophathite, </text>
    <verse num="31" />
    <text>Ithai the son of Ribai of Gibeah of the children of Benjamin, Benaiah the Pirathonite, </text>
    <verse num="32" />
    <text>Hurai of the brooks of Gaash, Abiel the Arbathite, </text>
    <verse num="33" />
    <text>Azmaveth the Baharumite, Eliahba the Shaalbonite, </text>
    <verse num="34" />
    <text>the sons of Hashem the Gizonite, Jonathan the son of Shagee the Hararite, </text>
    <verse num="35" />
    <text>Ahiam the son of Sacar the Hararite, Eliphal the son of Ur, </text>
    <verse num="36" />
    <text>Hepher the Mecherathite, Ahijah the Pelonite, </text>
    <verse num="37" />
    <text>Hezro the Carmelite, Naarai the son of Ezbai, </text>
    <verse num="38" />
    <text>Joel the brother of Nathan, Mibhar the son of Hagri, </text>
    <verse num="39" />
    <text>Zelek the Ammonite, Naharai the Berothite, the armor bearer of Joab the son of Zeruiah, </text>
    <verse num="40" />
    <text>Ira the Ithrite, Gareb the Ithrite, </text>
    <verse num="41" />
    <text>Uriah the Hittite, Zabad the son of Ahlai, </text>
    <verse num="42" />
    <text>Adina the son of Shiza the Reubenite, a chief of the Reubenites, and thirty with him, </text>
    <verse num="43" />
    <text>Hanan the son of Maacah, and Joshaphat the Mithnite, </text>
    <verse num="44" />
    <text>Uzzia the Ashterathite, Shama and Jeiel the sons of Hotham the Aroerite, </text>
    <verse num="45" />
    <text>Jediael the son of Shimri, and Joha his brother, the Tizite, </text>
    <verse num="46" />
    <text>Eliel the Mahavite, and Jeribai, and Joshaviah, the sons of Elnaam, and Ithmah the Moabite, </text>
    <verse num="47" />
    <text>Eliel, and Obed, and Jaasiel the Mezobaite.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="12" book="1CH" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1CH">
    <text>12</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Now these are those who came to David to Ziklag, while he yet kept himself close because of Saul the son of Kish; and they were among the mighty men, his helpers in war.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>They were armed with bows, and could use both the right hand and the left in slinging stones and in shooting arrows from the bow: they were of Saul's brothers of Benjamin.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>The chief was Ahiezer; then Joash, the sons of Shemaah the Gibeathite, and Jeziel, and Pelet, the sons of Azmaveth, and Beracah, and Jehu the Anathothite, </text>
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>and Ishmaiah the Gibeonite, a mighty man among the thirty, and over the thirty, and Jeremiah, and Jahaziel, and Johanan, and Jozabad the Gederathite, </text>
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>Eluzai, and Jerimoth, and Bealiah, and Shemariah, and Shephatiah the Haruphite, </text>
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>Elkanah, and Isshiah, and Azarel, and Joezer, and Jashobeam, the Korahites, </text>
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>and Joelah, and Zebadiah, the sons of Jeroham of Gedor.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>Of the Gadites there separated themselves to David to the stronghold in the wilderness, mighty men of valor, men trained for war, that could handle shield and spear; whose faces were like the faces of lions, and they were as swift as the roes on the mountains;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>Ezer the chief, Obadiah the second, Eliab the third, </text>
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>Mishmannah the fourth, Jeremiah the fifth, </text>
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>Attai the sixth, Eliel the seventh, </text>
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>Johanan the eighth, Elzabad the ninth, </text>
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>Jeremiah the tenth, Machbannai the eleventh.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>These of the sons of Gad were captains of the army: he who was least was equal to one hundred, and the greatest to one thousand.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>These are those who went over the Jordan in the first month, when it had overflowed all its banks; and they put to flight all them of the valleys, both toward the east, and toward the west.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>There came of the children of Benjamin and Judah to the stronghold to David. </text>
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>David went out to meet them, and answered them,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="David">
    <text>«If you have come peaceably to me to help me, my heart shall be knit to you; but if you have come to betray me to my adversaries, since there is no wrong in my hands, may the God of our fathers look thereon, and rebuke it.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>Then the Spirit came on Amasai, who was chief of the thirty, [and he said],</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="Amasai, chief of thirty">
    <text>«We are yours, David, and on your side, you son of Jesse: peace, peace be to you, and peace be to your helpers; for your God helps you.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <text>Then David received them, and made them captains of the band.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>Of Manasseh also there fell away some to David, when he came with the Philistines against Saul to battle; but they didn't help them; for the lords of the Philistines sent him away after consultation, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="Philistine rulers">
    <text>«He will fall away to his master Saul to the jeopardy of our heads.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>As he went to Ziklag, there fell to him of Manasseh, Adnah, and Jozabad, and Jediael, and Michael, and Jozabad, and Elihu, and Zillethai, captains of thousands who were of Manasseh.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>They helped David against the band of rovers: for they were all mighty men of valor, and were captains in the army.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>For from day to day men came to David to help him, until there was a great army, like the army of God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>These are the numbers of the heads of those who were armed for war, who came to David to Hebron, to turn the kingdom of Saul to him, according to the word of God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="24" />
    <text>The children of Judah who bore shield and spear were six thousand and eight hundred, armed for war.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="25" />
    <text>Of the children of Simeon, mighty men of valor for the war, seven thousand and one hundred.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="26" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="26" />
    <text>Of the children of Levi four thousand and six hundred.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="27" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="27" />
    <text>Jehoiada was the leader of [the house of] Aaron; and with him were three thousand and seven hundred, </text>
    <verse num="28" />
    <text>and Zadok, a young man mighty of valor, and of his father's house twenty-two captains.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="29" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="29" />
    <text>Of the children of Benjamin, the brothers of Saul, three thousand: for hitherto the greatest part of them had kept their allegiance to the house of Saul.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="30" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="30" />
    <text>Of the children of Ephraim twenty thousand eight hundred, mighty men of valor, famous men in their fathers' houses.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="31" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="31" />
    <text>Of the half-tribe of Manasseh eighteen thousand, who were mentioned by name, to come and make David king.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="32" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="32" />
    <text>Of the children of Issachar, men who had understanding of the times, to know what Israel ought to do, the heads of them were two hundred; and all their brothers were at their commandment.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="33" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="33" />
    <text>Of Zebulun, such as were able to go out in the army, who could set the battle in array, with all kinds of instruments of war, fifty thousand, and who could order [the battle array, and were] not of double heart.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="34" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="34" />
    <text>Of Naphtali one thousand captains, and with them with shield and spear thirty-seven thousand.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="35" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="35" />
    <text>Of the Danites who could set the battle in array, twenty-eight thousand six hundred.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="36" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="36" />
    <text>Of Asher, such as were able to go out in the army, who could set the battle in array, forty thousand.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="37" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="37" />
    <text>On the other side of the Jordan, of the Reubenites, and the Gadites, and of the half-tribe of Manasseh, with all kinds of instruments of war for the battle, one hundred twenty thousand.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="38" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="38" />
    <text>All these being men of war, who could order the battle array, came with a perfect heart to Hebron, to make David king over all Israel: and all the rest also of Israel were of one heart to make David king.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="39" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="39" />
    <text>They were there with David three days, eating and drinking; for their brothers had made preparation for them.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="40" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="40" />
    <text>Moreover those who were near to them, [even] as far as Issachar and Zebulun and Naphtali, brought bread on donkeys, and on camels, and on mules, and on oxen, food of meal, cakes of figs, and clusters of raisins, and wine, and oil, and cattle, and sheep in abundance: for there was joy in Israel.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="13" book="1CH" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1CH">
    <text>13</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>David consulted with the captains of thousands and of hundreds, even with every leader. </text>
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>David said to all the assembly of Israel,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="David">
    <text>«If it seems good to you, and if it is of God our God, let us send abroad everywhere to our brothers who are left in all the land of Israel, with whom the priests and Levites are in their cities that have suburbs, that they may gather themselves to us;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="David">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>and let us bring again the ark of our God to us. For we didn't seek it in the days of Saul.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>All the assembly said that they would do so; for the thing was right in the eyes of all the people.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>So David assembled all Israel together, from the Shihor [the brook] of Egypt even to the entrance of Hamath, to bring the ark of God from Kiriath Jearim.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>David went up, and all Israel, to Baalah, [that is], to Kiriath Jearim, which belonged to Judah, to bring up from there the ark of God God that sits [above] the cherubim, that is called by the Name.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>They carried the ark of God on a new cart, [and brought it] out of the house of Abinadab: and Uzza and Ahio drove the cart.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>David and all Israel played before God with all their might, even with songs, and with harps, and with stringed instruments, and with tambourines, and with cymbals, and with trumpets.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>When they came to the threshing floor of Chidon, Uzza put forth his hand to hold the ark; for the oxen stumbled.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>The anger of God was kindled against Uzza, and he struck him, because he put forth his hand to the ark; and there he died before God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>David was displeased, because God had broken forth on Uzza; and he called that place Perez Uzza, to this day. </text>
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>David was afraid of God that day, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="David">
    <text>«How shall I bring the ark of God home to me?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>So David didn't move the ark to him into the city of David, but carried it aside into the house of Obed-Edom the Gittite.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>The ark of God remained with the family of Obed-Edom in his house three months: and God blessed the house of Obed-Edom, and all that he had.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="14" book="1CH" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1CH">
    <text>14</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Hiram king of Tyre sent messengers to David, and cedar trees, and masons, and carpenters, to build him a house.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>David perceived that God had established him king over Israel; for his kingdom was exalted on high, for his people Israel's sake.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>David took more wives at Jerusalem; and David became the father of more sons and daughters.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>These are the names of the children whom he had in Jerusalem: Shammua, and Shobab, Nathan, and Solomon, </text>
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>and Ibhar, and Elishua, and Elpelet, </text>
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>and Nogah, and Nepheg, and Japhia, </text>
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>and Elishama, and Beeliada, and Eliphelet.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>When the Philistines heard that David was anointed king over all Israel, all the Philistines went up to seek David: and David heard of it, and went out against them.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>Now the Philistines had come and made a raid in the valley of Rephaim. </text>
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>David inquired of God, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="David" userConfirmed="true">
    <text>«Shall I go up against the Philistines? Will you deliver them into my hand?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <text>God said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="God" userConfirmed="true">
    <text>«Go up; for I will deliver them into your hand.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>So they came up to Baal Perazim, and David struck them there; and David said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="David">
    <text>God has broken my enemies by my hand, like the breach of waters.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <text>Therefore they called the name of that place Baal Perazim. </text>
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>They left their gods there; and David gave commandment, and they were burned with fire.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>The Philistines yet again made a raid in the valley.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>David inquired again of God; and God said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="God">
    <text>«You shall not go up after them. Turn away from them, and come on them over against the mulberry trees.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="God">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>It shall be, when you hear the sound of marching in the tops of the mulberry trees, that then you shall go out to battle; for God has gone out before you to strike the army of the Philistines.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>David did as God commanded him: and they struck the army of the Philistines from Gibeon even to Gezer.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>The fame of David went out into all lands; and God brought the fear of him on all nations.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="15" book="1CH" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1CH">
    <text>15</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>[David] made him houses in the city of David; and he prepared a place for the ark of God, and pitched for it a tent. </text>
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>Then David said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="David">
    <text>«No one ought to carry the ark of God but the Levites. For God has chosen them to carry the ark of God, and to minister to him forever.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>David assembled all Israel at Jerusalem, to bring up the ark of God to its place, which he had prepared for it.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>David gathered together the sons of Aaron, and the Levites:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>of the sons of Kohath, Uriel the chief, and his brothers one hundred twenty;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>of the sons of Merari, Asaiah the chief, and his brothers two hundred twenty;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>of the sons of Gershom, Joel the chief, and his brothers one hundred thirty;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>of the sons of Elizaphan, Shemaiah the chief, and his brothers two hundred;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>of the sons of Hebron, Eliel the chief, and his brothers eighty;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>of the sons of Uzziel, Amminadab the chief, and his brothers one hundred twelve.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>David called for Zadok and Abiathar the priests, and for the Levites, for Uriel, Asaiah, and Joel, Shemaiah, and Eliel, and Amminadab, </text>
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>and said to them,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="David">
    <text>«You are the heads of the fathers' [houses] of the Levites. Sanctify yourselves, both you and your brothers, that you may bring up the ark of God, the God of Israel, to the place that I have prepared for it.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="David">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>For because you didn't carry it at first, God our God made broke out against us, because we didn't seek him according to the ordinance.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>So the priests and the Levites sanctified themselves to bring up the ark of God, the God of Israel.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>The children of the Levites bore the ark of God on their shoulders with the poles thereon, as Moses commanded according to the word of God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>David spoke to the chief of the Levites to appoint their brothers the singers, with instruments of music, stringed instruments and harps and cymbals, sounding aloud and lifting up the voice with joy.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>So the Levites appointed Heman the son of Joel; and of his brothers, Asaph the son of Berechiah; and of the sons of Merari their brothers, Ethan the son of Kushaiah;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>and with them their brothers of the second degree, Zechariah, Ben, and Jaaziel, and Shemiramoth, and Jehiel, and Unni, Eliab, and Benaiah, and Maaseiah, and Mattithiah, and Eliphelehu, and Mikneiah, and Obed-Edom, and Jeiel, the doorkeepers.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>So the singers, Heman, Asaph, and Ethan, [were appointed] with cymbals of brass to sound aloud;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>and Zechariah, and Aziel, and Shemiramoth, and Jehiel, and Unni, and Eliab, and Maaseiah, and Benaiah, with stringed instruments set to Alamoth;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>and Mattithiah, and Eliphelehu, and Mikneiah, and Obed-Edom, and Jeiel, and Azaziah, with harps tuned to the eight-stringed lyre, to lead.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>Chenaniah, chief of the Levites, was over the song: he instructed about the song, because he was skillful.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>Berechiah and Elkanah were doorkeepers for the ark.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="24" />
    <text>Shebaniah, and Joshaphat, and Nethanel, and Amasai, and Zechariah, and Benaiah, and Eliezer, the priests, did blow the trumpets before the ark of God: and Obed-Edom and Jehiah were doorkeepers for the ark.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="25" />
    <text>So David, and the elders of Israel, and the captains over thousands, went to bring up the ark of the covenant of God out of the house of Obed-Edom with joy.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="26" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="26" />
    <text>It happened, when God helped the Levites who bore the ark of the covenant of God, that they sacrificed seven bulls and seven rams.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="27" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="27" />
    <text>David was clothed with a robe of fine linen, and all the Levites who bore the ark, and the singers, and Chenaniah the master of the song [with] the singers: and David had on him an ephod of linen.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="28" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="28" />
    <text>Thus all Israel brought up the ark of the covenant of God with shouting, and with sound of the cornet, and with trumpets, and with cymbals, sounding aloud with stringed instruments and harps.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="29" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="29" />
    <text>It happened, as the ark of the covenant of God came to the city of David, that Michal the daughter of Saul looked out at the window, and saw king David dancing and playing; and she despised him in her heart.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="16" book="1CH" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1CH">
    <text>16</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>They brought in the ark of God, and set it in the midst of the tent that David had pitched for it: and they offered burnt offerings and peace offerings before God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>When David had made an end of offering the burnt offering and the peace offerings, he blessed the people in the name of God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>He dealt to everyone of Israel, both man and woman, to every one a loaf of bread, and a portion [of flesh], and a cake of raisins.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>He appointed certain of the Levites to minister before the ark of God, and to celebrate and to thank and praise God, the God of Israel:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>Asaph the chief, and second to him Zechariah, Jeiel, and Shemiramoth, and Jehiel, and Mattithiah, and Eliab, and Benaiah, and Obed-Edom, and Jeiel, with stringed instruments and with harps; and Asaph with cymbals, sounding aloud;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>and Benaiah and Jahaziel the priests with trumpets continually, before the ark of the covenant of God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>Then on that day David first ordained to give thanks to God, by the hand of Asaph and his brothers.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="David" delivery="psalm">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>Oh give thanks to God. Call on his name. Make his doings known among the peoples.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="David" delivery="psalm">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>Sing to him. Sing praises to him. Tell of all his marvelous works.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="David" delivery="psalm">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>Glory in his holy name. Let the heart of those who seek God rejoice.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="David" delivery="psalm">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>Seek God and his strength. Seek his face forever more.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="David" delivery="psalm">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>Remember his marvelous works that he has done, his wonders, and the judgments of his mouth, </text>
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>you seed of Israel his servant, you children of Jacob, his chosen ones.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="David" delivery="psalm">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>He is God our God. His judgments are in all the earth.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="David" delivery="psalm">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>Remember his covenant forever, the word which he commanded to a thousand generations, </text>
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>[the covenant] which he made with Abraham, his oath to Isaac.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="David" delivery="psalm">
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>He confirmed the same to Jacob for a statute, and to Israel for an everlasting covenant, </text>
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>saying, «I will give you the land of Canaan, The lot of your inheritance,»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="David" delivery="psalm">
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>when you were but a few men in number, yes, very few, and foreigners were in it.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="David" delivery="psalm">
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>They went about from nation to nation, from one kingdom to another people.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="David" delivery="psalm">
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>He allowed no man to do them wrong. Yes, he reproved kings for their sakes, </text>
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>Don't touch my anointed ones! Do my prophets no harm!</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="David" delivery="psalm">
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>Sing to God, all the earth! Display his salvation from day to day.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="David" delivery="psalm">
    <verse num="24" />
    <text>Declare his glory among the nations, and his marvelous works among all the peoples.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="David" delivery="psalm">
    <verse num="25" />
    <text>For great is God, and greatly to be praised. He also is to be feared above all gods.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="26" characterId="David" delivery="psalm">
    <verse num="26" />
    <text>For all the gods of the peoples are idols, but God made the heavens.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="27" characterId="David" delivery="psalm">
    <verse num="27" />
    <text>Honor and majesty are before him. Strength and gladness are in his place.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="28" characterId="David" delivery="psalm">
    <verse num="28" />
    <text>Ascribe to God, you relatives of the peoples, ascribe to God glory and strength!</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="29" characterId="David" delivery="psalm">
    <verse num="29" />
    <text>Ascribe to God the glory due to his name. Bring an offering, and come before him. Worship God in holy array.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="30" characterId="David" delivery="psalm">
    <verse num="30" />
    <text>Tremble before him, all the earth. The world also is established that it can't be moved.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="31" characterId="David" delivery="psalm">
    <verse num="31" />
    <text>Let the heavens be glad, and let the earth rejoice! Let them say among the nations, «God reigns!»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="32" characterId="David" delivery="psalm">
    <verse num="32" />
    <text>Let the sea roar, and its fullness! Let the field exult, and all that is therein!</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="33" characterId="David" delivery="psalm">
    <verse num="33" />
    <text>Then the trees of the forest will sing for joy before God, for he comes to judge the earth.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="34" characterId="David" delivery="psalm">
    <verse num="34" />
    <text>Oh give thanks to God, for he is good, for his loving kindness endures forever. </text>
    <verse num="35" />
    <text>Say, «Save us, God of our salvation! Gather us together and deliver us from the nations, to give thanks to your holy name, to triumph in your praise.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="36" characterId="David" delivery="psalm" userConfirmed="true">
    <verse num="36" />
    <text>Blessed be God, the God of Israel, from everlasting even to everlasting.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="36" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <text>All the people said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="36" characterId="people, all the" userConfirmed="true">
    <text>«Amen,»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="36" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <text>and praised God. </text>
    <verse num="37" />
    <text>So he left there, before the ark of the covenant of God, Asaph and his brothers, to minister before the ark continually, as every day's work required;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="38" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="38" />
    <text>and Obed-Edom with their brothers, sixty-eight; Obed-Edom also the son of Jeduthun and Hosah to be doorkeepers;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="39" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="39" />
    <text>and Zadok the priest, and his brothers the priests, before the tabernacle of God in the high place that was at Gibeon, </text>
    <verse num="40" />
    <text>to offer burnt offerings to God on the altar of burnt offering continually morning and evening, even according to all that is written in the law of God, which he commanded to Israel;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="41" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="41" />
    <text>and with them Heman and Jeduthun, and the rest who were chosen, who were mentioned by name, to give thanks to God, because his loving kindness endures forever;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="42" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="42" />
    <text>and with them Heman and Jeduthun [with] trumpets and cymbals for those that should sound aloud, and [with] instruments for the songs of God; and the sons of Jeduthun to be at the gate.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="43" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="43" />
    <text>All the people departed every man to his house: and David returned to bless his house.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="17" book="1CH" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1CH">
    <text>17</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>It happened, when David lived in his house, that David said to Nathan the prophet,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="David">
    <text>«Behold, I dwell in a house of cedar, but the ark of the covenant of God is under curtains.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>Nathan said to David,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="Nathan">
    <text>«Do all that is in your heart; for God is with you.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>It happened the same night, that the word of God came to Nathan, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="God">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>Go and tell David my servant, 'Thus says God, You shall not build me a house to dwell in;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="God">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>for I have not lived in a house since the day that I brought up Israel, to this day, but have gone from tent to tent, and from one tent to another.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="God">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>In all places in which I have walked with all Israel, did I speak a word with any of the judges of Israel, whom I commanded to be shepherd of my people, saying, 'Why have you not built me a house of cedar?'»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="God">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>Now therefore, you shall tell my servant David, 'Thus says God of Armies, I took you from the sheep pen, from following the sheep, that you should be prince over my people Israel.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="God">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>I have been with you wherever you have gone, and have cut off all your enemies from before you. I will make you a name, like the name of the great ones who are in the earth.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="God">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>I will appoint a place for my people Israel, and will plant them, that they may dwell in their own place, and be moved no more; neither shall the children of wickedness waste them any more, as at the first, </text>
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>and from the day that I commanded judges to be over my people Israel; and I will subdue all your enemies. Moreover I tell you that God will build you a house.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="God">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>It shall happen, when your days are fulfilled that you must go to be with your fathers, that I will set up your seed after you, who shall be of your sons; and I will establish his kingdom.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="God">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>He shall build me a house, and I will establish his throne forever.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="God">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>I will be his father, and he shall be my son. I will not take my loving kindness away from him, as I took it from him that was before you;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="God">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>but I will settle him in my house and in my kingdom forever. His throne shall be established forever.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>According to all these words, and according to all this vision, so Nathan spoke to David. </text>
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>Then David the king went in, and sat before God; and he said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="David">
    <text>«Who am I, God, and what is my house, that you have brought me thus far?</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="David">
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>This was a small thing in your eyes, God; but you have spoken of your servant's house for a great while to come, and have respected me according to the estate of a man of high degree, God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="David">
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>What can David say yet more to you concerning the honor which is done to your servant? For you know your servant.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="David">
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>God, for your servant's sake, and according to your own heart, you have worked all this greatness, to make known all these great things.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="David">
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>God, there is none like you, neither is there any God besides you, according to all that we have heard with our ears.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="David">
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>What one nation in the earth is like your people Israel, whom God went to redeem to himself for a people, to make you a name by great and awesome things, in driving out nations from before your people, whom you redeem out of Egypt?</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="David">
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>For your people Israel you made your own people forever; and you, God, became their God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="David">
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>Now, God, let the word that you have spoken concerning your servant, and concerning his house, be established forever, and do as you have spoken.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="David">
    <verse num="24" />
    <text>Let your name be established and magnified forever, saying, 'God of Armies is the God of Israel, even a God to Israel. The house of David your servant is established before you.'</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="David">
    <verse num="25" />
    <text>For you, my God, have revealed to your servant that you will build him a house. Therefore your servant has found courage to pray before you.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="26" characterId="David">
    <verse num="26" />
    <text>Now, God, you are God, and have promised this good thing to your servant.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="27" characterId="David">
    <verse num="27" />
    <text>Now it has pleased you to bless the house of your servant, that it may continue forever before you; for you, God, have blessed, and it is blessed forever.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="18" book="1CH" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1CH">
    <text>18</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>After this it happened, that David struck the Philistines, and subdued them, and took Gath and its towns out of the hand of the Philistines.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>He struck Moab; and the Moabites became servants to David, and brought tribute.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>David struck Hadadezer king of Zobah to Hamath, as he went to establish his dominion by the river Euphrates.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>David took from him one thousand chariots, and seven thousand horsemen, and twenty thousand footmen; and David hamstrung all the chariot horses, but reserved of them for one hundred chariots.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>When the Syrians of Damascus came to help Hadadezer king of Zobah, David struck of the Syrians twenty-two thousand men.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>Then David put [garrisons] in Syria of Damascus; and the Syrians became servants to David, and brought tribute. God gave victory to David wherever he went.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>David took the shields of gold that were on the servants of Hadadezer, and brought them to Jerusalem.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>From Tibhath and from Cun, cities of Hadadezer, David took very much brass, with which Solomon made the bronze sea, and the pillars, and the vessels of brass.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>When Tou king of Hamath heard that David had struck all the army of Hadadezer king of Zobah, </text>
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>he sent Hadoram his son to king David, to Greet him, and to bless him, because he had fought against Hadadezer and struck him; (for Hadadezer had wars with Tou;) and [he had with him] all kinds of vessels of gold and silver and brass.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>These also did king David dedicate to God, with the silver and the gold that he carried away from all the nations; from Edom, and from Moab, and from the children of Ammon, and from the Philistines, and from Amalek.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>Moreover Abishai the son of Zeruiah struck of the Edomites in the Valley of Salt eighteen thousand.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>He put garrisons in Edom; and all the Edomites became servants to David. God gave victory to David wherever he went.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>David reigned over all Israel; and he executed justice and righteousness to all his people.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>Joab the son of Zeruiah was over the army; and Jehoshaphat the son of Ahilud was recorder;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>and Zadok the son of Ahitub, and Abimelech the son of Abiathar, were priests; and Shavsha was scribe;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>and Benaiah the son of Jehoiada was over the Cherethites and the Pelethites; and the sons of David were chief about the king.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="19" book="1CH" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1CH">
    <text>19</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>It happened after this, that Nahash the king of the children of Ammon died, and his son reigned in his place. </text>
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>David said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="David" delivery="thought">
    <text>«I will show kindness to Hanun the son of Nahash, because his father showed kindness to me.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <text>So David sent messengers to comfort him concerning his father. David's servants came into the land of the children of Ammon to Hanun, to comfort him. </text>
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>But the princes of the children of Ammon said to Hanun,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="Ammonite nobles">
    <text>«Do you think that David honors your father, in that he has sent comforters to you? Haven't his servants come to you to search, to overthrow, and to spy out the land?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>So Hanun took David's servants, and shaved them, and cut off their garments in the middle, even to their buttocks, and sent them away.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>Then there went certain persons, and told David how the men were served. He sent to meet them; for the men were greatly ashamed. The king said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="David">
    <text>«Stay at Jericho until your beards have grown, and then return.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>When the children of Ammon saw that they had made themselves odious to David, Hanun and the children of Ammon sent one thousand talents of silver to hire them chariots and horsemen out of Mesopotamia, and out of Arammaacah, and out of Zobah.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>So they hired for themselves thirty-two thousand chariots, and the king of Maacah and his people, who came and encamped before Medeba. The children of Ammon gathered themselves together from their cities, and came to battle.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>When David heard of it, he sent Joab, and all the army of the mighty men.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>The children of Ammon came out, and put the battle in array at the gate of the city: and the kings who had come were by themselves in the field.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>Now when Joab saw that the battle was set against him before and behind, he chose of all the choice men of Israel, and put them in array against the Syrians.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>The rest of the people he committed into the hand of Abishai his brother; and they put themselves in array against the children of Ammon. </text>
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>He said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="Joab">
    <text>«If the Syrians are too strong for me, then you are to help me; but if the children of Ammon are too strong for you, then I will help you.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="Joab">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>Be courageous, and let us be strong for our people, and for the cities of our God. May God do that which seems good to him.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>So Joab and the people who were with him drew near before the Syrians to the battle; and they fled before him.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>When the children of Ammon saw that the Syrians had fled, they likewise fled before Abishai his brother, and entered into the city. Then Joab came to Jerusalem.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>When the Syrians saw that they were defeated by Israel, they sent messengers, and drew forth the Syrians who were beyond the River, with Shophach the captain of the army of Hadadezer at their head.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>It was told David; and he gathered all Israel together, and passed over the Jordan, and came on them, and set the battle in array against them. So when David had put the battle in array against the Syrians, they fought with him.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>The Syrians fled before Israel; and David killed of the Syrians [the men of] seven thousand chariots, and forty thousand footmen, and killed Shophach the captain of the army.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>When the servants of Hadadezer saw that they were defeated by Israel, they made peace with David, and served him: neither would the Syrians help the children of Ammon any more.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="20" book="1CH" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1CH">
    <text>20</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>It happened, at the time of the return of the year, at the time when kings go out [to battle], that Joab led forth the army, and wasted the country of the children of Ammon, and came and besieged Rabbah. But David stayed at Jerusalem. Joab struck Rabbah, and overthrew it.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>David took the crown of their king from off his head, and found it to weigh a talent of gold, and there were precious stones in it; and it was set on David's head: and he brought forth the spoil of the city, exceeding much.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>He brought forth the people who were therein, and cut [them] with saws, and with iron picks, and with axes. David did so to all the cities of the children of Ammon. David and all the people returned to Jerusalem.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>It happened after this, that there arose war at Gezer with the Philistines: then Sibbecai the Hushathite killed Sippai, of the sons of the giant; and they were subdued.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>There was again war with the Philistines; and Elhanan the son of Jair killed Lahmi the brother of Goliath the Gittite, the staff of whose spear was like a weaver's beam.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>There was again war at Gath, where there was a man of great stature, whose fingers and toes were twenty-four, six [on each hand], and six [on each foot]; and he also was born to the giant.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>When he defied Israel, Jonathan the son of Shimea David's brother killed him.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>These were born to the giant in Gath; and they fell by the hand of David, and by the hand of his servants.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="21" book="1CH" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1CH">
    <text>21</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Satan stood up against Israel, and moved David to number Israel. </text>
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>David said to Joab and to the princes of the people,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="David">
    <text>«Go, number Israel from Beersheba even to Dan; and bring me word, that I may know the sum of them.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>Joab said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="Joab">
    <text>«May God make his people a hundred times as many as they are. But, my lord the king, aren't they all my lord's servants? Why does my lord require this thing? Why will he be a cause of guilt to Israel?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>Nevertheless the king's word prevailed against Joab. Therefore Joab departed, and went throughout all Israel, and came to Jerusalem.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>Joab gave up the sum of the numbering of the people to David. All those of Israel were one million one hundred thousand men who drew sword: and in Judah were four hundred seventy thousand men who drew sword.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>But he didn't count Levi and Benjamin among them; for the king's word was abominable to Joab.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>God was displeased with this thing; therefore he struck Israel. </text>
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>David said to God,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="David">
    <text>«I have sinned greatly, in that I have done this thing. But now, put away, I beg you, the iniquity of your servant; for I have done very foolishly.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>God spoke to Gad, David's seer, saying, </text>
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>Go and speak to David, saying, 'Thus says God, I offer you three things. Choose one of them, that I may do it to you.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>So Gad came to David, and said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="Gad the prophet, David's seer">
    <text>«Thus says God, 'Take your choice: </text>
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>either three years of famine; or three months to be consumed before your foes, while the sword of your enemies overtakes you; or else three days the sword of God, even pestilence in the land, and the angel of God destroying throughout all the borders of Israel. Now therefore consider what answer I shall return to him who sent me.'»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>David said to Gad,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="David">
    <text>«I am in distress. Let me fall, I pray, into the hand of God; for his mercies are very great. Let me not fall into the hand of man.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>So God sent a pestilence on Israel; and seventy thousand men of Israel fell.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>God sent an angel to Jerusalem to destroy it. As he was about to destroy, God saw, and he relented of the disaster, and said to the destroying angel,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="God">
    <text>«It is enough; now stay your hand.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <text>The angel of God was standing by the threshing floor of Ornan the Jebusite.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>David lifted up his eyes, and saw the angel of God standing between earth and the sky, having a drawn sword in his hand stretched out over Jerusalem. Then David and the elders, clothed in sackcloth, fell on their faces. </text>
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>David said to God,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="David">
    <text>«Isn't it I who commanded the people to be numbered? It is even I who have sinned and done very wickedly; but these sheep, what have they done? Please let your hand, O God my God, be against me, and against my father's house; but not against your people, that they should be plagued.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>Then the angel of God commanded Gad to tell David that David should go up, and raise an altar to God in the threshing floor of Ornan the Jebusite.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>David went up at the saying of Gad, which he spoke in the name of God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>Ornan turned back, and saw the angel; and his four sons who were with him hid themselves. Now Ornan was threshing wheat.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>As David came to Ornan, Ornan looked and saw David, and went out of the threshing floor, and bowed himself to David with his face to the ground. </text>
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>Then David said to Ornan,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="David">
    <text>«Give me the place of this threshing floor, that I may build thereon an altar to God. You shall sell it to me for the full price, that the plague may be stopped from afflicting the people.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>Ornan said to David,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="Araunah, the Jebusite">
    <text>«Take it for yourself, and let my lord the king do that which is good in his eyes. Behold, I give the oxen for burnt offerings, and the threshing instruments for wood, and the wheat for the meal offering. I give it all.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="24" />
    <text>King David said to Ornan,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="David">
    <text>«No; but I will most certainly buy it for the full price. For I will not take that which is yours for God, nor offer a burnt offering without cost.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="25" />
    <text>So David gave to Ornan six hundred shekels of gold by weight for the place.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="26" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="26" />
    <text>David built an altar to God there, and offered burnt offerings and peace offerings, and called on God; and he answered him from the sky by fire on the altar of burnt offering.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="27" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="27" />
    <text>God commanded the angel; and he put up his sword again into its sheath.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="28" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="28" />
    <text>At that time, when David saw that God had answered him in the threshing floor of Ornan the Jebusite, then he sacrificed there.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="29" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="29" />
    <text>For the tabernacle of God, which Moses made in the wilderness, and the altar of burnt offering, were at that time in the high place at Gibeon.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="30" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="30" />
    <text>But David couldn't go before it to inquire of God; for he was afraid because of the sword of the angel of God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="22" book="1CH" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1CH">
    <text>22</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="22" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Then David said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="22" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="David">
    <text>«This is the house of God, and this is the altar of burnt offering for Israel.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="22" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>David gave orders to gather together the foreigners who were in the land of Israel; and he set masons to cut worked stones to build the house of God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="22" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>David prepared iron in abundance for the nails for the doors of the gates, and for the couplings; and brass in abundance without weight;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="22" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>and cedar trees without number: for the Sidonians and they of Tyre brought cedar trees in abundance to David. </text>
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>David said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="22" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="David">
    <text>«Solomon my son is young and tender, and the house that is to be built for God must be exceedingly magnificent, of fame and of glory throughout all countries. I will therefore make preparation for it.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="22" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <text>So David prepared abundantly before his death.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="22" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>Then he called for Solomon his son, and commanded him to build a house for God, the God of Israel. </text>
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>David said to Solomon his son,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="22" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="David">
    <text>«As for me, it was in my heart to build a house to the name of God my God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="22" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="David">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>But the word of God came to me, saying, 'You have shed blood abundantly, and have made great wars. You shall not build a house to my name, because you have shed much blood on the earth in my sight.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="22" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="David">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>Behold, a son shall be born to you, who shall be a man of rest. I will give him rest from all his enemies all around; for his name shall be Solomon, and I will give peace and quietness to Israel in his days.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="22" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="David">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>He shall build a house for my name; and he shall be my son, and I will be his father; and I will establish the throne of his kingdom over Israel for ever.'</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="22" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="David">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>Now, my son, may God be with you and prosper you, and build the house of God your God, as he has spoken concerning you.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="22" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="David">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>May God give you discretion and understanding, and put you in charge of Israel; that so you may keep the law of God your God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="22" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="David">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>Then you will prosper, if you observe to do the statutes and the ordinances which God gave Moses concerning Israel. Be strong, and courageous. Don't be afraid, neither be dismayed.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="22" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="David">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>Now, behold, in my affliction I have prepared for the house of God one hundred thousand talents of gold, one million talents of silver, and brass and iron without weight; for it is in abundance. I have also prepared timber and stone; and you may add to them.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="22" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="David">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>There are also workmen with you in abundance, cutters and workers of stone and timber, and all kinds of men who are skillful in every kind of work: </text>
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>of the gold, the silver, and the brass, and the iron, there is no number. Arise and be doing, and may God be with you.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="22" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>David also commanded all the princes of Israel to help Solomon his son, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="22" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="David">
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>Isn't God your God with you? Hasn't he given you rest on every side? For he has delivered the inhabitants of the land into my hand; and the land is subdued before God, and before his people.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="22" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="David">
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>Now set your heart and your soul to seek after God your God. Arise therefore, and build the sanctuary of God, to bring the ark of the covenant of God, and the holy vessels of God, into the house that is to be built to the name of God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="23" book="1CH" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1CH">
    <text>23</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Now David was old and full of days; and he made Solomon his son king over Israel.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>He gathered together all the princes of Israel, with the priests and the Levites.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>The Levites were numbered from thirty years old and upward: and their number by their polls, man by man, was thirty-eight thousand. </text>
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>David said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="David">
    <text>«Of these, twenty-four thousand were to oversee the work of the house of God; six thousand were officers and judges;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="David">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>four thousand were doorkeepers; and four thousand praised God with the instruments which I made, for giving praise.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>David divided them into divisions according to the sons of Levi: Gershon, Kohath, and Merari.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>Of the Gershonites: Ladan and Shimei.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>The sons of Ladan: Jehiel the chief, and Zetham, and Joel, three.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>The sons of Shimei: Shelomoth, and Haziel, and Haran, three. These were the heads of the fathers' [houses] of Ladan.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>The sons of Shimei: Jahath, Zina, and Jeush, and Beriah. These four were the sons of Shimei.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>Jahath was the chief, and Zizah the second: but Jeush and Beriah didn't have many sons; therefore they became a fathers' house in one reckoning.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>The sons of Kohath: Amram, Izhar, Hebron, and Uzziel, four.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>The sons of Amram: Aaron and Moses; and Aaron was separated, that he should sanctify the most holy things, he and his sons, forever, to burn incense before God, to minister to him, and to bless in his name, forever.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>But as for Moses the man of God, his sons were named among the tribe of Levi.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>The sons of Moses: Gershom and Eliezer.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>The sons of Gershom: Shebuel the chief.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>The sons of Eliezer were: Rehabiah the chief; and Eliezer had no other sons; but the sons of Rehabiah were very many.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>The sons of Izhar: Shelomith the chief.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>The sons of Hebron: Jeriah the chief, Amariah the second, Jahaziel the third, and Jekameam the fourth.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>The sons of Uzziel: Micah the chief, and Isshiah the second.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>The sons of Merari: Mahli and Mushi. The sons of Mahli: Eleazar and Kish.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>Eleazar died, and had no sons, but daughters only: and their brothers the sons of Kish took them [to wife].</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>The sons of Mushi: Mahli, and Eder, and Jeremoth, three.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="24" />
    <text>These were the sons of Levi after their fathers' houses, even the heads of the fathers' houses of those who were counted individually, in the number of names by their polls, who did the work for the service of the house of God, from twenty years old and upward. </text>
    <verse num="25" />
    <text>For David said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="David">
    <text>«God, the God of Israel, has given rest to his people; and he dwells in Jerusalem forever.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="26" characterId="David">
    <verse num="26" />
    <text>Also the Levites will no longer need to carry the tabernacle and all its vessels for its service.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="27" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="27" />
    <text>For by the last words of David the sons of Levi were numbered, from twenty years old and upward.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="28" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="28" />
    <text>For their office was to wait on the sons of Aaron for the service of the house of God, in the courts, and in the rooms, and in the purifying of all holy things, even the work of the service of the house of God;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="29" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="29" />
    <text>for the show bread also, and for the fine flour for a meal offering, whether of unleavened wafers, or of that which is baked in the pan, or of that which is soaked, and for all kinds of measure and size;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="30" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="30" />
    <text>and to stand every morning to thank and praise God, and likewise in the evening;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="31" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="31" />
    <text>and to offer all burnt offerings to God, on the Sabbaths, on the new moons, and on the set feasts, in number according to the ordinance concerning them, continually before God;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="32" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="32" />
    <text>and that they should keep the duty of the Tent of Meeting, and the duty of the holy place, and the duty of the sons of Aaron their brothers, for the service of the house of God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="24" book="1CH" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1CH">
    <text>24</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="24" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>These were the divisions of the sons of Aaron. The sons of Aaron: Nadab and Abihu, Eleazar and Ithamar.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="24" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>But Nadab and Abihu died before their father, and had no children: therefore Eleazar and Ithamar executed the priest's office.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="24" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>David with Zadok of the sons of Eleazar, and Ahimelech of the sons of Ithamar, divided them according to their ordering in their service.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="24" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>There were more chief men found of the sons of Eleazar than of the sons of Ithamar; and [thus] were they divided: of the sons of Eleazar there were sixteen, heads of fathers' houses; and of the sons of Ithamar, according to their fathers' houses, eight.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="24" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>Thus were they divided impartially by drawing lots; for there were princes of the sanctuary, and princes of God, both of the sons of Eleazar, and of the sons of Ithamar.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="24" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>Shemaiah the son of Nethanel the scribe, who was of the Levites, wrote them in the presence of the king, and the princes, and Zadok the priest, and Ahimelech the son of Abiathar, and the heads of the fathers' [houses] of the priests and of the Levites; one fathers' house being taken for Eleazar, and one taken for Ithamar.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="24" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>Now the first lot came forth to Jehoiarib, the second to Jedaiah, </text>
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>the third to Harim, the fourth to Seorim, </text>
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>the fifth to Malchijah, the sixth to Mijamin, </text>
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>the seventh to Hakkoz, the eighth to Abijah, </text>
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>the ninth to Jeshua, the tenth to Shecaniah, </text>
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>the eleventh to Eliashib, the twelfth to Jakim, </text>
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>the thirteenth to Huppah, the fourteenth to Jeshebeab, </text>
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>the fifteenth to Bilgah, the sixteenth to Immer, </text>
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>the seventeenth to Hezir, the eighteenth to Happizzez, </text>
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>the nineteenth to Pethahiah, the twentieth to Jehezkel, </text>
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>the twenty-first to Jachin, the twenty-second to Gamul, </text>
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>the twenty-third to Delaiah, the twenty-fourth to Maaziah.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="24" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>This was the ordering of them in their service, to come into the house of God according to the ordinance [given] to them by Aaron their father, as God, the God of Israel, had commanded him.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="24" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>Of the rest of the sons of Levi: of the sons of Amram, Shubael; of the sons of Shubael, Jehdeiah.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="24" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>Of Rehabiah: of the sons of Rehabiah, Isshiah the chief.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="24" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>Of the Izharites, Shelomoth; of the sons of Shelomoth, Jahath.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="24" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>The sons [of Hebron]: Jeriah [the chief], Amariah the second, Jahaziel the third, Jekameam the fourth.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="24" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="24" />
    <text>The sons of Uzziel, Micah; of the sons of Micah, Shamir.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="24" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="25" />
    <text>The brother of Micah, Isshiah; of the sons of Isshiah, Zechariah.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="24" initialStartVerse="26" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="26" />
    <text>The sons of Merari: Mahli and Mushi; the sons of Jaaziah: Beno.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="24" initialStartVerse="27" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="27" />
    <text>The sons of Merari: of Jaaziah, Beno, and Shoham, and Zaccur, and Ibri.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="24" initialStartVerse="28" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="28" />
    <text>Of Mahli: Eleazar, who had no sons.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="24" initialStartVerse="29" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="29" />
    <text>Of Kish; the sons of Kish: Jerahmeel.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="24" initialStartVerse="30" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="30" />
    <text>The sons of Mushi: Mahli, and Eder, and Jerimoth. These were the sons of the Levites after their fathers' houses.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="24" initialStartVerse="31" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="31" />
    <text>These likewise cast lots even as their brothers the sons of Aaron in the presence of David the king, and Zadok, and Ahimelech, and the heads of the fathers' [houses] of the priests and of the Levites; the fathers' [houses] of the chief even as those of his younger brother.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="25" book="1CH" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1CH">
    <text>25</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Moreover, David and the captains of the army set apart for the service certain of the sons of Asaph, and of Heman, and of Jeduthun, who should prophesy with harps, with stringed instruments, and with cymbals: and the number of those who did the work according to their service was:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>of the sons of Asaph: Zaccur, and Joseph, and Nethaniah, and Asharelah, the sons of Asaph, under the hand of Asaph, who prophesied after the order of the king.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>Of Jeduthun; the sons of Jeduthun: Gedaliah, and Zeri, and Jeshaiah, Hashabiah, and Mattithiah, six, under the hands of their father Jeduthun with the harp, who prophesied in giving thanks and praising God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>Of Heman; the sons of Heman: Bukkiah, Mattaniah, Uzziel, Shebuel, and Jerimoth, Hananiah, Hanani, Eliathah, Giddalti, and Romamti-Ezer, Joshbekashah, Mallothi, Hothir, Mahazioth.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>All these were the sons of Heman the king's seer in the words of God, to lift up the horn. God gave to Heman fourteen sons and three daughters.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>All these were under the hands of their father for song in the house of God, with cymbals, stringed instruments, and harps, for the service of the house of God; Asaph, Jeduthun, and Heman being under the order of the king.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>The number of them, with their brothers who were instructed in singing to God, even all who were skillful, was two hundred eighty-eight.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>They cast lots for their offices, all alike, as well the small as the great, the teacher as the scholar.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>Now the first lot came forth for Asaph to Joseph: the second to Gedaliah; he and his brothers and sons were twelve:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>the third to Zaccur, his sons and his brothers, twelve:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>the fourth to Izri, his sons and his brothers, twelve:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>the fifth to Nethaniah, his sons and his brothers, twelve:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>the sixth to Bukkiah, his sons and his brothers, twelve:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>the seventh to Jesharelah, his sons and his brothers, twelve:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>the eighth to Jeshaiah, his sons and his brothers, twelve:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>the ninth to Mattaniah, his sons and his brothers, twelve:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>the tenth to Shimei, his sons and his brothers, twelve:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>the eleventh to Azarel, his sons and his brothers, twelve:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>the twelfth to Hashabiah, his sons and his brothers, twelve:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>for the thirteenth, Shubael, his sons and his brothers, twelve:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>for the fourteenth, Mattithiah, his sons and his brothers, twelve:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>for the fifteenth to Jeremoth, his sons and his brothers, twelve:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>for the sixteenth to Hananiah, his sons and his brothers, twelve:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="24" />
    <text>for the seventeenth to Joshbekashah, his sons and his brothers, twelve:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="25" />
    <text>for the eighteenth to Hanani, his sons and his brothers, twelve:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="26" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="26" />
    <text>for the nineteenth to Mallothi, his sons and his brothers, twelve:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="27" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="27" />
    <text>for the twentieth to Eliathah, his sons and his brothers, twelve:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="28" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="28" />
    <text>for the one and twentieth to Hothir, his sons and his brothers, twelve:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="29" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="29" />
    <text>for the two and twentieth to Giddalti, his sons and his brothers, twelve:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="30" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="30" />
    <text>for the three and twentieth to Mahazioth, his sons and his brothers, twelve:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="31" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="31" />
    <text>for the four and twentieth to Romamti-Ezer, his sons and his brothers, twelve.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="26" book="1CH" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1CH">
    <text>26</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="26" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>For the divisions of the doorkeepers: of the Korahites, Meshelemiah the son of Kore, of the sons of Asaph.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="26" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>Meshelemiah had sons: Zechariah the firstborn, Jediael the second, Zebadiah the third, Jathniel the fourth, </text>
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>Elam the fifth, Jehohanan the sixth, Eliehoenai the seventh.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="26" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>Obed-Edom had sons: Shemaiah the firstborn, Jehozabad the second, Joah the third, and Sacar the fourth, and Nethanel the fifth, </text>
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>Ammiel the sixth, Issachar the seventh, Peullethai the eighth; for God blessed him.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="26" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>Also to Shemaiah his son were sons born, who ruled over the house of their father; for they were mighty men of valor.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="26" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>The sons of Shemaiah: Othni, and Rephael, and Obed, Elzabad, whose brothers were valiant men, Elihu, and Semachiah.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="26" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>All these were of the sons of Obed-Edom: they and their sons and their brothers, able men in strength for the service; sixty-two of Obed-Edom.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="26" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>Meshelemiah had sons and brothers, valiant men, eighteen.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="26" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>Also Hosah, of the children of Merari, had sons: Shimri the chief, (for though he was not the firstborn, yet his father made him chief), </text>
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>Hilkiah the second, Tebaliah the third, Zechariah the fourth: all the sons and brothers of Hosah were thirteen.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="26" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>Of these were the divisions of the doorkeepers, even of the chief men, having offices like their brothers, to minister in the house of God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="26" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>They cast lots, the small as well as the great, according to their fathers' houses, for every gate.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="26" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>The lot eastward fell to Shelemiah. Then for Zechariah his son, a wise counselor, they cast lots; and his lot came out northward.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="26" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>To Obed-Edom southward; and to his sons the storehouse.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="26" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>To Shuppim and Hosah westward, by the gate of Shallecheth, at the causeway that goes up, watch against watch.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="26" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>Eastward were six Levites, northward four a day, southward four a day, and for the storehouse two and two.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="26" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>For Parbar westward, four at the causeway, and two at Parbar.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="26" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>These were the divisions of the doorkeepers; of the sons of the Korahites, and of the sons of Merari.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="26" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>Of the Levites, Ahijah was over the treasures of the house of God, and over the treasures of the dedicated things.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="26" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>The sons of Ladan, the sons of the Gershonites belonging to Ladan, the heads of the fathers' [houses] belonging to Ladan the Gershonite: Jehieli.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="26" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>The sons of Jehieli: Zetham, and Joel his brother, over the treasures of the house of God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="26" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>Of the Amramites, of the Izharites, of the Hebronites, of the Uzzielites:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="26" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="24" />
    <text>and Shebuel the son of Gershom, the son of Moses, was ruler over the treasures.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="26" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="25" />
    <text>His brothers: of Eliezer [came] Rehabiah his son, and Jeshaiah his son, and Joram his son, and Zichri his son, and Shelomoth his son.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="26" initialStartVerse="26" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="26" />
    <text>This Shelomoth and his brothers were over all the treasures of the dedicated things, which David the king, and the heads of the fathers' [houses], the captains over thousands and hundreds, and the captains of the army, had dedicated.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="26" initialStartVerse="27" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="27" />
    <text>Out of the spoil won in battles did they dedicate to repair the house of God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="26" initialStartVerse="28" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="28" />
    <text>All that Samuel the seer, and Saul the son of Kish, and Abner the son of Ner, and Joab the son of Zeruiah, had dedicated, whoever had dedicated anything, it was under the hand of Shelomoth, and of his brothers.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="26" initialStartVerse="29" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="29" />
    <text>Of the Izharites, Chenaniah and his sons were for the outward business over Israel, for officers and judges.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="26" initialStartVerse="30" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="30" />
    <text>Of the Hebronites, Hashabiah and his brothers, men of valor, one thousand seven hundred, had the oversight of Israel beyond the Jordan westward, for all the business of God, and for the service of the king.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="26" initialStartVerse="31" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="31" />
    <text>Of the Hebronites was Jerijah the chief, even of the Hebronites, according to their generations by fathers' [houses]. In the fortieth year of the reign of David they were sought for, and there were found among them mighty men of valor at Jazer of Gilead.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="26" initialStartVerse="32" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="32" />
    <text>His brothers, men of valor, were two thousand seven hundred, heads of fathers' [houses], whom king David made overseers over the Reubenites, and the Gadites, and the half-tribe of the Manassites, for every matter pertaining to God, and for the affairs of the king.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="27" book="1CH" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1CH">
    <text>27</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="27" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Now the children of Israel after their number, the heads of fathers' [houses] and the captains of thousands and of hundreds, and their officers who served the king, in any matter of the divisions which came in and went out month by month throughout all the months of the year--of every division were twenty-four thousand.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="27" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>Over the first division for the first month was Jashobeam the son of Zabdiel: and in his division were twenty-four thousand.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="27" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>[He was] of the children of Perez, the chief of all the captains of the army for the first month.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="27" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>Over the division of the second month was Dodai the Ahohite, and his division; and Mikloth the ruler: and in his division were twenty-four thousand.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="27" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>The third captain of the army for the third month was Benaiah, the son of Jehoiada the priest, chief: and in his division were twenty-four thousand.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="27" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>This is that Benaiah, who was the mighty man of the thirty, and over the thirty: and [of] his division was Ammizabad his son.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="27" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>The fourth [captain] for the fourth month was Asahel the brother of Joab, and Zebadiah his son after him: and in his division were twenty-four thousand.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="27" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>The fifth captain for this fifth month was Shamhuth the Izrahite: and in his division were twenty-four thousand.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="27" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>The sixth [captain] for the sixth month was Ira the son of Ikkesh the Tekoite: and in his division were twenty-four thousand.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="27" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>The seventh [captain] for the seventh month was Helez the Pelonite, of the children of Ephraim: and in his division were twenty-four thousand.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="27" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>The eighth [captain] for the eighth month was Sibbecai the Hushathite, of the Zerahites: and in his division were twenty-four thousand.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="27" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>The ninth [captain] for the ninth month was Abiezer the Anathothite, of the Benjamites: and in his division were twenty-four thousand.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="27" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>The tenth [captain] for the tenth month was Maharai the Netophathite, of the Zerahites: and in his division were Twenty-four thousand.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="27" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>The eleventh [captain] for the eleventh month was Benaiah the Pirathonite, of the children of Ephraim: and in his division were twenty-four thousand.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="27" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>The twelfth [captain] for the twelfth month was Heldai the Netophathite, of Othniel: and in his division were twenty-four thousand.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="27" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>Furthermore over the tribes of Israel: of the Reubenites was Eliezer the son of Zichri the ruler: of the Simeonites, Shephatiah the son of Maacah:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="27" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>of Levi, Hashabiah the son of Kemuel: of Aaron, Zadok:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="27" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>of Judah, Elihu, one of the brothers of David: of Issachar, Omri the son of Michael:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="27" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>of Zebulun, Ishmaiah the son of Obadiah: of Naphtali, Jeremoth the son of Azriel:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="27" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>of the children of Ephraim, Hoshea the son of Azaziah: of the half-tribe of Manasseh, Joel the son of Pedaiah:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="27" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>of the half-tribe of Manasseh in Gilead, Iddo the son of Zechariah: of Benjamin, Jaasiel the son of Abner:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="27" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>of Dan, Azarel the son of Jeroham. These were the captains of the tribes of Israel.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="27" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>But David didn't take the number of them from twenty years old and under, because God had said he would increase Israel like the stars of the sky.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="27" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="24" />
    <text>Joab the son of Zeruiah began to number, but didn't finish; and there came wrath for this on Israel; neither was the number put into the account in the chronicles of king David.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="27" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="25" />
    <text>Over the king's treasures was Azmaveth the son of Adiel: and over the treasures in the fields, in the cities, and in the villages, and in the towers, was Jonathan the son of Uzziah:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="27" initialStartVerse="26" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="26" />
    <text>Over those who did the work of the field for tillage of the ground was Ezri the son of Chelub:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="27" initialStartVerse="27" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="27" />
    <text>and over the vineyards was Shimei the Ramathite: and over the increase of the vineyards for the winecellars was Zabdi the Shiphmite:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="27" initialStartVerse="28" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="28" />
    <text>and over the olive trees and the sycamore trees that were in the lowland was Baal Hanan the Gederite: and over the cellars of oil was Joash:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="27" initialStartVerse="29" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="29" />
    <text>and over the herds that fed in Sharon was Shitrai the Sharonite: and over the herds that were in the valleys was Shaphat the son of Adlai:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="27" initialStartVerse="30" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="30" />
    <text>and over the camels was Obil the Ishmaelite: and over the donkeys was Jehdeiah the Meronothite: and over the flocks was Jaziz the Hagrite.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="27" initialStartVerse="31" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="31" />
    <text>All these were the rulers of the substance which was king David's.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="27" initialStartVerse="32" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="32" />
    <text>Also Jonathan, David's uncle, was a counselor, a man of understanding, and a scribe: and Jehiel the son of Hachmoni was with the king's sons:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="27" initialStartVerse="33" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="33" />
    <text>Ahithophel was the king's counselor: and Hushai the Archite was the king's friend:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="27" initialStartVerse="34" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="34" />
    <text>and after Ahithophel was Jehoiada the son of Benaiah, and Abiathar: and the captain of the king's army was Joab.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="28" book="1CH" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1CH">
    <text>28</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="28" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>David assembled all the princes of Israel, the princes of the tribes, and the captains of the companies who served the king by division, and the captains of thousands, and the captains of hundreds, and the rulers over all the substance and possessions of the king and of his sons, with the officers, and the mighty men, even all the mighty men of valor, to Jerusalem.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="28" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>Then David the king stood up on his feet, and said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="28" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="David">
    <text>«Hear me, my brothers, and my people! As for me, it was in my heart to build a house of rest for the ark of the covenant of God, and for the footstool of our God; and I had prepared for the building.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="28" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="David">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>But God said to me, 'You shall not build a house for my name, because you are a man of war, and have shed blood.'</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="28" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="David">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>However God, the God of Israel, chose me out of all the house of my father to be king over Israel forever. For he has chosen Judah to be prince; and in the house of Judah, the house of my father; and among the sons of my father he took pleasure in me to make me king over all Israel.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="28" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="David">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>Of all my sons (for God has given me many sons), he has chosen Solomon my son to sit on the throne of God's kingdom over Israel.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="28" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="David">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>He said to me, 'Solomon, your son, shall build my house and my courts; for I have chosen him to be my son, and I will be his father.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="28" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="David">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>I will establish his kingdom forever, if he continues to do my commandments and my ordinances, as at this day.'</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="28" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="David">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>Now therefore, in the sight of all Israel, the assembly of God, and in the audience of our God, observe and seek out all the commandments of God your God; that you may possess this good land, and leave it for an inheritance to your children after you forever.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="28" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="David">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>You, Solomon my son, know the God of your father, and serve him with a perfect heart and with a willing mind; for God searches all hearts, and understands all the imaginations of the thoughts. If you seek him, he will be found by you; but if you forsake him, he will cast you off forever.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="28" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="David">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>Take heed now; for God has chosen you to build a house for the sanctuary. Be strong, and do it.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="28" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>Then David gave to Solomon his son the pattern of the porch [of the temple], and of its houses, and of its treasuries, and of the upper rooms of it, and of the inner rooms of it, and of the place of the mercy seat;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="28" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>and the pattern of all that he had by the Spirit, for the courts of the house of God, and for all the surrounding rooms, for the treasuries of the house of God, and for the treasuries of the dedicated things;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="28" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>also for the divisions of the priests and the Levites, and for all the work of the service of the house of God, and for all the vessels of service in the house of God;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="28" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>of gold by weight for the [vessels of] gold, for all vessels of every kind of service; [of silver] for all the vessels of silver by weight, for all vessels of every kind of service;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="28" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>by weight also for the lampstands of gold, and for its lamps, of gold, by weight for every lampstand and for its lamps; and for the lampstands of silver, [silver] by weight for [every] lampstand and for its lamps, according to the use of every lampstand;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="28" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>and the gold by weight for the tables of show bread, for every table; and silver for the tables of silver;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="28" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>and the forks, and the basins, and the cups, of pure gold; and for the golden bowls by weight for every bowl; and for the silver bowls by weight for every bowl;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="28" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>and for the altar of incense refined gold by weight; and gold for the pattern of the chariot, [even] the cherubim, that spread out [their wings], and covered the ark of the covenant of God. </text>
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>All this, said David,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="28" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="David">
    <text>«I have been made to understand in writing from the hand of God, even all the works of this pattern.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="28" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>David said to Solomon his son,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="28" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="David">
    <text>«Be strong and courageous, and do it. Don't be afraid, nor be dismayed; for God, even my God, is with you. He will not fail you, nor forsake you, until all the work for the service of the house of God is finished.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="28" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="David">
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>Behold, there are the divisions of the priests and the Levites, for all the service of the house of God. There shall be with you in all kinds of work every willing man who has skill, for any kind of service. Also the captains and all the people will be entirely at your command.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="29" book="1CH" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1CH">
    <text>29</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="29" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>David the king said to all the assembly,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="29" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="David">
    <text>«Solomon my son, whom alone God has chosen, is yet young and tender, and the work is great; for the palace is not for man, but for God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="29" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="David">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>Now I have prepared with all my might for the house of my God the gold for the [things of] gold, and the silver for the [things of] silver, and the brass for the [things of] brass, the iron for the [things of] iron, and wood for the [things of] wood; onyx stones, and [stones] to be set, stones for inlaid work, and of various colors, and all kinds of precious stones, and marble stones in abundance.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="29" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="David">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>In addition, because I have set my affection on the house of my God, since I have a treasure of my own of gold and silver, I give it to the house of my God, over and above all that I have prepared for the holy house, </text>
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>even three thousand talents of gold, of the gold of Ophir, and seven thousand talents of refined silver, with which to overlay the walls of the houses;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="29" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="David">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>of gold for the [things of] gold, and of silver for the [things of] silver, and for all kinds of work [to be made] by the hands of artificers. Who then offers willingly to consecrate himself this day to God?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="29" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>Then the princes of the fathers' [houses], and the princes of the tribes of Israel, and the captains of thousands and of hundreds, with the rulers over the king's work, offered willingly;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="29" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>and they gave for the service of the house of God of gold five thousand talents and ten thousand darics, and of silver ten thousand talents, and of brass eighteen thousand talents, and of iron a hundred thousand talents.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="29" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>They with whom [precious] stones were found gave them to the treasure of the house of God, under the hand of Jehiel the Gershonite.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="29" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>Then the people rejoiced, because they offered willingly, because with a perfect heart they offered willingly to God: and David the king also rejoiced with great joy.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="29" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>Therefore David blessed God before all the assembly; and David said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="29" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="David">
    <text>«You are blessed, God, the God of Israel our father, forever and ever.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="29" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="David">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>Yours, God, is the greatness, the power, the glory, the victory, and the majesty! For all that is in the heavens and in the earth is yours. Yours is the kingdom, God, and you are exalted as head above all.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="29" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="David">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>Both riches and honor come from you, and you rule over all; and in your hand is power and might; and it is in your hand to make great, and to give strength to all.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="29" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="David">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>Now therefore, our God, we thank you, and praise your glorious name.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="29" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="David">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>But who am I, and what is my people, that we should be able to offer so willingly as this? For all things come from you, and of your own have we given you.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="29" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="David">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>For we are strangers before you, and foreigners, as all our fathers were. Our days on the earth are as a shadow, and there is no remaining.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="29" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="David">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>God our God, all this store that we have prepared to build you a house for your holy name comes from your hand, and is all your own.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="29" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="David">
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>I know also, my God, that you try the heart, and have pleasure in uprightness. As for me, in the uprightness of my heart I have willingly offered all these things. Now have I seen with joy your people, that are present here, offer willingly to you.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="29" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="David">
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>God, the God of Abraham, of Isaac, and of Israel, our fathers, keep this forever in the imagination of the thoughts of the heart of your people, and prepare their heart for you;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="29" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="David">
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>and give to Solomon my son a perfect heart, to keep your commandments, your testimonies, and your statutes, and to do all these things, and to build the palace, for which I have made provision.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="29" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>David said to all the assembly,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="29" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="David">
    <text>«Now bless God your God!»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="29" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <text>All the assembly blessed God, the God of their fathers, and bowed down their heads and prostrated themselves before God and the king.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="29" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>They sacrificed sacrifices to God, and offered burnt offerings to God, on the next day after that day, even one thousand bulls, one thousand rams, and one thousand lambs, with their drink offerings, and sacrifices in abundance for all Israel, </text>
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>and ate and drink before God on that day with great gladness. They made Solomon the son of David king the second time, and anointed him to God to be prince, and Zadok to be priest.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="29" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>Then Solomon sat on the throne of God as king instead of David his father, and prospered; and all Israel obeyed him.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="29" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="24" />
    <text>All the princes, the mighty men, and also all of the sons of king David submitted themselves to Solomon the king.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="29" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="25" />
    <text>God magnified Solomon exceedingly in the sight of all Israel, and bestowed on him such royal majesty as had not been on any king before him in Israel.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="29" initialStartVerse="26" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="26" />
    <text>Now David the son of Jesse reigned over all Israel.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="29" initialStartVerse="27" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="27" />
    <text>The time that he reigned over Israel was forty years; he reigned seven years in Hebron, and thirty-three [years] reigned he in Jerusalem.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="29" initialStartVerse="28" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="28" />
    <text>He died in a good old age, full of days, riches, and honor: and Solomon his son reigned in his place.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="29" initialStartVerse="29" characterId="narrator-1CH">
    <verse num="29" />
    <text>Now the acts of David the king, first and last, behold, they are written in the history of Samuel the seer, and in the history of Nathan the prophet, and in the history of Gad the seer, </text>
    <verse num="30" />
    <text>with all his reign and his might, and the times that went over him, and over Israel, and over all the kingdoms of the countries.</text>
  </block>
  <UnappliedSplits />
</book>