<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<book id="1SA" singlevoice="false" pageheader="1 Samuel">
  <block style="mt" chapter="0" book="1SA" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1SA">
    <text>1 Samuel</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" book="1SA" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1SA">
    <text>1</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Now there was a certain man of Ramathaim Zophim, of the hill country of Ephraim, and his name was Elkanah, the son of Jeroham, the son of Elihu, the son of Tohu, the son of Zuph, an Ephraimite:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>and he had two wives; the name of the one was Hannah, and the name of other Peninnah: and Peninnah had children, but Hannah had no children.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>This man went up out of his city from year to year to worship and to sacrifice to God of Armies in Shiloh. The two sons of Eli, Hophni and Phinehas, priests to God, were there.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>When the day came that Elkanah sacrificed, he gave to Peninnah his wife, and to all her sons and her daughters, portions:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>but to Hannah he gave a double portion; for he loved Hannah, but God had shut up her womb.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>Her rival provoked her severely, to make her fret, because God had shut up her womb.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>as he did so year by year, when she went up to the house of God, so she provoked her; therefore she wept, and did not eat.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>Elkanah her husband said to her,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="Elkanah">
    <text>«Hannah, why do you weep? Why don't you eat? Why is your heart grieved? Am I not better to you than ten sons?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>So Hannah rose up after they had eaten in Shiloh, and after they had drunk. Now Eli the priest was sitting on his seat by the doorpost of the temple of God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>She was in bitterness of soul, and prayed to God, and wept bitterly. </text>
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>She vowed a vow, and said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="Hannah">
    <text>«God of Armies, if you will indeed look on the affliction of your handmaid, and remember me, and not forget your handmaid, but will give to your handmaid a boy, then I will give him to God all the days of his life, and no razor shall come on his head.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>It happened, as she continued praying before God, that Eli saw her mouth.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>Now Hannah spoke in her heart. Only her lips moved, but her voice was not heard. Therefore Eli thought she had been drunken. </text>
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>Eli said to her,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="Eli">
    <text>«How long will you be drunken? Put away your wine from you.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>Hannah answered,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="Hannah">
    <text>«No, my lord, I am a woman of a sorrowful spirit. I have drunk neither wine nor strong drink, but I poured out my soul before God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="Hannah">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>Don’t count your handmaid for a wicked woman; for I have been speaking out of the abundance of my complaint and my provocation.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>Then Eli answered,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="Eli">
    <text>«Go in peace; and may the God of Israel grant your petition that you have asked of him.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>She said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="Hannah">
    <text>«Let your handmaid find favor in your sight.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>So the woman went her way, and ate; and her facial expression wasn't sad any more.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>They rose up in the morning early, and worshiped before God, and returned, and came to their house to Ramah: and Elkanah knew Hannah his wife; and God remembered her.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>It happened, when the time had come, that Hannah conceived, and bore a son; and she named him Samuel, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="Hannah">
    <text>«Because I have asked him of God.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>The man Elkanah, and all his house, went up to offer to God the yearly sacrifice, and his vow. </text>
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>But Hannah didn’t go up; for she said to her husband,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="Hannah">
    <text>«Not until the child is weaned; then I will bring him, that he may appear before God, and stay there forever.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>Elkanah her husband said to her,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="Elkanah">
    <text>«Do what seems good to you. Wait until you have weaned him; only may God establish his word.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>So the woman waited and nursed her son, until she weaned him.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="24" />
    <text>When she had weaned him, she took him up with her, with three bulls, and one ephah of meal, and a bottle of wine, and brought him to God’s house in Shiloh. The child was young.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="25" />
    <text>They killed the bull, and brought the child to Eli. </text>
    <verse num="26" />
    <text>She said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="26" characterId="Hannah">
    <text>«Oh, my lord, as your soul lives, my lord, I am the woman who stood by you here, praying to God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="27" characterId="Hannah">
    <verse num="27" />
    <text>For this child I prayed; and God has given me my petition which I asked of him.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="28" characterId="Hannah">
    <verse num="28" />
    <text>Therefore also I have granted him to God. As long as he lives he is granted to God.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="28" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>He worshiped God there.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" book="1SA" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1SA">
    <text>2</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Hannah prayed, and said:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="Hannah">
    <text>«My heart exults in God! My horn is exalted in God. My mouth is enlarged over my enemies, because I rejoice in your salvation.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="Hannah">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>There is no one as holy as God, For there is no one besides you, nor is there any rock like our God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="Hannah">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>Talk no more so exceeding proudly. Don’t let arrogance come out of your mouth, For God is a God of knowledge. By him actions are weighed.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="Hannah">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>The bows of the mighty men are broken. Those who stumbled are armed with strength.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="Hannah">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>Those who were full have hired themselves out for bread. Those who were hungry have ceased to hunger. Yes, the barren has borne seven. She who has many children languishes.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="Hannah">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>God kills, and makes alive. He brings down to Sheol, and brings up.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="Hannah">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>God makes poor, and makes rich. He brings low, he also lifts up.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="Hannah">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>He raises up the poor out of the dust. He lifts up the needy from the dunghill, To make them sit with princes, and inherit the throne of glory. For the pillars of the earth are God’s. He has set the world on them.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="Hannah">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>He will keep the feet of his holy ones, but the wicked shall be put to silence in darkness; for no man shall prevail by strength.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="Hannah">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>Those who strive with God shall be broken to pieces. He will thunder against them in the sky. God will judge the ends of the earth. He will give strength to his king, and exalt the horn of his anointed.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>Elkanah went to Ramah to his house. The child did minister to God before Eli the priest.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>Now the sons of Eli were base men; they didn’t know God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>The custom of the priests with the people was that when any man offered sacrifice, the priest’s servant came, while the flesh was boiling, with a fork of three teeth in his hand;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>and he struck it into the pan, or kettle, or caldron, or pot; all that the fork brought up the priest took therewith. So they did in Shiloh to all the Israelites who came there.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>Yes, before they burnt the fat, the priest’s servant came, and said to the man who sacrificed,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="servant of priest">
    <text>«Give meat to roast for the priest; for he will not accept boiled meat from you, but raw.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>If the man said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="person sacrificing" delivery="pleading">
    <text>«Let the fat be burned first, and then take as much as your soul desires;»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>then he would say,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="servant of priest" delivery="demanding">
    <text>«No, but you shall give it to me now; and if not, I will take it by force.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>The sin of the young men was very great before God; for the men despised the offering of God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>But Samuel ministered before God, being a child, clothed with a linen ephod.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>Moreover his mother made him a little robe, and brought it to him from year to year, when she came up with her husband to offer the yearly sacrifice.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>Eli blessed Elkanah and his wife, and said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="Eli">
    <text>«God give you seed of this woman for the petition which was asked of God.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>They went to their own home. </text>
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>God visited Hannah, and she conceived, and bore three sons and two daughters. The child Samuel grew before God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>Now Eli was very old; and he heard all that his sons did to all Israel, and how that they lay with the women who served at the door of the Tent of Meeting. </text>
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>He said to them,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="Eli">
    <text>«Why do you do such things? for I hear of your evil dealings from all this people.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="Eli">
    <verse num="24" />
    <text>No, my sons; for it is no good report that I hear: you make God’s people disobey.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="Eli">
    <verse num="25" />
    <text>If one man sin against another, God shall judge him; but if a man sin against God, who shall entreat for him?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>Notwithstanding, they didn't listen to the voice of their father, because God was minded to kill them.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="26" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="26" />
    <text>The child Samuel grew on, and increased in favor both with God, and also with men.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="27" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="27" />
    <text>A man of God came to Eli, and said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="27" characterId="man of God (prophet to Eli)">
    <text>«Thus says God, ‹Did I reveal myself to the house of your father, when they were in Egypt in bondage to Pharaoh’s house?</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="28" characterId="man of God (prophet to Eli)">
    <verse num="28" />
    <text>Did I choose him out of all the tribes of Israel to be my priest, to go up to my altar, to burn incense, to wear an ephod before me? Did I give to the house of your father all the offerings of the children of Israel made by fire?</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="29" characterId="man of God (prophet to Eli)">
    <verse num="29" />
    <text>Why do you kick at my sacrifice and at my offering, which I have commanded in my habitation, and honor your sons above me, to make yourselves fat with the best of all the offerings of Israel my people?›</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="30" characterId="man of God (prophet to Eli)">
    <verse num="30" />
    <text>Therefore God, the God of Israel, says, ‹I said indeed that your house, and the house of your father, should walk before me forever.› But now God says, ‹Be it far from me; for those who honor me I will honor, and those who despise me shall be lightly esteemed.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="31" characterId="man of God (prophet to Eli)">
    <verse num="31" />
    <text>Behold, the days come, that I will cut off your arm, and the arm of your father’s house, that there shall not be an old man in your house.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="32" characterId="man of God (prophet to Eli)">
    <verse num="32" />
    <text>You shall see the affliction of my habitation, in all the wealth which God shall give Israel; and there shall not be an old man in your house forever.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="33" characterId="man of God (prophet to Eli)">
    <verse num="33" />
    <text>The man of yours, whom I shall not cut off from my altar, shall be to consume your eyes, and to grieve your heart; and all the increase of your house shall die in the flower of their age.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="34" characterId="man of God (prophet to Eli)">
    <verse num="34" />
    <text>This shall be the sign to you, that shall come on your two sons, on Hophni and Phinehas: in one day they shall both die.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="35" characterId="man of God (prophet to Eli)">
    <verse num="35" />
    <text>I will raise me up a faithful priest, that shall do according to that which is in my heart and in my mind. I will build him a sure house; and he shall walk before my anointed forever.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="36" characterId="man of God (prophet to Eli)">
    <verse num="36" />
    <text>It shall happen, that everyone who is left in your house shall come and bow down to him for a piece of silver and a loaf of bread, and shall say, «Please put me into one of the priests’ offices, that I may eat a morsel of bread.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" book="1SA" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1SA">
    <text>3</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>The child Samuel ministered to God before Eli. The word of God was precious in those days; there was no frequent vision.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>It happened at that time, when Eli was laid down in his place (now his eyes had begun to grow dim, so that he could not see),</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>and the lamp of God hadn’t yet gone out, and Samuel had laid down to sleep, in the temple of God, where the ark of God was;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>that God called Samuel; and he said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="Samuel (boy)">
    <text>«Here I am.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>He ran to Eli, and said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="Samuel (boy)">
    <text>«Here I am; for you called me.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>He said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="Eli">
    <text>«I didn't call; lie down again.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>He went and lay down. </text>
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>God called yet again,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="God">
    <text>«Samuel!»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>Samuel arose and went to Eli, and said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="Samuel (boy)">
    <text>«Here I am; for you called me.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>He answered,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="Eli">
    <text>«I didn't call, my son; lie down again.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>Now Samuel didn’t yet know God, neither was the word of God yet revealed to him.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>God called Samuel again the third time. He arose and went to Eli, and said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="Samuel (boy)">
    <text>«Here I am; for you called me.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>Eli perceived that God had called the child. </text>
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>Therefore Eli said to Samuel,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="Eli">
    <text>«Go, lie down: and it shall be, if he calls you, that you shall say, ‹Speak, God; for your servant hears.› »</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>So Samuel went and lay down in his place. </text>
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>God came, and stood, and called as at other times,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="God">
    <text>«Samuel! Samuel!»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>Then Samuel said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="Samuel (boy)">
    <text>«Speak; for your servant hears.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>God said to Samuel,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="God">
    <text>«Behold, I will do a thing in Israel, at which both the ears of everyone who hears it shall tingle.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="God">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>In that day I will perform against Eli all that I have spoken concerning his house, from the beginning even to the end.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="God">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>For I have told him that I will judge his house forever, for the iniquity which he knew, because his sons brought a curse on themselves, and he didn’t restrain them.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="God">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>Therefore I have sworn to the house of Eli, that the iniquity of Eli’s house shall not be removed with sacrifice nor offering forever.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>Samuel lay until the morning, and opened the doors of the house of God. Samuel feared to show Eli the vision. </text>
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>Then Eli called Samuel, and said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="Eli">
    <text>«Samuel, my son!»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>He said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="Samuel (boy)">
    <text>«Here I am.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>He said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="Eli">
    <text>«What is the thing that God has spoken to you? Please don’t hide it from me. God do so to you, and more also, if you hide anything from me of all the things that he spoke to you.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>Samuel told him every bit, and hid nothing from him. He said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="Eli">
    <text>«It is God. Let him do what seems good to him.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>Samuel grew, and God was with him, and let none of his words fall to the ground.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>All Israel from Dan even to Beersheba knew that Samuel was established to be a prophet of God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>God appeared again in Shiloh; for God revealed himself to Samuel in Shiloh by the word of God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" book="1SA" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1SA">
    <text>4</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>The word of Samuel came to all Israel. Now Israel went out against the Philistines to battle, and encamped beside Ebenezer: and the Philistines encamped in Aphek.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>The Philistines put themselves in array against Israel: and when they joined battle, Israel was struck before the Philistines; and they killed of the army in the field about four thousand men.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>When the people were come into the camp, the elders of Israel said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="elders of Israel">
    <text>«Why has God struck us today before the Philistines? Let us get the ark of the covenant of God out of Shiloh to us, that it may come among us, and save us out of the hand of our enemies.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>So the people sent to Shiloh; and they brought from there the ark of the covenant of God of Armies, who sits above the cherubim: and the two sons of Eli, Hophni and Phinehas, were there with the ark of the covenant of God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>When the ark of the covenant of God came into the camp, all Israel shouted with a great shout, so that the earth rang again. </text>
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>When the Philistines heard the noise of the shout, they said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="Philistines">
    <text>«What does the noise of this great shout in the camp of the Hebrews mean?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>They understood that the ark of God had come into the camp. </text>
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>The Philistines were afraid, for they said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="Philistines">
    <text>«God has come into the camp.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>They said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="Philistines">
    <text>«Woe to us! For there has not been such a thing before.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="Philistines">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>Woe to us! Who shall deliver us out of the hand of these mighty gods? These are the gods that struck the Egyptians with all kinds of plagues in the wilderness.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="Philistines">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>Be strong, and behave like men, O you Philistines, that you not be servants to the Hebrews, as they have been to you. Strengthen yourselves like men, and fight!»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>The Philistines fought, and Israel was struck, and they fled every man to his tent: and there was a very great slaughter; for there fell of Israel thirty thousand footmen.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>The ark of God was taken; and the two sons of Eli, Hophni and Phinehas, were slain.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>There ran a man of Benjamin out of the army, and came to Shiloh the same day, with his clothes torn, and with earth on his head.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>When he came, behold, Eli was sitting on his seat by the road watching; for his heart trembled for the ark of God. When the man came into the city, and told it, all the city cried out.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>When Eli heard the noise of the crying, he said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="Eli">
    <text>«What does the noise of this tumult mean?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>The man hurried, and came and told Eli. </text>
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>Now Eli was ninety-eight years old; and his eyes were set, so that he could not see. </text>
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>The man said to Eli,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="Benjamite messenger to Eli">
    <text>«I am he who came out of the army, and I fled today out of the army.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>He said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="Eli">
    <text>«How did the matter go, my son?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>He who brought the news answered,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="Benjamite messenger to Eli">
    <text>«Israel has fled before the Philistines, and there has been also a great slaughter among the people. Your two sons also, Hophni and Phinehas, are dead, and the ark of God has been captured.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>It happened, when he made mention of the ark of God, that Eli fell from off his seat backward by the side of the gate; and his neck broke, and he died; for he was an old man, and heavy. He had judged Israel forty years.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>His daughter-in-law, Phinehas’ wife, was with child, near to be delivered. When she heard the news that the ark of God was taken, and that her father-in-law and her husband were dead, she bowed herself and brought forth; for her pains came on her.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>About the time of her death the women who stood by her said to her,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="attendents of Phineas' wife" delivery="encouraging">
    <text>«Don't be afraid; for you have brought forth a son.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>But she didn’t answer, neither did she regard it. </text>
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>She named the child Ichabod, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="Phineas' wife (daughter-in-law of Eli)" delivery="mourning">
    <text>«The glory has departed from Israel;»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>because the ark of God was taken, and because of her father-in-law and her husband. </text>
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>She said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="Phineas' wife (daughter-in-law of Eli)" delivery="mourning">
    <text>«The glory has departed from Israel; for the ark of God is taken.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" book="1SA" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1SA">
    <text>5</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Now the Philistines had taken the ark of God, and they brought it from Ebenezer to Ashdod.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>The Philistines took the ark of God, and brought it into the house of Dagon, and set it by Dagon.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>When they of Ashdod arose early on the next day, behold, Dagon was fallen on his face to the ground before the ark of God. They took Dagon, and set him in his place again.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>When they arose early on the next day morning, behold, Dagon was fallen on his face to the ground before the ark of God; and the head of Dagon and both the palms of his hands lay cut off on the threshold; only the stump of Dagon was left to him.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>Therefore neither the priests of Dagon, nor any who come into Dagon’s house, tread on the threshold of Dagon in Ashdod, to this day.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>But the hand of God was heavy on them of Ashdod, and he destroyed them, and struck them with tumors, even Ashdod and its borders.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>When the men of Ashdod saw that it was so, they said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="men of Ashdod">
    <text>«The ark of the God of Israel shall not stay with us; for his hand is severe on us, and on Dagon our god.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>They sent therefore and gathered all the lords of the Philistines to them, and said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="Philistine rulers">
    <text>«What shall we do with the ark of the God of Israel?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>They answered,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="Philistine rulers">
    <text>«Let the ark of the God of Israel be carried over to Gath.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>They carried the ark of the God of Israel there.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>It was so, that after they had carried it about, the hand of God was against the city with a very great confusion: and he struck the men of the city, both small and great; and tumors broke out on them.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>So they sent the ark of God to Ekron. It happened, as the ark of God came to Ekron, that the Ekronites cried out, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="Ekron, people of">
    <text>«They have brought about the ark of the God of Israel to us, to kill us and our people.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>They sent therefore and gathered together all the lords of the Philistines, and they said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="Ekron, people of">
    <text>«Send away the ark of the God of Israel, and let it go again to its own place, that it not kill us and our people.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>For there was a deadly confusion throughout all the city; the hand of God was very heavy there.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>The men who didn’t die were struck with the tumors; and the cry of the city went up to heaven.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="6" book="1SA" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1SA">
    <text>6</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>The ark of God was in the country of the Philistines seven months.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>The Philistines called for the priests and the diviners, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="Philistines">
    <text>«What shall we do with the ark of God? Show us with which we shall send it to its place.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>They said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="Philistine priests and fortune tellers">
    <text>«If you send away the ark of the God of Israel, don't send it empty; but by all means return him a trespass offering: then you shall be healed, and it shall be known to you why his hand is not removed from you.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>Then they said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="Philistines">
    <text>«What shall be the trespass offering which we shall return to him?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>They said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="Philistine priests and fortune tellers">
    <text>«Five golden tumors, and five golden mice, according to the number of the lords of the Philistines; for one plague was on you all, and on your lords.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="Philistine priests and fortune tellers">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>Therefore you shall make images of your tumors, and images of your mice that mar the land; and you shall give glory to the God of Israel: perhaps he will lighten his hand from off you, and from off your gods, and from off your land.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="Philistine priests and fortune tellers">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>Why then do you harden your hearts, as the Egyptians and Pharaoh hardened their hearts? When he had worked wonderfully among them, didn’t they let the people go, and they departed?</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="Philistine priests and fortune tellers">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>Now therefore take and prepare yourselves a new cart, and two milk cows, on which there has come no yoke; and tie the cows to the cart, and bring their calves home from them;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="Philistine priests and fortune tellers">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>and take the ark of God, and lay it on the cart; and put the jewels of gold, which you return him for a trespass offering, in a coffer by its side; and send it away, that it may go.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="Philistine priests and fortune tellers">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>Behold; if it goes up by the way of its own border to Beth Shemesh, then he has done us this great evil: but if not, then we shall know that it is not his hand that struck us; it was a chance that happened to us.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>The men did so, and took two milk cows, and tied them to the cart, and shut up their calves at home;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>and they put the ark of God on the cart, and the coffer with the mice of gold and the images of their tumors.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>The cows took the straight way by the way to Beth Shemesh; they went along the highway, lowing as they went, and didn’t turn aside to the right hand or to the left; and the lords of the Philistines went after them to the border of Beth Shemesh.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>They of Beth Shemesh were reaping their wheat harvest in the valley; and they lifted up their eyes, and saw the ark, and rejoiced to see it.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>The cart came into the field of Joshua of Beth Shemesh, and stood there, where there was a great stone: and they split the wood of the cart, and offered up the cows for a burnt offering to God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>The Levites took down the ark of God, and the coffer that was with it, in which the jewels of gold were, and put them on the great stone: and the men of Beth Shemesh offered burnt offerings and sacrificed sacrifices the same day to God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>When the five lords of the Philistines had seen it, they returned to Ekron the same day.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>These are the golden tumors which the Philistines returned for a trespass offering to God: for Ashdod one, for Gaza one, for Ashkelon one, for Gath one, for Ekron one;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>and the golden mice, according to the number of all the cities of the Philistines belonging to the five lords, both of fortified cities and of country villages, even to the great stone, whereon they set down the ark of God, which stone remains to this day in the field of Joshua of Beth Shemesh.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>He struck of the men of Beth Shemesh, because they had looked into the ark of God, he struck of the people fifty thousand seventy men; and the people mourned, because God had struck the people with a great slaughter. </text>
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>The men of Beth Shemesh said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="Beth Shemesh, men of">
    <text>«Who is able to stand before God, this holy God? To whom shall he go up from us?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>They sent messengers to the inhabitants of Kiriath Jearim, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="Beth Shemesh, messenger from">
    <text>«The Philistines have brought back the ark of God; come down, and bring it up to yourselves.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="7" book="1SA" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1SA">
    <text>7</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>The men of Kiriath Jearim came, and fetched up the ark of God, and brought it into the house of Abinadab in the hill, and sanctified Eleazar his son to keep the ark of God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>It happened, from the day that the ark stayed in Kiriath Jearim, that the time was long; for it was twenty years: and all the house of Israel lamented after God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>Samuel spoke to all the house of Israel, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="Samuel">
    <text>«If you do return to God with all your heart, then put away the foreign gods and the Ashtaroth from among you, and direct your hearts to God, and serve him only; and he will deliver you out of the hand of the Philistines.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>Then the children of Israel did put away the Baals and the Ashtaroth, and served God only. </text>
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>Samuel said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="Samuel">
    <text>«Gather all Israel to Mizpah, and I will pray for you to God.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>They gathered together to Mizpah, and drew water, and poured it out before God, and fasted on that day, and said there,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="Israelites">
    <text>«We have sinned against God.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>Samuel judged the children of Israel in Mizpah.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>When the Philistines heard that the children of Israel were gathered together at Mizpah, the lords of the Philistines went up against Israel. When the children of Israel heard it, they were afraid of the Philistines.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>The children of Israel said to Samuel,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="Israelites">
    <text>«Don't cease to cry to God our God for us, that he will save us out of the hand of the Philistines.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>Samuel took a suckling lamb, and offered it for a whole burnt offering to God: and Samuel cried to God for Israel; and God answered him.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>As Samuel was offering up the burnt offering, the Philistines drew near to battle against Israel; but God thundered with a great thunder on that day on the Philistines, and confused them; and they were struck down before Israel.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>The men of Israel went out of Mizpah, and pursued the Philistines, and struck them, until they came under Beth Kar.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>Then Samuel took a stone, and set it between Mizpah and Shen, and called its name Ebenezer, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="Samuel">
    <text>«God helped us until now.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>So the Philistines were subdued, and they came no more within the border of Israel. The hand of God was against the Philistines all the days of Samuel.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>The cities which the Philistines had taken from Israel were restored to Israel, from Ekron even to Gath; and its border did Israel deliver out of the hand of the Philistines. There was peace between Israel and the Amorites.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>Samuel judged Israel all the days of his life.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>He went from year to year in circuit to Bethel and Gilgal, and Mizpah; and he judged Israel in all those places.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>His return was to Ramah, for there was his house; and there he judged Israel: and he built there an altar to God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="8" book="1SA" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1SA">
    <text>8</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>It happened, when Samuel was old, that he made his sons judges over Israel.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>Now the name of his firstborn was Joel; and the name of his second, Abijah: they were judges in Beersheba.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>His sons didn’t walk in his ways, but turned aside after lucre, and took bribes, and perverted justice.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>Then all the elders of Israel gathered themselves together, and came to Samuel to Ramah; </text>
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>and they said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="elders of Israel">
    <text>«Behold, you are old, and your sons don't walk in your ways: now make us a king to judge us like all the nations.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>But the thing displeased Samuel, when they said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="elders of Israel">
    <text>«Give us a king to judge us.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>Samuel prayed to God. </text>
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>God said to Samuel,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="God">
    <text>«Listen to the voice of the people in all that they tell you; for they have not rejected you, but they have rejected me, that I should not be king over them.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="God">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>According to all the works which they have done since the day that I brought them up out of Egypt even to this day, in that they have forsaken me, and served other gods, so do they also to you.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="God">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>Now therefore listen to their voice: however you shall protest solemnly to them, and shall show them the way of the king who shall reign over them.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>Samuel told all the words of God to the people who asked of him a king. </text>
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>He said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="Samuel">
    <text>«This will be the way of the king who shall reign over you: he will take your sons, and appoint them to him, for his chariots, and to be his horsemen; and they shall run before his chariots;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="Samuel">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>and he will appoint them to him for captains of thousands, and captains of fifties; and he will set some to plow his ground, and to reap his harvest, and to make his instruments of war, and the instruments of his chariots.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="Samuel">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>He will take your daughters to be perfumers, and to be cooks, and to be bakers.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="Samuel">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>He will take your fields, and your vineyards, and your olive groves, even the best of them, and give them to his servants.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="Samuel">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>He will take the tenth of your seed, and of your vineyards, and give to his officers, and to his servants.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="Samuel">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>He will take your male servants, and your female servants, and your best young men, and your donkeys, and put them to his work.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="Samuel">
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>He will take the tenth of your flocks: and you shall be his servants.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="Samuel">
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>You shall cry out in that day because of your king whom you shall have chosen you; and God will not answer you in that day.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>But the people refused to listen to the voice of Samuel; and they said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="Israelites">
    <text>«No; but we will have a king over us, </text>
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>that we also may be like all the nations, and that our king may judge us, and go out before us, and fight our battles.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>Samuel heard all the words of the people, and he rehearsed them in the ears of God. </text>
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>God said to Samuel,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="God">
    <text>«Listen to their voice, and make them a king.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>Samuel said to the men of Israel,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="Samuel">
    <text>«Every man go to his city.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="9" book="1SA" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1SA">
    <text>9</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Now there was a man of Benjamin, whose name was Kish, the son of Abiel, the son of Zeror, the son of Becorath, the son of Aphiah, the son of a Benjamite, a mighty man of valor.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>He had a son, whose name was Saul, an impressive young man; and there was not among the children of Israel a better person than he. From his shoulders and upward he was higher than any of the people.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>The donkeys of Kish, Saul’s father, were lost. Kish said to Saul his son,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="Kish, father of Saul">
    <text>«Take now one of the servants with you, and arise, go seek the donkeys.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>He passed through the hill country of Ephraim, and passed through the land of Shalishah, but they didn’t find them: then they passed through the land of Shaalim, and there they weren’t there: and he passed through the land of the Benjamites, but they didn’t find them.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>When they had come to the land of Zuph, Saul said to his servant who was with him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="Saul">
    <text>«Come, and let us return, lest my father stop caring about the donkeys, and be anxious for us.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>He said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="servant of Saul">
    <text>«See now, there is in this city a man of God, and he is a man who is held in honor. All that he says comes surely to pass. Now let us go there. Perhaps he can tell us concerning our journey whereon we go.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>Then Saul said to his servant,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="Saul">
    <text>«But, behold, if we go, what shall we bring the man? For the bread is spent in our vessels, and there is not a present to bring to the man of God. What do we have?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>The servant answered Saul again, and said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="servant of Saul">
    <text>«Behold, I have in my hand the fourth part of a shekel of silver. I will give that to the man of God, to tell us our way.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>(In earlier times in Israel, when a man went to inquire of God, thus he said, «Come, and let us go to the seer;» for he who is now called a prophet was before called a Seer.)</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>Then Saul said to his servant,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="Saul">
    <text>«Well said. Come, let us go.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>So they went to the city where the man of God was. </text>
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>As they went up the ascent to the city, they found young maidens going out to draw water, and said to them,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="Saul/Saul's servant">
    <text>«Is the seer here?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>They answered them, and said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="young women (maidens)">
    <text>«He is. Behold, he is before you. Hurry now, for he has come today into the city; for the people have a sacrifice today in the high place.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="young women (maidens)">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>As soon as you have come into the city, you shall immediately find him, before he goes up to the high place to eat; for the people will not eat until he come, because he blesses the sacrifice. Afterwards those who are invited eat. Now therefore go up; for at this time you shall find him.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>They went up to the city; and as they came within the city, behold, Samuel came out toward them, to go up to the high place.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>Now God had revealed to Samuel a day before Saul came, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="God">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>Tomorrow about this time I will send you a man out of the land of Benjamin, and you shall anoint him to be prince over my people Israel; and he shall save my people out of the hand of the Philistines: for I have looked on my people, because their cry has come to me.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>When Samuel saw Saul, God said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="God">
    <text>«Behold, the man of whom I spoke to you! this same shall have authority over my people.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>Then Saul drew near to Samuel in the gate, and said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="Saul">
    <text>«Please tell me where the seer's house is.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>Samuel answered Saul, and said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="Samuel">
    <text>«I am the seer. Go up before me to the high place, for you shall eat with me today. In the morning I will let you go, and will tell you all that is in your heart.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="Samuel">
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>As for your donkeys who were lost three days ago, don’t set your mind on them; for they are found. For whom is all that is desirable in Israel? Is it not for you, and for all your father’s house?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>Saul answered,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="Saul">
    <text>«Am I not a Benjamite, of the smallest of the tribes of Israel? And my family the least of all the families of the tribe of Benjamin? Why then do you speak to me like this?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>Samuel took Saul and his servant, and brought them into the guest room, and made them sit in the best place among those who were invited, who were about thirty persons. </text>
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>Samuel said to the cook,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="Samuel">
    <text>«Bring the portion which I gave you, of which I said to you, ‹Set it aside.› »</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="24" />
    <text>The cook took up the thigh, and that which was on it, and set it before Saul. Samuel said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="Samuel">
    <text>«Behold, that which has been reserved! Set it before yourself and eat; because for the appointed time has it been kept for you, for I said, ‹I have invited the people.› »</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>So Saul ate with Samuel that day. </text>
    <verse num="25" />
    <text>When they had come down from the high place into the city, he talked with Saul on the housetop.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="26" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="26" />
    <text>They arose early: and it happened about the spring of the day, that Samuel called to Saul on the housetop, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="26" characterId="Samuel">
    <text>«Get up, that I may send you away.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="26" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>Saul arose, and they went out both of them, he and Samuel, abroad. </text>
    <verse num="27" />
    <text>As they were going down at the end of the city, Samuel said to Saul,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="27" characterId="Samuel">
    <text>«Tell the servant pass on before us» «but stand still first, that I may cause you to hear the word of God.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="10" book="1SA" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1SA">
    <text>10</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Then Samuel took the vial of oil, and poured it on his head, and kissed him, and said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="Samuel">
    <text>«Isn't it that God has anointed you to be prince over his inheritance?</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="Samuel">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>When you have departed from me today, then you shall find two men by Rachel’s tomb, in the border of Benjamin at Zelzah; and they will tell you, ‹The donkeys which you went to seek have been found; and behold, your father has stopped caring about the donkeys, and is anxious for you, saying, «What shall I do for my son?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="Samuel">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>Then you shall go on forward from there, and you shall come to the oak of Tabor; and three men shall meet you there going up to God to Bethel, one carrying three young goats, and another carrying three loaves of bread, and another carrying a bottle of wine:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="Samuel">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>and they will greet you, and give you two loaves of bread, which you shall receive of their hand.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="Samuel">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>After that you shall come to the hill of God, where is the garrison of the Philistines: and it shall happen, when you have come there to the city, that you shall meet a band of prophets coming down from the high place with a psaltery, and a tambourine, and a pipe, and a harp, before them; and they will be prophesying:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="Samuel">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>and the Spirit of God will come mightily on you, and you shall prophesy with them, and shall be turned into another man.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="Samuel">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>Let it be, when these signs have come to you, that you do as occasion shall serve you; for God is with you.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="Samuel">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>You shall go down before me to Gilgal; and behold, I will come down to you, to offer burnt offerings, and to sacrifice sacrifices of peace offerings: you shall wait seven days, until I come to you, and show you what you shall do.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>It was so, that when he had turned his back to go from Samuel, God gave him another heart: and all those signs happened that day.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>When they came there to the hill, behold, a band of prophets met him; and the Spirit of God came mightily on him, and he prophesied among them.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>It happened, when all who knew him before saw that, behold, he prophesied with the prophets, then the people said one to another,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="people who had known Saul">
    <text>«What is this that is come to the son of Kish? Is Saul also among the prophets?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>One of the same place answered,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="man of Gibeah">
    <text>«Who is their father?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>Therefore it became a proverb,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="saying about Saul">
    <text>«Is Saul also among the prophets?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>When he had made an end of prophesying, he came to the high place. </text>
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>Saul’s uncle said to him and to his servant,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="Saul's uncle">
    <text>«Where did you go?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>He said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="Saul">
    <text>«To seek the donkeys. When we saw that they were not found, we came to Samuel.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>Saul’s uncle said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="Saul's uncle">
    <text>«Please tell me what Samuel said to you.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>Saul said to his uncle,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="Saul">
    <text>«He told us plainly that the donkeys were found.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>But concerning the matter of the kingdom, of which Samuel spoke, he didn’t tell him. </text>
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>Samuel called the people together to God to Mizpah; </text>
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>and he said to the children of Israel,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="Samuel">
    <text>«Thus says God, the God of Israel, ‹I brought up Israel out of Egypt, and I delivered you out of the hand of the Egyptians, and out of the hand of all the kingdoms that oppressed you:›</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="Samuel">
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>but you have this day rejected your God, who himself saves you out of all your calamities and your distresses; and you have said to him, ‹No, but set a king over us.› Now therefore present yourselves before God by your tribes, and by your thousands.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>So Samuel brought all the tribes of Israel near, and the tribe of Benjamin was taken.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>He brought the tribe of Benjamin near by their families; and the family of the Matrites was taken; and Saul the son of Kish was taken: but when they sought him, he could not be found. </text>
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>Therefore they asked of God further,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="Israelites">
    <text>«Is there yet a man to come here?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>God answered,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="God">
    <text>«Behold, he has hidden himself among the baggage.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>They ran and fetched him there; and when he stood among the people, he was higher than any of the people from his shoulders and upward. </text>
    <verse num="24" />
    <text>Samuel said to all the people,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="Samuel">
    <text>«You see him whom God has chosen, that there is none like him among all the people?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>All the people shouted, and said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="Israelites" delivery="shouting">
    <text>«Long live the king!»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="25" />
    <text>Then Samuel told the people the regulations of the kingdom, and wrote it in a book, and laid it up before God. Samuel sent all the people away, every man to his house.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="26" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="26" />
    <text>Saul also went to his house to Gibeah; and there went with him the army, whose hearts God had touched. </text>
    <verse num="27" />
    <text>But certain worthless fellows said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="27" characterId="troublemakers">
    <text>«How shall this man save us?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="27" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>They despised him, and brought him no present. But he held his peace.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="11" book="1SA" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1SA">
    <text>11</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Then Nahash the Ammonite came up, and encamped against Jabesh Gilead: and all the men of Jabesh said to Nahash,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="men of Jabesh">
    <text>«Make a covenant with us, and we will serve you.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>Nahash the Ammonite said to them,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="Nahash the Ammonite">
    <text>«On this condition I will make it with you, that all your right eyes be put out; and I will lay it for a reproach on all Israel.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>The elders of Jabesh said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="elders of Jabesh">
    <text>«Give us seven day, that we may send messengers to all the borders of Israel; and then, if there is no one to save us, we will come out to you.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>Then the messengers came to Gibeah of Saul, and spoke these words in the ears of the people: and all the people lifted up their voice, and wept.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>Behold, Saul came following the oxen out of the field; and Saul said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="Saul">
    <text>«What ails the people that they weep?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>They told him the words of the men of Jabesh.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>The Spirit of God came mightily on Saul when he heard those words, and his anger was kindled greatly.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>He took a yoke of oxen, and cut them in pieces, and sent them throughout all the borders of Israel by the hand of messengers, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="messengers of Saul">
    <text>«Whoever doesn't come forth after Saul and after Samuel, so shall it be done to his oxen.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>The dread of God fell on the people, and they came out as one man.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>He numbered them in Bezek; and the children of Israel were three hundred thousand, and the men of Judah thirty thousand. </text>
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>They said to the messengers who came,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="Saul/Israel, men of">
    <text>«Thus you shall tell the men of Jabesh Gilead, ‹Tomorrow, by the time the sun is hot, you shall have deliverance.› »</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>The messengers came and told the men of Jabesh; and they were glad. </text>
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>Therefore the men of Jabesh said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="men of Jabesh">
    <text>«Tomorrow we will come out to you, and you shall do with us all that seems good to you.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>It was so on the next day, that Saul put the people in three companies; and they came into the midst of the camp in the morning watch, and struck the Ammonites until the heat of the day: and it happened, that those who remained were scattered, so that no two of them were left together. </text>
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>The people said to Samuel,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="Israelites">
    <text>«Who is he who said, ‹Shall Saul reign over us?› Bring those men, that we may put them to death!»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>Saul said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="Saul">
    <text>«There shall not a man be put to death this day; for today God has worked deliverance in Israel.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>Then Samuel said to the people,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="Samuel">
    <text>«Come, and let us go to Gilgal, and renew the kingdom there.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>All the people went to Gilgal; and there they made Saul king before God in Gilgal; and there they offered sacrifices of peace offerings before God; and there Saul and all the men of Israel rejoiced greatly.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="12" book="1SA" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1SA">
    <text>12</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Samuel said to all Israel,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="Samuel">
    <text>«Behold, I have listened to your voice in all that you said to me, and have made a king over you.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="Samuel">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>Now, behold, the king walks before you; and I am old and gray-headed; and behold, my sons are with you: and I have walked before you from my youth to this day.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="Samuel">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>Here I am. Witness against me before God, and before his anointed. Whose ox have I taken? Whose donkey have I taken? Whom have I defrauded? Whom have I oppressed? Of whose hand have I taken a ransom to blind my eyes therewith? I will restore it to you.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>They said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="Israel, all">
    <text>«You have not defrauded us, nor oppressed us, neither have you taken anything of any man's hand.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>He said to them,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="Samuel">
    <text>«God is witness against you, and his anointed is witness this day, that you have not found anything in my hand.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>They said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="Israel, all">
    <text>«He is witness.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>Samuel said to the people,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="Samuel">
    <text>«It is God who appointed Moses and Aaron, and that brought your fathers up out of the land of Egypt.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="Samuel">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>Now therefore stand still, that I may plead with you before God concerning all the righteous acts of God, which he did to you and to your fathers.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="Samuel">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>When Jacob was come into Egypt, and your fathers cried to God, then God sent Moses and Aaron, who brought forth your fathers out of Egypt, and made them to dwell in this place.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="Samuel">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>But they forgot God their God; and he sold them into the hand of Sisera, captain of the army of Hazor, and into the hand of the Philistines, and into the hand of the king of Moab; and they fought against them.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="Samuel">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>They cried to God, and said, ‹We have sinned, because we have forsaken God, and have served the Baals and the Ashtaroth: but now deliver us out of the hand of our enemies, and we will serve you.›</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="Samuel">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>God sent Jerubbaal, and Bedan, and Jephthah, and Samuel, and delivered you out of the hand of your enemies on every side; and you lived in safety.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="Samuel">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>When you saw that Nahash the king of the children of Ammon came against you, you said to me, ‹No, but a king shall reign over us;› when God your God was your king.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="Samuel">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>Now therefore see the king whom you have chosen, and whom you have asked for: and behold, God has set a king over you.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="Samuel">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>If you will fear God, and serve him, and listen to his voice, and not rebel against the commandment of God, and both you and also the king who reigns over you are followers of God your God, well:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="Samuel">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>but if you will not listen to the voice of God, but rebel against the commandment of God, then will the hand of God be against you, as it was against your fathers.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="Samuel">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>Now therefore stand still and see this great thing, which God will do before your eyes.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="Samuel">
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>Isn’t it wheat harvest today? I will call to God, that he may send thunder and rain; and you shall know and see that your wickedness is great, which you have done in the sight of God, in asking for a king.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>So Samuel called to God; and God sent thunder and rain that day: and all the people greatly feared God and Samuel. </text>
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>All the people said to Samuel,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="Israel, all">
    <text>«Pray for your servants to God your God, that we not die; for we have added to all our sins this evil, to ask us a king.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>Samuel said to the people,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="Samuel">
    <text>«Don't be afraid. You have indeed done all this evil; yet don't turn aside from following God, but serve God with all your heart.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="Samuel">
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>Don’t turn aside; for then you would go after vain things which can’t profit nor deliver, for they are vain.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="Samuel">
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>For God will not forsake his people for his great name’s sake, because it has pleased God to make you a people to himself.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="Samuel">
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>Moreover as for me, far be it from me that I should sin against God in ceasing to pray for you: but I will instruct you in the good and the right way.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="Samuel">
    <verse num="24" />
    <text>Only fear God, and serve him in truth with all your heart; for consider how great things he has done for you.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="Samuel">
    <verse num="25" />
    <text>But if you shall still do wickedly, you shall be consumed, both you and your king.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="13" book="1SA" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1SA">
    <text>13</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Saul was forty years old when he began to reign; and when he had reigned two years over Israel,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>Saul chose him three thousand men of Israel, of which two thousand were with Saul in Michmash and in the Mount of Bethel, and one thousand were with Jonathan in Gibeah of Benjamin: and the rest of the people he sent every man to his tent.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>Jonathan struck the garrison of the Philistines that was in Geba: and the Philistines heard of it. Saul blew the trumpet throughout all the land, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="Saul">
    <text>«Let the Hebrews hear!»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>All Israel heard that Saul had struck the garrison of the Philistines, and also that Israel was had in abomination with the Philistines. The people were gathered together after Saul to Gilgal.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>The Philistines assembled themselves together to fight with Israel, thirty thousand chariots, and six thousand horsemen, and people as the sand which is on the seashore in multitude: and they came up, and encamped in Michmash, eastward of Beth Aven.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>When the men of Israel saw that they were in a strait (for the people were distressed), then the people did hide themselves in caves, and in thickets, and in rocks, and in coverts, and in pits.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>Now some of the Hebrews had gone over the Jordan to the land of Gad and Gilead; but as for Saul, he was yet in Gilgal, and all the people followed him trembling.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>He stayed seven days, according to the set time that Samuel had appointed: but Samuel didn’t come to Gilgal; and the people were scattered from him. </text>
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>Saul said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="Saul">
    <text>«Bring here the burnt offering to me, and the peace offerings.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>He offered the burnt offering. </text>
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>It came to pass that as soon as he had made an end of offering the burnt offering, behold, Samuel came; and Saul went out to meet him, that he might greet him. </text>
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>Samuel said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="Samuel">
    <text>«What have you done?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>Saul said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="Saul">
    <text>«Because I saw that the people were scattered from me, and that you didn't come within the days appointed, and that the Philistines assembled themselves together at Michmash;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="Saul">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>therefore I said, ‹Now the Philistines will come down on me to Gilgal, and I haven’t entreated the favor of God.› I forced myself therefore, and offered the burnt offering.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>Samuel said to Saul,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="Samuel">
    <text>«You have done foolishly. You have not kept the commandment of God your God, which he commanded you; for now God would have established your kingdom on Israel forever.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="Samuel">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>But now your kingdom shall not continue. God has sought for himself a man after his own heart, and God has appointed him to be prince over his people, because you have not kept that which God commanded you.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>Samuel arose, and went from Gilgal to Gibeah of Benjamin. Saul numbered the people who were present with him, about six hundred men.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>Saul, and Jonathan his son, and the people who were present with them, stayed in Geba of Benjamin: but the Philistines encamped in Michmash.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>The spoilers came out of the camp of the Philistines in three companies: one company turned to the way that leads to Ophrah, to the land of Shual; </text>
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>and another company turned the way to Beth Horon; and another company turned the way of the border that looks down on the valley of Zeboim toward the wilderness.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>Now there was no smith found throughout all the land of Israel; for the Philistines said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="Philistines">
    <text>«Lest the Hebrews make them swords or spears;»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>but all the Israelites went down to the Philistines, to sharpen every man his plowshare, mattock, axe, and sickle;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>yet they had a file for the mattocks, and for the plowshares, and for the forks, and for the axes, and to set the goads.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>So it came to pass in the day of battle, that there was neither sword nor spear found in the hand of any of the people who were with Saul and Jonathan: but with Saul and with Jonathan his son was there found.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>The garrison of the Philistines went out to the pass of Michmash.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="14" book="1SA" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1SA">
    <text>14</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Now it fell on a day, that Jonathan the son of Saul said to the young man who bore his armor,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="Jonathan">
    <text>«Come, and let us go over to the Philistines’ garrison, that is on the other side.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>But he didn't tell his father.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>Saul stayed in the uttermost part of Gibeah under the pomegranate tree which is in Migron: and the people who were with him were about six hundred men;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>and Ahijah, the son of Ahitub, Ichabod’s brother, the son of Phinehas, the son of Eli, the priest of God in Shiloh, wearing an ephod. The people didn’t know that Jonathan was gone.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>Between the passes, by which Jonathan sought to go over to the Philistines’ garrison, there was a rocky crag on the one side, and a rocky crag on the other side: and the name of the one was Bozez, and the name of the other Seneh.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>The one crag rose up on the north in front of Michmash, and the other on the south in front of Geba. </text>
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>Jonathan said to the young man who bore his armor,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="Jonathan">
    <text>«Come, and let us go over to the garrison of these uncircumcised. It may be that God will work for us; for there is no restraint on God to save by many or by few.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>His armor bearer said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="Jonathan's armor bearer">
    <text>«Do all that is in your heart. Turn and, behold, I am with you according to your heart.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>Then Jonathan said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="Jonathan">
    <text>«Behold, we will pass over to the men, and we will reveal ourselves to them.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="Jonathan">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>If they say thus to us, ‹Wait until we come to you!› then we will stand still in our place, and will not go up to them.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="Jonathan">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>But if they say this, ‹Come up to us!› then we will go up; for God has delivered them into our hand. This shall be the sign to us.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>Both of them revealed themselves to the garrison of the Philistines: and the Philistines said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="Philistines">
    <text>«Behold, the Hebrews are coming out of the holes where they had hidden themselves!»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>The men of the garrison answered Jonathan and his armor bearer, and said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="Philistines">
    <text>«Come up to us, and we will show you something!»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>Jonathan said to his armor bearer,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="Jonathan">
    <text>«Come up after me; for God has delivered them into the hand of Israel.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>Jonathan climbed up on his hands and on his feet, and his armor bearer after him: and they fell before Jonathan; and his armor bearer killed them after him.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>That first slaughter, which Jonathan and his armor bearer made, was about twenty men, within as it were half a furrow’s length in an acre of land.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>There was a trembling in the camp, in the field, and among all the people; the garrison, and the spoilers, they also trembled; and the earth quaked: so there was an exceeding great trembling.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>The watchmen of Saul in Gibeah of Benjamin looked; and behold, the multitude melted away, and they went here and there. </text>
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>Then Saul said to the people who were with him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="Saul">
    <text>«Count now, and see who is missing from us.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>When they had counted, behold, Jonathan and his armor bearer were not there. </text>
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>Saul said to Ahijah,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="Saul">
    <text>«Bring the ark of God here.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>For the ark of God was there at that time with the children of Israel. </text>
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>It happened, while Saul talked to the priest, that the tumult that was in the camp of the Philistines went on and increased: and Saul said to the priest,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="Saul">
    <text>«Withdraw your hand!»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>Saul and all the people who were with him were gathered together, and came to the battle: and behold, every man’s sword was against his fellow, and there was a very great confusion.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>Now the Hebrews who were with the Philistines as before, and who went up with them into the camp, from the country all around, even they also turned to be with the Israelites who were with Saul and Jonathan.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>Likewise all the men of Israel who had hidden themselves in the hill country of Ephraim, when they heard that the Philistines fled, even they also followed hard after them in the battle.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>So God saved Israel that day: and the battle passed over by Beth Aven.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="24" />
    <text>The men of Israel were distressed that day; for Saul had adjured the people, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="Saul">
    <text>«Cursed is the man who eats any food until it is evening, and I am avenged of my enemies.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>So none of the people tasted food. </text>
    <verse num="25" />
    <text>All the people came into the forest; and there was honey on the ground.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="26" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="26" />
    <text>When the people were come to the forest, behold, the honey dropped: but no man put his hand to his mouth; for the people feared the oath.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="27" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="27" />
    <text>But Jonathan didn’t hear when his father commanded the people with the oath: therefore he put forth the end of the rod who was in his hand, and dipped it in the honeycomb, and put his hand to his mouth; and his eyes were enlightened. </text>
    <verse num="28" />
    <text>Then one of the people answered, and said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="28" characterId="Israelite soldier in Saul's army">
    <text>«Your father directly commanded the people with an oath, saying, ‹Cursed is the man who eats food this day.› » The people were faint.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="29" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="29" />
    <text>Then Jonathan said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="29" characterId="Jonathan">
    <text>«My father has troubled the land. Please look how my eyes have been enlightened, because I tasted a little of this honey.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="30" characterId="Jonathan">
    <verse num="30" />
    <text>How much more, if perhaps the people had eaten freely today of the spoil of their enemies which they found? For now has there been no great slaughter among the Philistines.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="31" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="31" />
    <text>They struck of the Philistines that day from Michmash to Aijalon. The people were very faint;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="32" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="32" />
    <text>and the people flew on the spoil, and took sheep, and cattle, and calves, and killed them on the ground; and the people ate them with the blood.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="33" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="33" />
    <text>Then they told Saul, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="33" characterId="messengers to Saul">
    <text>«Behold, the people are sinning against God, in that they eat meat with the blood.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="33" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>He said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="33" characterId="Saul">
    <text>«You have dealt treacherously. Roll a large stone to me this day!»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="34" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="34" />
    <text>Saul said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="34" characterId="Saul">
    <text>«Disperse yourselves among the people, and tell them, ‹Bring me here every man his ox, and every man his sheep, and kill them here, and eat; and don’t sin against God in eating meat with the blood.› »</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="34" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>All the people brought every man his ox with him that night, and killed them there.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="35" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="35" />
    <text>Saul built an altar to God. This was the first altar that he built to God. </text>
    <verse num="36" />
    <text>Saul said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="36" characterId="Saul">
    <text>«Let us go down after the Philistines by night, and take spoil among them until the morning light, and let us not leave a man of them.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="36" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>They said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="36" characterId="Israelites (soldiers)">
    <text>«Do whatever seems good to you.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="36" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>Then the priest said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="36" characterId="Ahijah the priest">
    <text>«Let us draw near here to God.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="37" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="37" />
    <text>Saul asked counsel of God,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="37" characterId="Saul">
    <text>«Shall I go down after the Philistines? Will you deliver them into the hand of Israel?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="37" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>But he didn’t answer him that day. </text>
    <verse num="38" />
    <text>Saul said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="38" characterId="Saul">
    <text>«Draw near here, all you chiefs of the people; and know and see in which this sin has been this day.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="39" characterId="Saul">
    <verse num="39" />
    <text>For, as God lives, who saves Israel, though it is in Jonathan my son, he shall surely die.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="39" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>But there was not a man among all the people who answered him. </text>
    <verse num="40" />
    <text>Then he said to all Israel,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="40" characterId="Saul">
    <text>«You be on one side, and I and Jonathan my son will be on the other side.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="40" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>The people said to Saul,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="40" characterId="Israelites (soldiers)">
    <text>«Do what seems good to you.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="41" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="41" />
    <text>Therefore Saul said to God, the God of Israel,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="41" characterId="Saul">
    <text>«Show the right.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="41" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>Jonathan and Saul were chosen; but the people escaped. </text>
    <verse num="42" />
    <text>Saul said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="42" characterId="Saul">
    <text>«Cast lots between me and Jonathan my son.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="42" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>Jonathan was selected. </text>
    <verse num="43" />
    <text>Then Saul said to Jonathan,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="43" characterId="Saul">
    <text>«Tell me what you have done!»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="43" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>Jonathan told him, and said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="43" characterId="Jonathan">
    <text>«I certainly did taste a little honey with the end of the rod that was in my hand; and behold, I must die.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="44" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="44" />
    <text>Saul said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="44" characterId="Saul">
    <text>«God do so and more also; for you shall surely die, Jonathan.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="45" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="45" />
    <text>The people said to Saul,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="45" characterId="Israelites (soldiers)">
    <text>«Shall Jonathan die, who has worked this great salvation in Israel? Far from it! As God lives, there shall not one hair of his head fall to the ground; for he has worked with God this day!»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="45" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>So the people rescued Jonathan, that he didn't die.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="46" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="46" />
    <text>Then Saul went up from following the Philistines; and the Philistines went to their own place.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="47" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="47" />
    <text>Now when Saul had taken the kingdom over Israel, he fought against all his enemies on every side, against Moab, and against the children of Ammon, and against Edom, and against the kings of Zobah, and against the Philistines: and wherever he turned himself, he put them to the worse.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="48" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="48" />
    <text>He did valiantly, and struck the Amalekites, and delivered Israel out of the hands of those who despoiled them.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="49" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="49" />
    <text>Now the sons of Saul were Jonathan, and Ishvi, and Malchishua; and the names of his two daughters were these: the name of the firstborn Merab, and the name of the younger Michal:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="50" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="50" />
    <text>and the name of Saul’s wife was Ahinoam the daughter of Ahimaaz. The name of the captain of his army was Abner the son of Ner, Saul’s uncle.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="51" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="51" />
    <text>Kish was the father of Saul; and Ner the father of Abner was the son of Abiel.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="52" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="52" />
    <text>There was severe war against the Philistines all the days of Saul: and when Saul saw any mighty man, or any valiant man, he took him to him.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="15" book="1SA" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1SA">
    <text>15</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Samuel said to Saul,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="Samuel">
    <text>«God sent me to anoint you to be king over his people, over Israel. Now therefore listen to the voice of the words of God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="Samuel">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>Thus says God of Armies, ‹I have marked that which Amalek did to Israel, how he set himself against him in the way, when he came up out of Egypt.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="Samuel">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>Now go and strike Amalek, and utterly destroy all that they have, and don’t spare them; but kill both man and woman, infant and nursing baby, ox and sheep, camel and donkey.› »</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>Saul summoned the people, and numbered them in Telaim, two hundred thousand footmen, and ten thousand men of Judah.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>Saul came to the city of Amalek, and laid wait in the valley. </text>
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>Saul said to the Kenites,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="Saul">
    <text>«Go, depart, go down from among the Amalekites, lest I destroy you with them; for you showed kindness to all the children of Israel, when they came up out of Egypt.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>So the Kenites departed from among the Amalekites.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>Saul struck the Amalekites, from Havilah as you go to Shur, that is before Egypt.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>He took Agag the king of the Amalekites alive, and utterly destroyed all the people with the edge of the sword.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>But Saul and the people spared Agag, and the best of the sheep, and of the cattle, and of the fatlings, and the lambs, and all that was good, and wouldn’t utterly destroy them: but everything that was vile and refuse, that they destroyed utterly.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>Then the word of God came to Samuel, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="God">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>It grieves me that I have set up Saul to be king; for he is turned back from following me, and has not performed my commandments.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>Samuel was angry; and he cried to God all night. </text>
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>Samuel rose early to meet Saul in the morning; and it was told Samuel, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="person who told Samuel where Saul was">
    <text>«Saul came to Carmel, and behold, he set up a monument for himself, and turned, and passed on, and went down to Gilgal.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>Samuel came to Saul; and Saul said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="Saul">
    <text>«You are blessed by God! I have performed the commandment of God.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>Samuel said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="Samuel">
    <text>«Then what does this bleating of the sheep in my ears, and the lowing of the cattle which I hear mean?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>Saul said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="Saul">
    <text>«They have brought them from the Amalekites; for the people spared the best of the sheep and of the cattle, to sacrifice to God your God. We have utterly destroyed the rest.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>Then Samuel said to Saul,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="Samuel">
    <text>«Stay, and I will tell you what God has said to me last night.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>He said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="Saul">
    <text>«Say on.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>Samuel said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="Samuel">
    <text>«Though you were little in your own sight, weren't you made the head of the tribes of Israel? God anointed you king over Israel;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="Samuel">
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>and God sent you on a journey, and said, ‹Go, and utterly destroy the sinners the Amalekites, and fight against them until they are consumed.›</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="Samuel">
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>Why then didn’t you obey the voice of God, but took the spoils, and did that which was evil in the sight of God?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>Saul said to Samuel,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="Saul">
    <text>«But I have obeyed the voice of God, and have gone the way which God sent me, and have brought Agag the king of Amalek, and have utterly destroyed the Amalekites.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="Saul">
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>But the people took of the spoil, sheep and cattle, the chief of the devoted things, to sacrifice to God your God in Gilgal.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>Samuel said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="Samuel">
    <text>«Has God as great delight in burnt offerings and sacrifices, as in obeying the voice of God? Behold, to obey is better than sacrifice, and to listen than the fat of rams.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="Samuel">
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>For rebellion is as the sin of witchcraft, and stubbornness is as idolatry and teraphim. Because you have rejected the word of God, he has also rejected you from being king.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="24" />
    <text>Saul said to Samuel,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="Saul">
    <text>«I have sinned; for I have transgressed the commandment of God, and your words, because I feared the people, and obeyed their voice.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="Saul">
    <verse num="25" />
    <text>Now therefore, please pardon my sin, and turn again with me, that I may worship God.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="26" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="26" />
    <text>Samuel said to Saul,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="26" characterId="Samuel">
    <text>«I will not return with you; for you have rejected the word of God, and God has rejected you from being king over Israel.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="27" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="27" />
    <text>As Samuel turned about to go away, Saul grabbed the skirt of his robe, and it tore. </text>
    <verse num="28" />
    <text>Samuel said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="28" characterId="Samuel">
    <text>«God has torn the kingdom of Israel from you this day, and has given it to a neighbor of yours who is better than you.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="29" characterId="Samuel">
    <verse num="29" />
    <text>Also the Strength of Israel will not lie nor repent; for he is not a man, that he should repent.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="30" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="30" />
    <text>Then he said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="30" characterId="Saul">
    <text>«I have sinned: yet please honor me now before the elders of my people, and before Israel, and come back with me, that I may worship God your God.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="31" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="31" />
    <text>So Samuel went back with Saul; and Saul worshiped God. </text>
    <verse num="32" />
    <text>Then Samuel said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="32" characterId="Samuel">
    <text>«Bring here to me Agag the king of the Amalekites!»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="32" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>Agag came to him cheerfully. Agag said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="32" characterId="Agag, king of the Amalekites">
    <text>«Surely the bitterness of death is past.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="33" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="33" />
    <text>Samuel said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="33" characterId="Samuel">
    <text>«As your sword has made women childless, so your mother will be childless among women!»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="33" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>Samuel cut Agag in pieces before God in Gilgal.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="34" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="34" />
    <text>Then Samuel went to Ramah; and Saul went up to his house to Gibeah of Saul.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="35" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="35" />
    <text>Samuel came no more to see Saul until the day of his death; for Samuel mourned for Saul: and God grieved that he had made Saul king over Israel.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="16" book="1SA" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1SA">
    <text>16</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>God said to Samuel,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="God">
    <text>«How long will you mourn for Saul, since I have rejected him from being king over Israel? Fill your horn with oil, and go. I will send you to Jesse the Bethlehemite; for I have provided a king for myself among his sons.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>Samuel said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="Samuel">
    <text>«How can I go? If Saul hears it, he will kill me.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>God said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="God">
    <text>«Take a heifer with you, and say, I have come to sacrifice to God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="God">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>Call Jesse to the sacrifice, and I will show you what you shall do. You shall anoint to me him whom I name to you.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>Samuel did that which God spoke, and came to Bethlehem. The elders of the city came to meet him trembling, and said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="Bethlehem, elders of" delivery="trembled">
    <text>«Do you come peaceably?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>He said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="Samuel">
    <text>«Peaceably; I have come to sacrifice to God. Sanctify yourselves, and come with me to the sacrifice.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>He sanctified Jesse and his sons, and called them to the sacrifice. </text>
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>It happened, when they had come, that he looked at Eliab, and said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="Samuel" delivery="thought">
    <text>«Surely God's anointed is before him.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>But God said to Samuel,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="God">
    <text>«Don’t look on his face, or on the height of his stature; because I have rejected him: for God sees not as man sees; for man looks at the outward appearance, but God looks at the heart.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>Then Jesse called Abinadab, and made him pass before Samuel. He said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="Samuel">
    <text>«Neither has God chosen this one.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>Then Jesse made Shammah to pass by. He said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="Samuel">
    <text>«Neither has God chosen this one.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>Jesse made seven of his sons to pass before Samuel. Samuel said to Jesse,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="Samuel">
    <text>«God has not chosen these.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>Samuel said to Jesse,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="Samuel">
    <text>«Are all your children here?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>He said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="Jesse">
    <text>«There remains yet the youngest, and behold, he is keeping the sheep.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>Samuel said to Jesse,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="Samuel">
    <text>«Send and get him; for we will not sit down until he comes here.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>He sent, and brought him in. Now he was ruddy, and withal of a beautiful face, and goodly to look on. God said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="God">
    <text>«Arise, anoint him; for this is he.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>Then Samuel took the horn of oil, and anointed him in the midst of his brothers: and the Spirit of God came mightily on David from that day forward. So Samuel rose up, and went to Ramah.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>Now the Spirit of God departed from Saul, and an evil spirit from God troubled him. </text>
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>Saul’s servants said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="Saul's attendants">
    <text>«See now, an evil spirit from God troubles you.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="Saul's attendants">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>Let our lord now command your servants who are before you, to seek out a man who is a skillful player on the harp. It shall happen, when the evil spirit from God is on you, that he shall play with his hand, and you shall be well.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>Saul said to his servants,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="Saul">
    <text>«Provide me now a man who can play well, and bring him to me.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>Then one of the young men answered, and said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="Saul's servant">
    <text>«Behold, I have seen a son of Jesse the Bethlehemite, who is skillful in playing, a mighty man of valor, a man of war, prudent in speech, and a comely person; and God is with him.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>Therefore Saul sent messengers to Jesse, and said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="Saul">
    <text>«Send me David your son, who is with the sheep.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>Jesse took a donkey loaded with bread, and a bottle of wine, and a young goat, and sent them by David his son to Saul.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>David came to Saul, and stood before him. He loved him greatly; and he became his armor bearer.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>Saul sent to Jesse, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="Saul">
    <text>«Please let David stand before me; for he has found favor in my sight.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>It happened, when the evil spirit from God was on Saul, that David took the harp, and played with his hand: so Saul was refreshed, and was well, and the evil spirit departed from him.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="17" book="1SA" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1SA">
    <text>17</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Now the Philistines gathered together their armies to battle; and they were gathered together at Socoh, which belongs to Judah, and encamped between Socoh and Azekah, in Ephesdammim.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>Saul and the men of Israel were gathered together, and encamped in the valley of Elah, and set the battle in array against the Philistines.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>The Philistines stood on the mountain on the one side, and Israel stood on the mountain on the other side: and there was a valley between them.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>There went out a champion out of the camp of the Philistines, named Goliath, of Gath, whose height was six cubits and a span.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>He had a helmet of brass on his head, and he was clad with a coat of mail; and the weight of the coat was five thousand shekels of brass.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>He had brass shin armor on his legs, and a javelin of brass between his shoulders.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>The staff of his spear was like a weaver’s beam; and his spear’s head weighed six hundred shekels of iron: and his shield bearer went before him.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>He stood and cried to the armies of Israel, and said to them,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="Goliath, Philistine champion">
    <text>«Why have you come out to set your battle in array? Am I not a Philistine, and you servants to Saul? Choose a man for yourselves, and let him come down to me.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="Goliath, Philistine champion">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>If he be able to fight with me, and kill me, then will we be your servants; but if I prevail against him, and kill him, then you will be our servants, and serve us.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>The Philistine said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="Goliath, Philistine champion">
    <text>«I defy the armies of Israel this day! Give me a man, that we may fight together!»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>When Saul and all Israel heard those words of the Philistine, they were dismayed, and greatly afraid.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>Now David was the son of that Ephrathite of Bethlehem Judah, whose name was Jesse; and he had eight sons: and the man was an old man in the days of Saul, stricken in years among men.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>The three eldest sons of Jesse had gone after Saul to the battle: and the names of his three sons who went to the battle were Eliab the firstborn, and next to him Abinadab, and the third Shammah.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>David was the youngest; and the three eldest followed Saul.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>Now David went back and forth from Saul to feed his father’s sheep at Bethlehem.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>The Philistine drew near morning and evening, and presented himself forty days. </text>
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>Jesse said to David his son,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="Jesse">
    <text>«Now take for your brothers an ephah of this parched grain, and these ten loaves, and carry them quickly to the camp to your brothers;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="Jesse">
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>and bring these ten cheeses to the captain of their thousand, and see how your brothers are doing, and bring back news.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>Now Saul, and they, and all the men of Israel, were in the valley of Elah, fighting with the Philistines.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>David rose up early in the morning, and left the sheep with a keeper, and took, and went, as Jesse had commanded him; and he came to the place of the wagons, as the army which was going forth to the fight shouted for the battle.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>Israel and the Philistines put the battle in array, army against army.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>David left his baggage in the hand of the keeper of the baggage, and ran to the army, and came and greeted his brothers.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>As he talked with them, behold, there came up the champion, the Philistine of Gath, Goliath by name, out of the ranks of the Philistines, and spoke according to the same words: and David heard them.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="24" />
    <text>All the men of Israel, when they saw the man, fled from him, and were terrified. </text>
    <verse num="25" />
    <text>The men of Israel said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="Israelites (soldiers)">
    <text>«Have you seen this man who is come up? He has surely come up to defy Israel. It shall be, that the man who kills him, the king will enrich him with great riches, and will give him his daughter, and make his father's house free in Israel.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="26" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="26" />
    <text>David spoke to the men who stood by him, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="26" characterId="David">
    <text>«What shall be done to the man who kills this Philistine, and takes away the reproach from Israel? For who is this uncircumcised Philistine, that he should defy the armies of the living God?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="27" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="27" />
    <text>The people answered him in this way, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="27" characterId="men (soldiers) standing near David">
    <text>«So shall it be done to the man who kills him.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="28" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="28" />
    <text>Eliab his eldest brother heard when he spoke to the men; and Eliab’s anger was kindled against David, and he said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="28" characterId="Eliab, David's brother">
    <text>«Why have you come down? With whom have you left those few sheep in the wilderness? I know your pride, and the naughtiness of your heart; for you have come down that you might see the battle.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="29" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="29" />
    <text>David said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="29" characterId="David">
    <text>«What have I now done? Is there not a cause?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="30" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="30" />
    <text>He turned away from him toward another, and spoke like that again; and the people answered him again the same way.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="31" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="31" />
    <text>When the words were heard which David spoke, they rehearsed them before Saul; and he sent for him. </text>
    <verse num="32" />
    <text>David said to Saul,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="32" characterId="David">
    <text>«Let no man's heart fail because of him. Your servant will go and fight with this Philistine.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="33" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="33" />
    <text>Saul said to David,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="33" characterId="Saul">
    <text>«You are not able to go against this Philistine to fight with him; for you are but a youth, and he a man of war from his youth.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="34" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="34" />
    <text>David said to Saul,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="34" characterId="David">
    <text>«Your servant was keeping his father’s sheep; and when a lion or a bear came, and took a lamb out of the flock, </text>
    <verse num="35" />
    <text>I went out after him, and struck him, and rescued it out of his mouth. When he arose against me, I caught him by his beard, and struck him, and killed him.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="36" characterId="David">
    <verse num="36" />
    <text>Your servant struck both the lion and the bear. This uncircumcised Philistine shall be as one of them, since he has defied the armies of the living God.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="37" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="37" />
    <text>David said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="37" characterId="David">
    <text>«God who delivered me out of the paw of the lion, and out of the paw of the bear, he will deliver me out of the hand of this Philistine.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="37" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>Saul said to David,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="37" characterId="Saul">
    <text>«Go; and God shall be with you.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="38" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="38" />
    <text>Saul dressed David with his clothing. He put a helmet of brass on his head, and he clad him with a coat of mail.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="39" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="39" />
    <text>David strapped his sword on his clothing, and he tried to move; for he had not tested it. David said to Saul,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="39" characterId="David">
    <text>«I can't go with these; for I have not tested them.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="39" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>David took them off. </text>
    <verse num="40" />
    <text>He took his staff in his hand, and chose for himself five smooth stones out of the brook, and put them in the shepherd’s bag which he had, even in his wallet. His sling was in his hand; and he drew near to the Philistine.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="41" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="41" />
    <text>The Philistine came on and drew near to David; and the man who bore the shield went before him.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="42" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="42" />
    <text>When the Philistine looked about, and saw David, he disdained him; for he was but a youth, and ruddy, and withal of a fair face.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="43" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="43" />
    <text>The Philistine said to David,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="43" characterId="Goliath, Philistine champion">
    <text>«Am I a dog, that you come to me with sticks?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="43" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>The Philistine cursed David by his gods. </text>
    <verse num="44" />
    <text>The Philistine said to David,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="44" characterId="Goliath, Philistine champion">
    <text>«Come to me, and I will give your flesh to the birds of the sky, and to the animals of the field.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="45" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="45" />
    <text>Then David said to the Philistine,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="45" characterId="David">
    <text>«You come to me with a sword, and with a spear, and with a javelin: but I come to you in the name of God of Armies, the God of the armies of Israel, whom you have defied.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="46" characterId="David">
    <verse num="46" />
    <text>Today, God will deliver you into my hand. I will strike you, and take your head from off you. I will give the dead bodies of the army of the Philistines this day to the birds of the sky, and to the wild animals of the earth; that all the earth may know that there is a God in Israel, </text>
    <verse num="47" />
    <text>and that all this assembly may know that God doesn’t save with sword and spear: for the battle is God’s, and he will give you into our hand.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="48" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="48" />
    <text>It happened, when the Philistine arose, and came and drew near to meet David, that David hurried, and ran toward the army to meet the Philistine.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="49" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="49" />
    <text>David put his hand in his bag, took a stone, and slung it, and struck the Philistine in his forehead; and the stone sank into his forehead, and he fell on his face to the earth.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="50" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="50" />
    <text>So David prevailed over the Philistine with a sling and with a stone, and struck the Philistine, and killed him; but there was no sword in the hand of David.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="51" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="51" />
    <text>Then David ran, and stood over the Philistine, and took his sword, and drew it out of its sheath, and killed him, and cut off his head therewith. When the Philistines saw that their champion was dead, they fled.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="52" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="52" />
    <text>The men of Israel and of Judah arose, and shouted, and pursued the Philistines, until you come to Gai, and to the gates of Ekron. The wounded of the Philistines fell down by the way to Shaaraim, even to Gath, and to Ekron.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="53" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="53" />
    <text>The children of Israel returned from chasing after the Philistines, and they plundered their camp.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="54" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="54" />
    <text>David took the head of the Philistine, and brought it to Jerusalem; but he put his armor in his tent.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="55" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="55" />
    <text>When Saul saw David go forth against the Philistine, he said to Abner, the captain of the army,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="55" characterId="Saul">
    <text>«Abner, whose son is this youth?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="55" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>Abner said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="55" characterId="Abner, commander of Saul's army">
    <text>«As your soul lives, O king, I can't tell.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="56" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="56" />
    <text>The king said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="56" characterId="Saul">
    <text>«Inquire whose son the young man is!»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="57" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="57" />
    <text>As David returned from the slaughter of the Philistine, Abner took him, and brought him before Saul with the head of the Philistine in his hand. </text>
    <verse num="58" />
    <text>Saul said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="58" characterId="Saul">
    <text>«Whose son are you, you young man?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="58" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>David answered,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="58" characterId="David">
    <text>«I am the son of your servant Jesse the Bethlehemite.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="18" book="1SA" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1SA">
    <text>18</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>It happened, when he had made an end of speaking to Saul, that the soul of Jonathan was knit with the soul of David, and Jonathan loved him as his own soul.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>Saul took him that day, and would let him go no more home to his father’s house.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>Then Jonathan and David made a covenant, because he loved him as his own soul.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>Jonathan stripped himself of the robe that was on him, and gave it to David, and his clothing, even to his sword, and to his bow, and to his sash.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>David went out wherever Saul sent him, and behaved himself wisely: and Saul set him over the men of war, and it was good in the sight of all the people, and also in the sight of Saul’s servants.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>It happened as they came, when David returned from the slaughter of the Philistine, that the women came out of all the cities of Israel, singing and dancing, to meet king Saul, with tambourines, with joy, and with instruments of music.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>The women sang one to another as they played, and said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="women, dancing" delivery="joyfully singing">
    <text>«Saul has slain his thousands, David his ten thousands.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>Saul was very angry, and this saying displeased him; and he said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="Saul" delivery="thought">
    <text>«They have ascribed to David ten thousands, and to me they have ascribed but thousands. What can he have more but the kingdom?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>Saul eyed David from that day and forward.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>It happened on the next day, that an evil spirit from God came mightily on Saul, and he prophesied in the midst of the house. David played with his hand, as he did day by day. Saul had his spear in his hand; </text>
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>and Saul threw the spear; for he said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="Saul">
    <text>«I will pin David even to the wall!»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>David escaped from his presence twice. </text>
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>Saul was afraid of David, because God was with him, and was departed from Saul.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>Therefore Saul removed him from him, and made him his captain over a thousand; and he went out and came in before the people.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>David behaved himself wisely in all his ways; and God was with him.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>When Saul saw that he behaved himself very wisely, he stood in awe of him.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>But all Israel and Judah loved David; for he went out and came in before them. </text>
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>Saul said to David,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="Saul">
    <text>«Behold, my elder daughter Merab, I will give her to you as wife. Only be valiant for me, and fight God's battles.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>For Saul said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="Saul">
    <text>«Don't let my hand be on him, but let the hand of the Philistines be on him.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>David said to Saul,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="David">
    <text>«Who am I, and what is my life, or my father's family in Israel, that I should be son-in-law to the king?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>But it happened at the time when Merab, Saul’s daughter, should have been given to David, that she was given to Adriel the Meholathite as wife.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>Michal, Saul’s daughter, loved David; and they told Saul, and the thing pleased him. </text>
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>Saul said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="Saul">
    <text>I will give her to him, that she may be a snare to him, and that the hand of the Philistines may be against him.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>Therefore Saul said to David,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="Saul">
    <text>«You shall this day be my son-in-law a second time.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>Saul commanded his servants,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="Saul">
    <text>«Talk with David secretly, and say, ‹Behold, the king has delight in you, and all his servants love you: now therefore be the king’s son-in-law.› »</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>Saul’s servants spoke those words in the ears of David. David said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="David">
    <text>«Does it seem to you a light thing to be the king's son-in-law, since I am a poor man, and lightly esteemed?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="24" />
    <text>The servants of Saul told him, saying, «David spoke like this.» </text>
    <verse num="25" />
    <text>Saul said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="Saul">
    <text>«You shall tell David, ‹The king desires no dowry except one hundred foreskins of the Philistines, to be avenged of the king’s enemies.› »</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>Now Saul thought to make David fall by the hand of the Philistines.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="26" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="26" />
    <text>When his servants told David these words, it pleased David well to be the king’s son-in-law. The days were not expired;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="27" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="27" />
    <text>and David arose and went, he and his men, and killed of the Philistines two hundred men; and David brought their foreskins, and they gave them in full number to the king, that he might be the king’s son-in-law. Saul gave him Michal his daughter as wife.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="28" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="28" />
    <text>Saul saw and knew that God was with David; and Michal, Saul’s daughter, loved him. </text>
    <verse num="29" />
    <text>Saul was yet the more afraid of David; and Saul was David’s enemy continually.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="30" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="30" />
    <text>Then the princes of the Philistines went forth: and it happened, as often as they went forth, that David behaved himself more wisely than all the servants of Saul; so that his name was highly esteemed.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="19" book="1SA" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1SA">
    <text>19</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Saul spoke to Jonathan his son, and to all his servants, that they should kill David. But Jonathan, Saul’s son, delighted much in David. </text>
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>Jonathan told David, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="Jonathan">
    <text>«Saul my father seeks to kill you. Now therefore, please take care of yourself in the morning, and live in a secret place, and hide yourself.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="Jonathan">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>I will go out and stand beside my father in the field where you are, and I will talk with my father about you; and if I see anything, I will tell you.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>Jonathan spoke good of David to Saul his father, and said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="Jonathan">
    <text>«Don't let the king sin against his servant, against David; because he has not sinned against you, and because his works have been very good toward you;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="Jonathan">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>for he put his life in his hand, and struck the Philistine, and God worked a great victory for all Israel. You saw it, and rejoiced. Why then will you sin against innocent blood, to kill David without a cause?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>Saul listened to the voice of Jonathan: and Saul swore,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="Saul">
    <text>«As God lives, he shall not be put to death.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>Jonathan called David, and Jonathan showed him all those things. Jonathan brought David to Saul, and he was in his presence, as before.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>There was war again. David went out, and fought with the Philistines, and killed them with a great slaughter; and they fled before him.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>An evil spirit from God was on Saul, as he sat in his house with his spear in his hand; and David was playing with his hand.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>Saul sought to pin David even to the wall with the spear; but he slipped away out of Saul’s presence, and he stuck the spear into the wall. David fled, and escaped that night.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>Saul sent messengers to David’s house, to watch him, and to kill him in the morning. Michal, David’s wife, told him, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="Michal, David's wife">
    <text>«If you don't save your life tonight, tomorrow you will be killed.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>So Michal let David down through the window. He went, fled, and escaped.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>Michal took the teraphim, and laid it in the bed, and put a pillow of goats’ hair at its head, and covered it with the clothes.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>When Saul sent messengers to take David, she said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="Michal, David's wife">
    <text>«He is sick.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>Saul sent the messengers to see David, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="Saul">
    <text>«Bring him up to me in the bed, that I may kill him.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>When the messengers came in, behold, the teraphim was in the bed, with the pillow of goats’ hair at its head. </text>
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>Saul said to Michal,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="Saul">
    <text>«Why have you deceived me thus, and let my enemy go, so that he is escaped?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>Michal answered Saul,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="Michal, David's wife">
    <text>«He said to me, ‹Let me go! Why should I kill you?› »</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>Now David fled, and escaped, and came to Samuel to Ramah, and told him all that Saul had done to him. He and Samuel went and lived in Naioth.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>It was told Saul, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="message to Saul">
    <text>«Behold, David is at Naioth in Ramah.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>Saul sent messengers to take David: and when they saw the company of the prophets prophesying, and Samuel standing as head over them, the Spirit of God came on the messengers of Saul, and they also prophesied.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>When it was told Saul, he sent other messengers, and they also prophesied. Saul sent messengers again the third time, and they also prophesied.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>Then went he also to Ramah, and came to the great well that is in Secu: and he asked,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="Saul">
    <text>«Where are Samuel and David?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>One said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="people at cistern">
    <text>«Behold, they are at Naioth in Ramah.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>He went there to Naioth in Ramah. Then the Spirit of God came on him also, and he went on, and prophesied, until he came to Naioth in Ramah.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="24" />
    <text>He also stripped off his clothes, and he also prophesied before Samuel, and lay down naked all that day and all that night. Therefore they say,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="saying about Saul">
    <text>«Is Saul also among the prophets?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="20" book="1SA" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1SA">
    <text>20</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>David fled from Naioth in Ramah, and came and said before Jonathan,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="David">
    <text>«What have I done? What is my iniquity? What is my sin before your father, that he seeks my life?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>He said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="Jonathan">
    <text>«Far from it; you shall not die. Behold, my father does nothing either great or small, but that he discloses it to me; and why should my father hide this thing from me? It is not so.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>David swore moreover, and said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="David">
    <text>«Your father knows well that I have found favor in your eyes; and he says, ‹Don’t let Jonathan know this, lest he be grieved:› but truly as God lives, and as your soul lives, there is but a step between me and death.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>Then Jonathan said to David,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="Jonathan">
    <text>«Whatever your soul desires, I will even do it for you.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>David said to Jonathan,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="David">
    <text>«Behold, tomorrow is the new moon, and I should not fail to dine with the king; but let me go, that I may hide myself in the field to the third day at evening.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="David">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>If your father miss me at all, then say, ‹David earnestly asked leave of me that he might run to Bethlehem his city; for it is the yearly sacrifice there for all the family.›</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="David">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>If he says, ‹It is well;› your servant shall have peace: but if he be angry, then know that evil is determined by him.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="David">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>Therefore deal kindly with your servant; for you have brought your servant into a covenant of God with you: but if there be in me iniquity, kill me yourself; for why should you bring me to your father?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>Jonathan said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="Jonathan">
    <text>«Far be it from you; for if I should at all know that evil were determined by my father to come on you, then wouldn't I tell you that?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>Then David said to Jonathan,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="David">
    <text>«Who shall tell me if perchance your father answers you roughly?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>Jonathan said to David,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="Jonathan">
    <text>«Come, and let us go out into the field.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>They both went out into the field. </text>
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>Jonathan said to David,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="Jonathan">
    <text>«God, the God of Israel, be witness: when I have sounded my father about this time tomorrow, or the third day, behold, if there be good toward David, shall I not then send to you, and disclose it to you?</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="Jonathan">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>God do so to Jonathan, and more also, should it please my father to do you evil, if I don’t disclose it to you, and send you away, that you may go in peace: and God be with you, as he has been with my father.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="Jonathan">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>You shall not only while yet I live show me the loving kindness of God, that I not die;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="Jonathan">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>but also you shall not cut off your kindness from my house forever; no, not when God has cut off the enemies of David everyone from the surface of the earth.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>So Jonathan made a covenant with the house of David, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="Jonathan">
    <text>«God will require it at the hand of David's enemies.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>Jonathan caused David to swear again, for the love that he had to him; for he loved him as he loved his own soul. </text>
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>Then Jonathan said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="Jonathan">
    <text>«Tomorrow is the new moon: and you will be missed, because your seat will be empty.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="Jonathan">
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>When you have stayed three days, you shall go down quickly, and come to the place where you did hide yourself when the business was in hand, and shall remain by the stone Ezel.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="Jonathan">
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>I will shoot three arrows on its side, as though I shot at a mark.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="Jonathan">
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>Behold, I will send the boy, saying, ‹Go, find the arrows!› If I tell the boy, ‹Behold, the arrows are on this side of you. Take them;› then come; for there is peace to you and no hurt, as God lives.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="Jonathan">
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>But if I say this to the boy, ‹Behold, the arrows are beyond you;› then go your way; for God has sent you away.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="Jonathan">
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>Concerning the matter which you and I have spoken of, behold, God is between you and me forever.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="24" />
    <text>So David hid himself in the field: and when the new moon was come, the king sat him down to eat food.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="25" />
    <text>The king sat on his seat, as at other times, even on the seat by the wall; and Jonathan stood up, and Abner sat by Saul’s side: but David’s place was empty.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="26" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="26" />
    <text>Nevertheless Saul didn’t say anything that day: for he thought,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="26" characterId="Saul">
    <text>«Something has happened to him. He is not clean. Surely he is not clean.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="27" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="27" />
    <text>It happened on the next day after the new moon, the second day, that David’s place was empty. Saul said to Jonathan his son,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="27" characterId="Saul">
    <text>«Why doesn't the son of Jesse come to eat, neither yesterday, nor today?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="28" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="28" />
    <text>Jonathan answered Saul,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="28" characterId="Jonathan">
    <text>«David earnestly asked leave of me to go to Bethlehem.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="29" characterId="Jonathan">
    <verse num="29" />
    <text>He said, ‹Please let me go, for our family has a sacrifice in the city. My brother has commanded me to be there. Now, if I have found favor in your eyes, please let me go away and see my brothers.› Therefore he has not come to the king’s table.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="30" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="30" />
    <text>Then Saul’s anger was kindled against Jonathan, and he said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="30" characterId="Saul">
    <text>«You son of a perverse rebellious woman, don't I know that you have chosen the son of Jesse to your own shame, and to the shame of your mother's nakedness?</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="31" characterId="Saul">
    <verse num="31" />
    <text>For as long as the son of Jesse lives on the earth, you shall not be established, nor your kingdom. Therefore now send and bring him to me, for he shall surely die!»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="32" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="32" />
    <text>Jonathan answered Saul his father, and said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="32" characterId="Jonathan">
    <text>«Why should he be put to death? What has he done?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="33" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="33" />
    <text>Saul cast his spear at him to strike him. By this Jonathan knew that his father was determined to put David to death.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="34" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="34" />
    <text>So Jonathan arose from the table in fierce anger, and ate no food the second day of the month; for he was grieved for David, because his father had done him shame.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="35" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="35" />
    <text>It happened in the morning, that Jonathan went out into the field at the time appointed with David, and a little boy with him. </text>
    <verse num="36" />
    <text>He said to his boy,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="36" characterId="Jonathan">
    <text>«Run, find now the arrows which I shoot.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="36" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>As the boy ran, he shot an arrow beyond him.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="37" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="37" />
    <text>When the boy was come to the place of the arrow which Jonathan had shot, Jonathan cried after the boy, and said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="37" characterId="Jonathan">
    <text>«Isn't the arrow beyond you?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="38" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="38" />
    <text>Jonathan cried after the boy,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="38" characterId="Jonathan">
    <text>«Go fast! Hurry! Don't delay!»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="38" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>Jonathan’s boy gathered up the arrows, and came to his master. </text>
    <verse num="39" />
    <text>But the boy didn’t know anything. Only Jonathan and David knew the matter.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="40" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="40" />
    <text>Jonathan gave his weapons to his boy, and said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="40" characterId="Jonathan">
    <text>«Go, carry them to the city.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="41" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="41" />
    <text>As soon as the boy was gone, David arose out of a place toward the South, and fell on his face to the ground, and bowed himself three times. They kissed one another, and wept one with another, and David wept the most. </text>
    <verse num="42" />
    <text>Jonathan said to David,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="42" characterId="Jonathan">
    <text>«Go in peace, because we have both sworn in the name of God, saying, ‹God shall be between me and you, and between my seed and your seed, forever.› »</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="42" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>He arose and departed; and Jonathan went into the city.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="21" book="1SA" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1SA">
    <text>21</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Then came David to Nob to Ahimelech the priest. Ahimelech came to meet David trembling, and said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="Ahimelech the priest (son of Ahitub)">
    <text>«Why are you alone, and no man with you?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>David said to Ahimelech the priest,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="David">
    <text>«The king has commanded me a business, and has said to me, ‹Let no man know anything of the business about which I send you, and what I have commanded you; and I have appointed the young men to such and such a place.›</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="David">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>Now therefore what is under your hand? Give me five loaves of bread in my hand, or whatever there is present.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>The priest answered David, and said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="Ahimelech the priest (son of Ahitub)">
    <text>«There is no common bread under my hand, but there is holy bread; if only the young men have kept themselves from women.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>David answered the priest, and said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="David">
    <text>«Truly, women have been kept from us about these three days. When I came out, the vessels of the young men were holy, though it was but a common journey. How much more then today shall their vessels be holy?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>So the priest gave him holy bread; for there was no bread there but the show bread, that was taken from before God, to put hot bread in the day when it was taken away.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>Now a certain man of the servants of Saul was there that day, detained before God; and his name was Doeg the Edomite, the best of the herdsmen who belonged to Saul. </text>
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>David said to Ahimelech,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="David">
    <text>«Isn't there here under your hand spear or sword? For I have neither brought my sword nor my weapons with me, because the king's business required haste.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>The priest said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="Ahimelech the priest (son of Ahitub)">
    <text>«The sword of Goliath the Philistine, whom you killed in the valley of Elah, behold, it is here wrapped in a cloth behind the ephod. If you will take that, take it; for there is no other except that here.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>David said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="David">
    <text>«There is none like that. Give it to me.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>David arose, and fled that day for fear of Saul, and went to Achish the king of Gath. </text>
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>The servants of Achish said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="servants of Achish, king of Gath">
    <text>«Isn’t this David the king of the land? Didn’t they sing one to another about him in dances, saying, ‹Saul has slain his thousands, David his ten thousands?› »</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>David laid up these words in his heart, and was very afraid of Achish the king of Gath.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>He changed his behavior before them, and pretended to be mad in their hands, and scrabbled on the doors of the gate, and let his spittle fall down on his beard.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>Then Achish said to his servants,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="Achish, king of Gath">
    <text>«Look, you see the man is mad. Why then have you brought him to me?</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="Achish, king of Gath">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>Do I lack madmen, that you have brought this fellow to play the madman in my presence? Shall this fellow come into my house?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="22" book="1SA" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1SA">
    <text>22</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="22" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>David therefore departed there, and escaped to the cave of Adullam. When his brothers and all his father’s house heard it, they went down there to him.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="22" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>Everyone who was in distress, and everyone who was in debt, and everyone who was discontented, gathered themselves to him; and he became captain over them: and there were with him about four hundred men.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="22" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>David went there to Mizpeh of Moab, and he said to the king of Moab,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="22" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="David">
    <text>«Please let my father and my mother come out with you, until I know what God will do for me.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="22" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>He brought them before the king of Moab; and they lived with him all the while that David was in the stronghold. </text>
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>The prophet Gad said to David,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="22" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="Gad the prophet, David's seer">
    <text>«Don't stay in the stronghold. Depart, and go into the land of Judah.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="22" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>Then David departed, and came into the forest of Hereth.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="22" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>Saul heard that David was discovered, and the men who were with him. Now Saul was sitting in Gibeah, under the tamarisk tree in Ramah, with his spear in his hand, and all his servants were standing about him. </text>
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>Saul said to his servants who stood about him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="22" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="Saul">
    <text>«Hear now, you Benjamites! Will the son of Jesse give everyone of you fields and vineyards, will he make you all captains of thousands and captains of hundreds,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="22" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="Saul">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>that all of you have conspired against me, and there is none who discloses to me when my son makes a treaty with the son of Jesse, and there is none of you who is sorry for me, or discloses to me that my son has stirred up my servant against me, to lie in wait, as at this day?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="22" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>Then Doeg the Edomite, who stood by the servants of Saul, answered and said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="22" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="Doeg the Edomite">
    <text>«I saw the son of Jesse coming to Nob, to Ahimelech the son of Ahitub.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="22" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="Doeg the Edomite">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>He inquired of God for him, gave him food, and gave him the sword of Goliath the Philistine.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="22" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>Then the king sent to call Ahimelech the priest, the son of Ahitub, and all his father’s house, the priests who were in Nob: and they came all of them to the king. </text>
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>Saul said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="22" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="Saul">
    <text>«Hear now, you son of Ahitub.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="22" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>He answered,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="22" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="Ahimelech the priest (son of Ahitub)">
    <text>«Here I am, my lord.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="22" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>Saul said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="22" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="Saul">
    <text>«Why have you conspired against me, you and the son of Jesse, in that you have given him bread, and a sword, and have inquired of God for him, that he should rise against me, to lie in wait, as at this day?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="22" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>Then Ahimelech answered the king, and said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="22" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="Ahimelech the priest (son of Ahitub)">
    <text>«Who among all your servants is so faithful as David, who is the king's son-in-law, and is taken into your council, and is honorable in your house?</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="22" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="Ahimelech the priest (son of Ahitub)">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>Have I today begun to inquire of God for him? Be it far from me! Don’t let the king impute anything to his servant, nor to all the house of my father; for your servant knows nothing of all this, less or more.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="22" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>The king said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="22" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="Saul">
    <text>«You shall surely die, Ahimelech, you, and all your father's house.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="22" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>The king said to the guard who stood about him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="22" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="Saul">
    <text>«Turn, and kill the priests of God; because their hand also is with David, and because they knew that he fled, and didn't disclose it to me.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="22" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>But the servants of the king wouldn’t put forth their hand to fall on the priests of God. </text>
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>The king said to Doeg,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="22" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="Saul">
    <text>«Turn and attack the priests!»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="22" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>Doeg the Edomite turned, and he attacked the priests, and he killed on that day eighty-five people who wore a linen ephod.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="22" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>He struck Nob, the city of the priests, with the edge of the sword, both men and women, children and nursing babies, and cattle and donkeys and sheep, with the edge of the sword.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="22" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>One of the sons of Ahimelech, the son of Ahitub, named Abiathar, escaped, and fled after David.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="22" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>Abiathar told David that Saul had slain God’s priests. </text>
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>David said to Abiathar,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="22" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="David">
    <text>«I knew on that day, when Doeg the Edomite was there, that he would surely tell Saul. I am responsible for the death of all the persons of your father's house.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="22" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="David">
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>Stay with me, don’t be afraid; for he who seeks my life seeks your life. For with me you shall be in safeguard.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="23" book="1SA" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1SA">
    <text>23</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>David was told,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="person who told David about Philistines">
    <text>«Behold, the Philistines are fighting against Keilah, and are robbing the threshing floors.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>Therefore David inquired of God, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="David">
    <text>«Shall I go and strike these Philistines?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>God said to David,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="God">
    <text>«Go strike the Philistines, and save Keilah.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>David’s men said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="David's men">
    <text>«Behold, we are afraid here in Judah: how much more then if we go to Keilah against the armies of the Philistines?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>Then David inquired of God yet again. God answered him, and said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="God">
    <text>«Arise, go down to Keilah; for I will deliver the Philistines into your hand.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>David and his men went to Keilah, and fought with the Philistines, and brought away their livestock, and killed them with a great slaughter. So David saved the inhabitants of Keilah.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>It happened, when Abiathar the son of Ahimelech fled to David to Keilah, that he came down with an ephod in his hand.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>It was told Saul that</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="messenger to Saul">
    <text>David had come to Keilah.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>Saul said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="Saul">
    <text>«God has delivered him into my hand; for he is shut in, by entering into a town that has gates and bars.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>Saul summoned all the people to war, to go down to Keilah, to besiege David and his men.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>David knew that Saul was devising mischief against him; and he said to Abiathar the priest,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="David">
    <text>«Bring the ephod here.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>Then David said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="David">
    <text>«O God, the God of Israel, your servant has surely heard that Saul seeks to come to Keilah, to destroy the city for my sake.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="David">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>Will the men of Keilah deliver me up into his hand? Will Saul come down, as your servant has heard? God, the God of Israel, I beg you, tell your servant.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>God said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="God">
    <text>«He will come down.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>Then David said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="David">
    <text>«Will the men of Keilah deliver me and my men into the hand of Saul?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>God said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="God">
    <text>«They will deliver you up.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>Then David and his men, who were about six hundred, arose and departed out of Keilah, and went wherever they could go. It was told Saul that David was escaped from Keilah; and he gave up going there.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>David stayed in the wilderness in the strongholds, and remained in the hill country in the wilderness of Ziph. Saul sought him every day, but God didn’t deliver him into his hand.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>David saw that Saul had come out to seek his life. David was in the wilderness of Ziph in the wood.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>Jonathan, Saul’s son, arose, and went to David into the woods, and strengthened his hand in God. </text>
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>He said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="Jonathan">
    <text>«Don't be afraid; for the hand of Saul my father shall not find you; and you shall be king over Israel, and I shall be next to you; and that also Saul my father knows.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>They both made a covenant before God: and David stayed in the woods, and Jonathan went to his house. </text>
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>Then the Ziphites came up to Saul to Gibeah, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="Ziphites">
    <text>«Doesn't David hide himself with us in the strongholds in the wood, in the hill of Hachilah, which is on the south of the desert?</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="Ziphites">
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>Now therefore, O king, come down, according to all the desire of your soul to come down; and our part shall be to deliver him up into the king’s hand.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>Saul said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="Saul">
    <text>«You are blessed by God; for you have had compassion on me.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="Saul">
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>Please go make yet more sure, and know and see his place where his haunt is, and who has seen him there; for it is told me that he deals very subtly.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="Saul">
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>See therefore, and take knowledge of all the lurking places where he hides himself, and come again to me with certainty, and I will go with you: and it shall happen, if he is in the land, that I will search him out among all the thousands of Judah.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="24" />
    <text>They arose, and went to Ziph before Saul: but David and his men were in the wilderness of Maon, in the Arabah on the south of the desert.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="25" />
    <text>Saul and his men went to seek him. When David was told, he went down to the rock, and stayed in the wilderness of Maon. When Saul heard that, he pursued after David in the wilderness of Maon.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="26" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="26" />
    <text>Saul went on this side of the mountain, and David and his men on that side of the mountain: and David made haste to get away for fear of Saul; for Saul and his men surrounded David and his men to take them. </text>
    <verse num="27" />
    <text>But a messenger came to Saul, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="27" characterId="messenger to Saul">
    <text>«Hurry and come; for the Philistines have made a raid on the land!»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="28" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="28" />
    <text>So Saul returned from pursuing after David, and went against the Philistines: therefore they called that place Sela Hammahlekoth.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="23" initialStartVerse="29" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="29" />
    <text>David went up from there, and lived in the strongholds of En Gedi.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="24" book="1SA" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1SA">
    <text>24</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="24" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>It happened, when Saul was returned from following the Philistines, that it was told him, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="24" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="person who told Saul where David was">
    <text>«Behold, David is in the wilderness of En Gedi.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="24" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>Then Saul took three thousand chosen men out of all Israel, and went to seek David and his men on the rocks of the wild goats.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="24" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>He came to the sheep pens by the way, where there was a cave; and Saul went in to relieve himself. Now David and his men were abiding in the innermost parts of the cave. </text>
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>The men of David said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="24" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="David's men">
    <text>«Behold, the day of which God said to you, ‹Behold, I will deliver your enemy into your hand, and you shall do to him as it shall seem good to you.› »</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="24" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>Then David arose, and cut off the skirt of Saul's robe secretly.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="24" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>It happened afterward, that David’s heart struck him, because he had cut off Saul’s skirt. </text>
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>He said to his men,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="24" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="David">
    <text>«God forbid that I should do this thing to my lord, God's anointed, to put forth my hand against him, since he is God's anointed.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="24" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>So David checked his men with these words, and didn’t allow them to rise against Saul. Saul rose up out of the cave, and went on his way.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="24" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>David also arose afterward, and went out of the cave, and cried after Saul, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="24" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="David">
    <text>«My lord the king!»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="24" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>When Saul looked behind him, David bowed with his face to the earth, and did obeisance. </text>
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>David said to Saul,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="24" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="David">
    <text>«Why do you listen to men’s words, saying, ‹Behold, David seeks your hurt?›</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="24" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="David">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>Behold, this day your eyes have seen how that God had delivered you today into my hand in the cave. Some urged me to kill you; but I spared you; and I said, I will not put forth my hand against my lord; for he is God’s anointed.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="24" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="David">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>Moreover, my father, behold, yes, see the skirt of your robe in my hand; for in that I cut off the skirt of your robe, and didn’t kill you, know and see that there is neither evil nor disobedience in my hand, and I have not sinned against you, though you hunt for my life to take it.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="24" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="David">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>May God judge between me and you, and may God avenge me of you; but my hand shall not be on you.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="24" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="David">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>As the proverb of the ancients says, ‹Out of the wicked comes forth wickedness;› but my hand shall not be on you.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="24" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="David">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>Against whom has the king of Israel come out? Whom do you pursue? A dead dog? A flea?</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="24" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="David">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>May God therefore be judge, and give sentence between me and you, and see, and plead my cause, and deliver me out of your hand.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="24" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>It came to pass, when David had made an end of speaking these words to Saul, that Saul said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="24" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="Saul">
    <text>«Is this your voice, my son David?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="24" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>Saul lifted up his voice, and wept. </text>
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>He said to David,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="24" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="Saul">
    <text>«You are more righteous than I; for you have done good to me, whereas I have done evil to you.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="24" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="Saul">
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>You have declared this day how you have dealt well with me, because when God had delivered me up into your hand, you didn’t kill me.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="24" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="Saul">
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>For if a man finds his enemy, will he let him go away unharmed? Therefore may God reward you good for that which you have done to me this day.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="24" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="Saul">
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>Now, behold, I know that you shall surely be king, and that the kingdom of Israel shall be established in your hand.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="24" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="Saul">
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>Swear now therefore to me by God, that you will not cut off my seed after me, and that you will not destroy my name out of my father’s house.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="24" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>David swore to Saul. Saul went home; but David and his men went up to the stronghold.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="25" book="1SA" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1SA">
    <text>25</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Samuel died; and all Israel gathered themselves together, and lamented him, and buried him in his house at Ramah. David arose, and went down to the wilderness of Paran.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>There was a man in Maon, whose possessions were in Carmel; and the man was very great, and he had three thousand sheep, and a thousand goats: and he was shearing his sheep in Carmel.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>Now the name of the man was Nabal; and the name of his wife Abigail; and the woman was of good understanding, and of a beautiful face: but the man was churlish and evil in his doings; and he was of the house of Caleb.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>David heard in the wilderness that Nabal was shearing his sheep.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>David sent ten young men, and David said to the young men,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="David">
    <text>«Go up to Carmel, and go to Nabal, and greet him in my name.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="David">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>You shall tell him, ‹Long life to you! Peace be to you, and peace be to your house, and peace be to all that you have.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="David">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>Now I have heard that you have shearers. Your shepherds have now been with us, and we did them no hurt, neither was there anything missing to them, all the while they were in Carmel.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="David">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>Ask your young men, and they will tell you. Therefore, let the young men find favor in your eyes; for we come in a good day. Please give whatever comes to your hand, to your servants, and to your son David.› »</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>When David’s young men came, they spoke to Nabal according to all those words in the name of David, and ceased. </text>
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>Nabal answered David’s servants, and said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="Nabal">
    <text>«Who is David? Who is the son of Jesse? There are many servants who break away from their masters these days.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="Nabal">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>Shall I then take my bread, and my water, and my meat that I have killed for my shearers, and give it to men who I don’t know where they come from?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>So David’s young men turned on their way, and went back, and came and told him according to all these words. </text>
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>David said to his men,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="David">
    <text>«Every man put on his sword!»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>Every man put on his sword. David also put on his sword. About four hundred men followed David; and two hundred stayed by the baggage.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>But one of the young men told Abigail, Nabal’s wife, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="servant of Nabal">
    <text>«Behold, David sent messengers out of the wilderness to Greet our master; and he railed at them.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="servant of Nabal">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>But the men were very good to us, and we were not hurt, neither missed we anything, as long as we went with them, when we were in the fields.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="servant of Nabal">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>They were a wall to us both by night and by day, all the while we were with them keeping the sheep.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="servant of Nabal">
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>Now therefore know and consider what you will do; for evil is determined against our master, and against all his house; for he is such a worthless fellow that one can’t speak to him.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>Then Abigail hurried and took two hundred loaves of bread, two bottles of wine, five sheep ready dressed, five measures of parched grain, one hundred clusters of raisins, and two hundred cakes of figs, and laid them on donkeys.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>She said to her young men,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="Abigail">
    <text>«Go on before me. Behold, I come after you.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>But she didn't tell her husband, Nabal.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>It was so, as she rode on her donkey, and came down by the covert of the mountain, that behold, David and his men came down toward her; and she met them. </text>
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>Now David had said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="David" delivery="thinking or talking to himself">
    <text>«Surely in vain have I kept all that this fellow has in the wilderness, so that nothing was missed of all that pertained to him. He has returned me evil for good.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="David" delivery="thinking or talking to himself">
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>God do so to the enemies of David, and more also, if I leave of all that belongs to him by the morning light so much as one who urinates on a wall.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>When Abigail saw David, she hurried, and alighted from her donkey, and fell before David on her face, and bowed herself to the ground. </text>
    <verse num="24" />
    <text>She fell at his feet, and said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="Abigail">
    <text>«On me, my lord, on me be the iniquity; and please let your handmaid speak in your ears. Hear the words of your handmaid.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="Abigail">
    <verse num="25" />
    <text>Please don’t let my lord regard this worthless fellow, even Nabal; for as his name is, so is he. Nabal is his name, and folly is with him; but I, your handmaid, didn’t see the young men of my lord, whom you sent.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="26" characterId="Abigail">
    <verse num="26" />
    <text>Now therefore, my lord, as God lives, and as your soul lives, since God has withheld you from blood guiltiness, and from avenging yourself with your own hand, now therefore let your enemies, and those who seek evil to my lord, be as Nabal.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="27" characterId="Abigail">
    <verse num="27" />
    <text>Now this present which your servant has brought to my lord, let it be given to the young men who follow my lord.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="28" characterId="Abigail">
    <verse num="28" />
    <text>Please forgive the trespass of your handmaid. For God will certainly make my lord a sure house, because my lord fights the battles of God; and evil shall not be found in you all your days.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="29" characterId="Abigail">
    <verse num="29" />
    <text>Though men may rise up to pursue you, and to seek your soul, yet the soul of my lord shall be bound in the bundle of life with God your God. He will sling out the souls of your enemies, as from the hollow of a sling.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="30" characterId="Abigail">
    <verse num="30" />
    <text>It shall come to pass, when God has done to my lord according to all the good that he has spoken concerning you, and shall have appointed you prince over Israel, </text>
    <verse num="31" />
    <text>that this shall be no grief to you, nor offense of heart to my lord, either that you have shed blood without cause, or that my lord has avenged himself. When God has dealt well with my lord, then remember your handmaid.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="32" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="32" />
    <text>David said to Abigail,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="32" characterId="David">
    <text>«Blessed is God, the God of Israel, who sent you this day to meet me!</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="33" characterId="David">
    <verse num="33" />
    <text>Blessed is your discretion, and blessed are you, that have kept me this day from blood guiltiness, and from avenging myself with my own hand.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="34" characterId="David">
    <verse num="34" />
    <text>For indeed, as God, the God of Israel, lives, who has withheld me from hurting you, unless you had hurried and come to meet me, surely there wouldn’t have been left to Nabal by the morning light so much as one who urinates on a wall.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="35" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="35" />
    <text>So David received of her hand that which she had brought him: and he said to her,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="35" characterId="David">
    <text>«Go up in peace to your house. Behold, I have listened to your voice, and have granted your request.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="36" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="36" />
    <text>Abigail came to Nabal; and behold, he held a feast in his house, like the feast of a king. Nabal’s heart was merry within him, for he was very drunken. Therefore she told him nothing, less or more, until the morning light.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="37" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="37" />
    <text>It happened in the morning, when the wine was gone out of Nabal, that his wife told him these things, and his heart died within him, and he became as a stone.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="38" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="38" />
    <text>It happened about ten days after, that God struck Nabal, so that he died. </text>
    <verse num="39" />
    <text>When David heard that Nabal was dead, he said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="39" characterId="David">
    <text>«Blessed is God, who has pleaded the cause of my reproach from the hand of Nabal, and has kept back his servant from evil. God has returned the evildoing of Nabal on his own head.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="39" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>David sent and spoke concerning Abigail, to take her to him as wife. </text>
    <verse num="40" />
    <text>When the servants of David had come to Abigail to Carmel, they spoke to her, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="40" characterId="servants of David">
    <text>«David has sent us to you, to take you to him as wife.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="41" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="41" />
    <text>She arose, and bowed herself with her face to the earth, and said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="41" characterId="Abigail">
    <text>«Behold, your handmaid is a servant to wash the feet of the servants of my lord.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="42" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="42" />
    <text>Abigail hurried, and arose, and rode on a donkey, with five ladies of hers who followed her; and she went after the messengers of David, and became his wife.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="43" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="43" />
    <text>David also took Ahinoam of Jezreel; and they both became his wives.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="25" initialStartVerse="44" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="44" />
    <text>Now Saul had given Michal his daughter, David’s wife, to Palti the son of Laish, who was of Gallim.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="26" book="1SA" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1SA">
    <text>26</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="26" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>The Ziphites came to Saul to Gibeah, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="26" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="Ziphites">
    <text>«Doesn't David hide himself in the hill of Hachilah, which is before the desert?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="26" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>Then Saul arose, and went down to the wilderness of Ziph, having three thousand chosen men of Israel with him, to seek David in the wilderness of Ziph.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="26" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>Saul encamped in the hill of Hachilah, which is before the desert, by the way. But David stayed in the wilderness, and he saw that Saul came after him into the wilderness.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="26" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>David therefore sent out spies, and understood that Saul had certainly come.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="26" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>David arose, and came to the place where Saul had encamped; and David saw the place where Saul lay, and Abner the son of Ner, the captain of his army: and Saul lay within the place of the wagons, and the people were encamped around him.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="26" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>Then answered David and said to Ahimelech the Hittite, and to Abishai the son of Zeruiah, brother to Joab, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="26" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="David">
    <text>«Who will go down with me to Saul to the camp?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="26" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>Abishai said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="26" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="Abishai, Joab's brother">
    <text>«I will go down with you.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="26" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>So David and Abishai came to the people by night: and, behold, Saul lay sleeping within the place of the wagons, with his spear stuck in the ground at his head; and Abner and the people lay around him. </text>
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>Then Abishai said to David,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="26" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="Abishai, Joab's brother">
    <text>«God has delivered up your enemy into your hand this day. Now therefore please let me strike him with the spear to the earth at one stroke, and I will not strike him the second time.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="26" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>David said to Abishai,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="26" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="David">
    <text>«Don't destroy him; for who can put forth his hand against God's anointed, and be guiltless?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="26" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>David said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="26" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="David">
    <text>«As God lives, God will strike him; or his day shall come to die; or he shall go down into battle and perish.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="26" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="David">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>God forbid that I should put forth my hand against God’s anointed; but now please take the spear that is at his head, and the jar of water, and let us go.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="26" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>So David took the spear and the jar of water from Saul’s head; and they went away: and no man saw it, nor knew it, neither did any awake; for they were all asleep, because a deep sleep from God was fallen on them.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="26" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>Then David went over to the other side, and stood on the top of the mountain afar off; a great space being between them;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="26" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>and David cried to the people, and to Abner the son of Ner, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="26" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="David">
    <text>«Don't you answer, Abner?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="26" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>Then Abner answered,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="26" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="Abner, commander of Saul's army">
    <text>«Who are you who cries to the king?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="26" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>David said to Abner,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="26" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="David">
    <text>«Aren't you a man? Who is like you in Israel? Why then have you not kept watch over your lord, the king? For one of the people came in to destroy the king your lord.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="26" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="David">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>This thing isn’t good that you have done. As God lives, you are worthy to die, because you have not kept watch over your lord, God’s anointed. Now see where the king’s spear is, and the jar of water that was at his head.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="26" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>Saul knew David’s voice, and said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="26" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="Saul">
    <text>«Is this your voice, my son David?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="26" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>David said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="26" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="David">
    <text>«It is my voice, my lord, O king.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="26" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>He said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="26" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="David">
    <text>«Why does my lord pursue after his servant? For what have I done? Or what evil is in my hand?</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="26" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="David">
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>Now therefore, please let my lord the king hear the words of his servant. If it is so that God has stirred you up against me, let him accept an offering. But if it is the children of men, they are cursed before God; for they have driven me out this day that I shouldn’t cling to God’s inheritance, saying, ‹Go, serve other gods!›</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="26" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="David">
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>Now therefore, don’t let my blood fall to the earth away from the presence of God; for the king of Israel has come out to seek a flea, as when one hunts a partridge in the mountains.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="26" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>Then Saul said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="26" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="Saul">
    <text>«I have sinned. Return, my son David; for I will no more do you harm, because my life was precious in your eyes this day. Behold, I have played the fool, and have erred exceedingly.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="26" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>David answered,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="26" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="David">
    <text>«Behold the spear, O king! Then let one of the young men come over and get it.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="26" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="David">
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>God will render to every man his righteousness and his faithfulness; because God delivered you into my hand today, and I wouldn’t put forth my hand against God’s anointed.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="26" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="David">
    <verse num="24" />
    <text>Behold, as your life was respected this day in my eyes, so let my life be respected in the eyes of God, and let him deliver me out of all oppression.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="26" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="25" />
    <text>Then Saul said to David,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="26" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="Saul">
    <text>«You are blessed, my son David. You shall both do mightily, and shall surely prevail.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="26" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>So David went his way, and Saul returned to his place.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="27" book="1SA" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1SA">
    <text>27</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="27" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>David said in his heart,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="27" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="David" delivery="thought">
    <text>«I shall now perish one day by the hand of Saul. There is nothing better for me than that I should escape into the land of the Philistines; and Saul will despair of me, to seek me any more in all the borders of Israel. So shall I escape out of his hand.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="27" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>David arose, and passed over, he and the six hundred men who were with him, to Achish the son of Maoch, king of Gath.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="27" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>David lived with Achish at Gath, he and his men, every man with his household, even David with his two wives, Ahinoam the Jezreelitess, and Abigail the Carmelitess, Nabal’s wife.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="27" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>It was told Saul that David was fled to Gath: and he sought no more again for him. </text>
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>David said to Achish,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="27" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="David">
    <text>«If now I have found favor in your eyes, let them give me a place in one of the cities in the country, that I may dwell there. For why should your servant dwell in the royal city with you?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="27" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>Then Achish gave him Ziklag that day: why Ziklag pertains to the kings of Judah to this day.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="27" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>The number of the days that David lived in the country of the Philistines was a full year and four months.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="27" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>David and his men went up, and made a raid on the Geshurites, and the Girzites, and the Amalekites; for those nations were the inhabitants of the land, who were of old, as you go to Shur, even to the land of Egypt.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="27" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>David struck the land, and saved neither man nor woman alive, and took away the sheep, and the cattle, and the donkeys, and the camels, and the clothing; and he returned, and came to Achish. </text>
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>Achish said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="27" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="Achish, king of Gath">
    <text>«Against whom have you made a raid today?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="27" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>David said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="27" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="David">
    <text>«Against the South of Judah, against the South of the Jerahmeelites, and against the South of the Kenites.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="27" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>David saved neither man nor woman alive, to bring them to Gath, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="27" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="David" delivery="thought">
    <text>«Lest they should tell of us, saying, ‹So did David, and so has been his way all the while he has lived in the country of the Philistines.› »</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="27" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>Achish believed David, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="27" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="Achish, king of Gath" delivery="said to himself">
    <text>«He has made his people Israel utterly to abhor him. Therefore he shall be my servant forever.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="28" book="1SA" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1SA">
    <text>28</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="28" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>It happened in those days, that the Philistines gathered their armies together for warfare, to fight with Israel. Achish said to David,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="28" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="Achish, king of Gath">
    <text>«Know assuredly that you shall go out with me in the army, you and your men.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="28" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>David said to Achish,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="28" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="David">
    <text>«Therefore you shall know what your servant will do.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="28" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>Achish said to David,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="28" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="Achish, king of Gath">
    <text>«Therefore will I make you my bodyguard for ever.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="28" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>Now Samuel was dead, and all Israel had lamented him, and buried him in Ramah, even in his own city. Saul had put away those who had familiar spirits, and the wizards, out of the land.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="28" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>The Philistines gathered themselves together, and came and encamped in Shunem: and Saul gathered all Israel together, and they encamped in Gilboa.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="28" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>When Saul saw the army of the Philistines, he was afraid, and his heart trembled greatly.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="28" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>When Saul inquired of God, God didn’t answer him, neither by dreams, nor by Urim, nor by prophets. </text>
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>Then Saul said to his servants,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="28" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="Saul">
    <text>«Seek me a woman who has a familiar spirit, that I may go to her, and inquire of her.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="28" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>His servants said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="28" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="Saul's attendants">
    <text>«Behold, there is a woman who has a familiar spirit at Endor.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="28" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>Saul disguised himself, and put on other clothing, and went, he and two men with him, and they came to the woman by night: and he said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="28" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="Saul">
    <text>«Please divine to me by the familiar spirit, and bring me up whoever I shall name to you.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="28" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>The woman said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="28" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="woman medium">
    <text>«Behold, you know what Saul has done, how he has cut off those who have familiar spirits, and the wizards, out of the land. Why then do you lay a snare for my life, to cause me to die?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="28" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>Saul swore to her by God, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="28" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="Saul">
    <text>«As God lives, no punishment shall happen to you for this thing.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="28" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>Then the woman said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="28" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="woman medium">
    <text>«Whom shall I bring up to you?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="28" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>He said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="28" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="Saul">
    <text>«Bring Samuel up for me.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="28" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>When the woman saw Samuel, she cried with a loud voice; and the woman spoke to Saul, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="28" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="woman medium">
    <text>«Why have you deceived me? For you are Saul!»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="28" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>The king said to her,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="28" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="Saul">
    <text>«Don't be afraid. For what do you see?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="28" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>The woman said to Saul,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="28" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="woman medium">
    <text>«I see a god coming up out of the earth.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="28" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>He said to her,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="28" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="Saul">
    <text>«What does he look like?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="28" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>She said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="28" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="woman medium">
    <text>«An old man comes up. He is covered with a robe.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="28" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>Saul perceived that it was Samuel, and he bowed with his face to the ground, and did obeisance. </text>
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>Samuel said to Saul,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="28" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="Samuel (dead)">
    <text>«Why have you disturbed me, to bring me up?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="28" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>Saul answered,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="28" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="Saul">
    <text>«I am very distressed; for the Philistines make war against me, and God has departed from me, and answers me no more, neither by prophets, nor by dreams. Therefore I have called you, that you may make known to me what I shall do.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="28" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>Samuel said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="28" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="Samuel (dead)">
    <text>«Why then do you ask of me, since God has departed from you and has become your adversary?</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="28" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="Samuel (dead)">
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>God has done to you as he spoke by me. God has torn the kingdom out of your hand, and given it to your neighbor, even to David.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="28" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="Samuel (dead)">
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>Because you didn’t obey the voice of God, and didn’t execute his fierce wrath on Amalek, therefore God has done this thing to you this day.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="28" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="Samuel (dead)">
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>Moreover God will deliver Israel also with you into the hand of the Philistines; and tomorrow you and your sons will be with me. God will deliver the army of Israel also into the hand of the Philistines.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="28" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>Then Saul fell immediately his full length on the earth, and was terrified, because of the words of Samuel. There was no strength in him; for he had eaten no bread all the day, nor all the night.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="28" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>The woman came to Saul, and saw that he was very troubled, and said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="28" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="woman medium">
    <text>«Behold, your handmaid has listened to your voice, and I have put my life in my hand, and have listened to your words which you spoke to me.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="28" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="woman medium">
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>Now therefore, please listen also to the voice of your handmaid, and let me set a morsel of bread before you; and eat, that you may have strength, when you go on your way.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="28" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>But he refused, and said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="28" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="Saul">
    <text>I will not eat.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="28" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>But his servants, together with the woman, constrained him; and he listened to their voice. So he arose from the earth, and sat on the bed.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="28" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="24" />
    <text>The woman had a fattened calf in the house. She hurried and killed it; and she took flour, and kneaded it, and baked unleavened bread of it.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="28" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="25" />
    <text>She brought it before Saul, and before his servants; and they ate. Then they rose up, and went away that night.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="29" book="1SA" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1SA">
    <text>29</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="29" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Now the Philistines gathered together all their armies to Aphek: and the Israelites encamped by the spring which is in Jezreel.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="29" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>The lords of the Philistines passed on by hundreds, and by thousands; and David and his men passed on in the rear with Achish.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="29" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>Then the princes of the Philistines said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="29" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="Philistine commanders">
    <text>«What about these Hebrews?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="29" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>Achish said to the princes of the Philistines,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="29" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="Achish, king of Gath">
    <text>«Isn't this David, the servant of Saul the king of Israel, who has been with me these days, or rather these years, and I have found no fault in him since he fell away to this day?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="29" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>But the princes of the Philistines were angry with him; and the princes of the Philistines said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="29" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="Philistine commanders">
    <text>«Make the man return, that he may go back to his place where you have appointed him, and let him not go down with us to battle, lest in the battle he become an adversary to us. For with what should this fellow reconcile himself to his lord? Should it not be with the heads of these men?</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="29" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="Philistine commanders">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>Is not this David, of whom they sang one to another in dances, saying, ‹Saul has slain his thousands, David his ten thousands?› »</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="29" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>Then Achish called David, and said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="29" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="Achish, king of Gath">
    <text>«As God lives, you have been upright, and your going out and your coming in with me in the army is good in my sight; for I have not found evil in you since the day of your coming to me to this day. Nevertheless, the lords don't favor you.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="29" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="Achish, king of Gath">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>Therefore now return, and go in peace, that you not displease the lords of the Philistines.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="29" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>David said to Achish,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="29" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="David">
    <text>«But what have I done? What have you found in your servant so long as I have been before you to this day, that I may not go and fight against the enemies of my lord the king?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="29" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>Achish answered David,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="29" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="Achish, king of Gath">
    <text>«I know that you are good in my sight, as an angel of God. Notwithstanding the princes of the Philistines have said, ‹He shall not go up with us to the battle.›</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="29" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="Achish, king of Gath">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>Therefore now rise up early in the morning with the servants of your lord who have come with you; and as soon as you are up early in the morning, and have light, depart.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="29" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>So David rose up early, he and his men, to depart in the morning, to return into the land of the Philistines. The Philistines went up to Jezreel.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="30" book="1SA" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1SA">
    <text>30</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="30" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>It happened, when David and his men were come to Ziklag on the third day, that the Amalekites had made a raid on the South, and on Ziklag, and had struck Ziklag, and burned it with fire,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="30" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>and had taken captive the women and all who were therein, both small and great. They didn’t kill any, but carried them off, and went their way.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="30" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>When David and his men came to the city, behold, it was burned with fire; and their wives, and their sons, and their daughters, were taken captive.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="30" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>Then David and the people who were with him lifted up their voice and wept, until they had no more power to weep.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="30" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>David’s two wives were taken captive, Ahinoam the Jezreelitess, and Abigail the wife of Nabal the Carmelite.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="30" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>David was greatly distressed; for the people spoke of stoning him, because the soul of all the people was grieved, every man for his sons and for his daughters: but David strengthened himself in God his God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="30" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>David said to Abiathar the priest, the son of Ahimelech,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="30" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="David">
    <text>«Please bring me here the ephod.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="30" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>Abiathar brought the ephod to David. </text>
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>David inquired of God, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="30" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="David">
    <text>«If I pursue after this troop, shall I overtake them?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="30" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>He answered him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="30" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="God">
    <text>«Pursue; for you shall surely overtake them, and shall without fail recover all.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="30" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>So David went, he and the six hundred men who were with him, and came to the brook Besor, where those who were left behind stayed.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="30" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>But David pursued, he and four hundred men; for two hundred stayed behind, who were so faint that they couldn’t go over the brook Besor.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="30" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>They found an Egyptian in the field, and brought him to David, and gave him bread, and he ate; and they gave him water to drink.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="30" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>They gave him a piece of a cake of figs, and two clusters of raisins. when he had eaten, his spirit came again to him; for he had eaten no bread, nor drunk any water, three days and three nights. </text>
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>David asked him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="30" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="David">
    <text>«To whom do you belong? Where are you from?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="30" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>He said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="30" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="Egyptian (slave of Amalekite)">
    <text>«I am a young man of Egypt, servant to an Amalekite; and my master left me, because three days ago I fell sick.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="30" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="Egyptian (slave of Amalekite)">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>We made a raid on the South of the Cherethites, and on that which belongs to Judah, and on the South of Caleb; and we burned Ziklag with fire.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="30" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>David said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="30" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="David">
    <text>«Will you bring me down to this troop?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="30" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>He said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="30" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="Egyptian (slave of Amalekite)">
    <text>«Swear to me by God that you will neither kill me, nor deliver me up into the hands of my master, and I will bring you down to this troop.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="30" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>When he had brought him down, behold, they were spread around over all the ground, eating, drinking, and dancing, because of all the great spoil that they had taken out of the land of the Philistines, and out of the land of Judah.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="30" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>David struck them from the twilight even to the evening of the next day. Not a man of them escaped from there, except four hundred young men, who rode on camels and fled.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="30" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>David recovered all that the Amalekites had taken; and David rescued his two wives.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="30" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>There was nothing lacking to them, neither small nor great, neither sons nor daughters, neither spoil, nor anything that they had taken to them. David brought back all.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="30" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>David took all the flocks and the herds, which they drove before those other livestock, and said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="30" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="David's men">
    <text>«This is David's spoil.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="30" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>David came to the two hundred men, who were so faint that they could not follow David, whom also they had made to stay at the brook Besor; and they went forth to meet David, and to meet the people who were with him. When David came near to the people, he greeted them.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="30" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>Then all the wicked men and base fellows, of those who went with David, answered and said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="30" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="evil men and troublemakers">
    <text>«Because they didn't go with us, we will not give them anything of the spoil that we have recovered, except to every man his wife and his children, that he may lead them away, and depart.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="30" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>Then David said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="30" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="David">
    <text>«You shall not do so, my brothers, with that which God has given to us, who has preserved us, and delivered the troop that came against us into our hand.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="30" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="David">
    <verse num="24" />
    <text>Who will listen to you in this matter? For as his share is who goes down to the battle, so shall his share be who tarries by the baggage: they shall share alike.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="30" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="25" />
    <text>It was so from that day forward, that he made it a statute and an ordinance for Israel to this day.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="30" initialStartVerse="26" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="26" />
    <text>When David came to Ziklag, he sent of the spoil to the elders of Judah, even to his friends, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="30" initialStartVerse="26" characterId="David">
    <text>«Behold, a present for you of the spoil of the enemies of God.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="30" initialStartVerse="27" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="27" />
    <text>He sent it to those who were in Bethel, and to those who were in Ramoth of the South, and to those who were in Jattir, </text>
    <verse num="28" />
    <text>and to those who were in Aroer, and to those who were in Siphmoth, and to those who were in Eshtemoa, </text>
    <verse num="29" />
    <text>and to those who were in Racal, and to those who were in the cities of the Jerahmeelites, and to those who were in the cities of the Kenites, </text>
    <verse num="30" />
    <text>and to those who were in Hormah, and to those who were in Borashan, and to those who were in Athach, </text>
    <verse num="31" />
    <text>and to those who were in Hebron, and to all the places where David himself and his men used to stay.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="31" book="1SA" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1SA">
    <text>31</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="31" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Now the Philistines fought against Israel: and the men of Israel fled from before the Philistines, and fell down slain on Mount Gilboa.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="31" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>The Philistines followed hard on Saul and on his sons; and the Philistines killed Jonathan, and Abinadab, and Malchishua, the sons of Saul.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="31" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>The battle went hard against Saul, and the archers overtook him; and he was greatly distressed by reason of the archers. </text>
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>Then Saul said to his armor bearer,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="31" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="Saul" delivery="critically wounded">
    <text>«Draw your sword, and thrust me through with it, lest these uncircumcised come and thrust me through, and abuse me!»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="31" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <text>But his armor bearer would not; for he was terrified. Therefore Saul took his sword, and fell on it.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="31" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>When his armor bearer saw that Saul was dead, he likewise fell on his sword, and died with him.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="31" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>So Saul died, and his three sons, and his armor bearer, and all his men, that same day together.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="31" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>When the men of Israel who were on the other side of the valley, and those who were beyond the Jordan, saw that the men of Israel fled, and that Saul and his sons were dead, they forsook the cities, and fled; and the Philistines came and lived in them.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="31" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>It happened on the next day, when the Philistines came to strip the slain, that they found Saul and his three sons fallen on Mount Gilboa.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="31" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>They cut off his head, and stripped off his armor, and sent into the land of the Philistines all around, to carry the news to the house of their idols, and to the people.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="31" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>They put his armor in the house of the Ashtaroth; and they fastened his body to the wall of Beth Shan.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="31" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>When the inhabitants of Jabesh Gilead heard concerning him that which the Philistines had done to Saul, </text>
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>all the valiant men arose, and went all night, and took the body of Saul and the bodies of his sons from the wall of Beth Shan; and they came to Jabesh, and burnt them there.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="31" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1SA">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>They took their bones, and buried them under the tamarisk tree in Jabesh, and fasted seven days.</text>
  </block>
  <UnappliedSplits />
</book>