<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<book id="2TI" singlevoice="false" pageheader="2 TIMOTHY CHP">
  <block style="mt" chapter="0" book="2TI" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-2TI">
    <text>2 TIMOTHY</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" book="2TI" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-2TI">
    <text>1</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Paul, an apostle of Jesus Christ through the will of God, according to the promise of the life which is in Christ Jesus,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>to Timothy, my beloved child: Grace, mercy, and peace, from God the Father and Christ Jesus our Lord.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>I thank God, whom I serve as my forefathers did, with a pure conscience. How unceasing is my memory of you in my petitions, night and day.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>When I remember your tears, I long to see you, that I may be filled with joy;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>I remember the sincere faith that is in you; which lived first in your grandmother Lois, and your mother Eunice, and, I am persuaded, it is in you also.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>For this cause, I remind you that you should stir up the gift of God which is in you through the laying on of my hands.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>For God didn’t give us a spirit of fear, but of power, love, and self-control.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>Therefore don’t be ashamed of the testimony of our Lord, nor of me his prisoner; but endure hardship for the Good News according to the power of God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>He is the one who saved us and called us with a holy calling, not according to our works, but according to his own purpose and grace, which was given to us in Christ Jesus before times eternal.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>It has been revealed to us now by the appearing of our Savior, Christ Jesus. He abolished death, and brought life and immortality to light through the Good News.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>For this, I was appointed as a preacher, an apostle, and a teacher of the Gentiles.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>For this cause I also suffer these things. Yet I am not ashamed, for I know him whom I have believed. I am persuaded that he is able to guard that which I have committed to him against that day.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>Hold the pattern of sound words which you have heard from me, in faith and love which is in Christ Jesus.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>That good thing which was committed to you, guard through the Holy Spirit who dwells in us.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>This you know, that all who are in Asia turned away from me; of whom are Phygelus and Hermogenes.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>May the Lord grant mercy to the house of Onesiphorus, for he often refreshed me, and was not ashamed of my chain.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>But when he was in Rome, he sought me diligently, and found me.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>When the Lord comes again may he show mercy to him. You know what a help he was to me in Ephesus.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" book="2TI" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-2TI">
    <text>2</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>You therefore, my child, be strengthened in the grace that is in Christ Jesus.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>The things which you have heard from me among many witnesses, commit the same to faithful men, who will be able to teach others also.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>You therefore must endure hardship, as a good soldier of Christ Jesus.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>No soldier on duty entangles himself in the affairs of life, that he may please him who enrolled him as a soldier.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>Also, if anyone competes in athletics, he isn’t crowned unless he has competed by the rules.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>The farmers who labor must be the first to get a share of the crops.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>Consider what I say, and may the Lord give you understanding in all things.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>Remember Jesus Christ, risen from the dead, of the seed of David, according to my Good News,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>in which I suffer hardship to the point of chains as a criminal. But God’s word isn’t chained.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>Therefore I endure all things for the chosen ones’ sake, that they also may obtain the salvation which is in Christ Jesus with eternal glory.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>This saying is faithful: “For if we died with him, we will also live with him.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>If we endure, we will also reign with him. If we deny him, he also will deny us.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>If we are faithless, he remains faithful. He can’t deny himself.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>Remind them of these things, charging them in the sight of the Lord, that they don’t argue about words. It is of no profit, subverting of those who hear.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>Study to present yourself approved by God, a workman who doesn’t need to be ashamed, properly handling the Word of Truth.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>But shun empty chatter, for it will go further in ungodliness.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>Their teaching will consume like gangrene. Hymenaeus and Philetus are like this.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>They have turned from the truth, saying that the resurrection is already past, and overthrowing the faith of some.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>However God's firm foundation stands, having this seal,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="scripture">
    <text>The Lord knows those who are his, and, Let every one who names the name of the Lord depart from unrighteousness.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>Now in a large house there are not only vessels of gold and of silver, but also of wood and of clay. Some are for honor, and some for dishonor.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>If anyone therefore purges himself from these, he will be a vessel for honor, sanctified. A vessel suitable for the master’s use, prepared for every good work.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>Flee from youthful lusts; but pursue righteousness, faith, love, and peace with those who call on the Lord out of a pure heart.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>But refuse foolish and ignorant questionings, knowing that they generate strife.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="24" />
    <text>The Lord’s servant must not quarrel, but be gentle towards all, able to teach, and be patient.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="25" />
    <text>In gentleness he must correct those who oppose him: perhaps God may give them repentance leading to a full knowledge of the truth.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="26" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="26" />
    <text>Then they may recover themselves out of the devil’s snare, having been taken captive by him to his will.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" book="2TI" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-2TI">
    <text>3</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>But know this, that in the last days, grievous times will come.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>For men will be lovers of self, lovers of money, boastful, arrogant, blasphemers, disobedient to parents, unthankful, unholy,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>without natural affection, unforgiving, slanderers, without self-control, fierce, no lovers of those that are good,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>traitors, headstrong, conceited, lovers of pleasure rather than lovers of God;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>holding a form of godliness, but having denied its power. Turn away from these, also.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>For some of these are people who creep into houses, and take captive gullible women loaded down with sins, led away by various lusts.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>Such women are always learning, but never able to come to the knowledge of the truth.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>Even as Jannes and Jambres opposed Moses, so do these also oppose the truth; men corrupted in mind, who concerning the faith, are rejected.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>But they will proceed no further. For their folly will be evident to all men, as theirs also came to be.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>But you however know all about my teaching, conduct, purpose, faith, patience, love, steadfastness,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>persecutions, and sufferings: those things that happened to me at Antioch, Iconium, and Lystra. I endured those persecutions. Out of them all the Lord delivered me.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>Yes, and all who desire to live godly in Christ Jesus will suffer persecution.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>But evil men and impostors will grow worse and worse, deceiving and being deceived.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>But you remain in the things which you have learned and have been assured of, knowing from whom you have learned them.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>From infancy, you have known the holy Scriptures which are able to make you wise for salvation through faith, which is in Christ Jesus.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>Every Scripture is God-breathed and profitable for teaching, for reproof, for correction, and for instruction in righteousness.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>It gives the man of God everything he needs so that he will be complete, thoroughly equipped for every good work.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" book="2TI" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-2TI">
    <text>4</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>I command you therefore before God and the Lord Jesus Christ, who will judge the living and the dead at his appearing and his Kingdom:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>Preach the word; be urgent in season and out of season; reprove, rebuke, and exhort, with all patience and teaching.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>For the time will come when they will not listen to the sound doctrine. Having itching ears, will heap up for themselves teachers after their own lusts.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>They will turn away their ears from the truth, and turn aside to fables.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>But you be sober in all things, suffer hardship, do the work of an evangelist, and fulfill your ministry.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>For I am already being offered, and the time of my departure has come.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>I have fought the good fight. I have finished the course. I have kept the faith.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>From now on, there is stored up for me the crown of righteousness, which the Lord, the righteous judge, will give to me on that day; and not to me only, but also to all those who have loved his appearing.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>Be diligent to come to me soon,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>for Demas left me, having loved this present world, and went to Thessalonica; Crescens to Galatia, and Titus to Dalmatia.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>Only Luke is with me. Take Mark, and bring him with you, for he is useful to me for service.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>But I sent Tychicus to Ephesus.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>Bring the cloak that I left at Troas with Carpus when you come, and the books, especially the parchments.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>Alexander, the coppersmith, did much evil to me. The Lord will repay him according to his works.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>You also must beware of him; for he greatly opposed our words.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>At my first defense, no one came to help me, but all left me. May it not be held against them.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>But the Lord stood by me, and strengthened me, that through me the message might be fully proclaimed, and that all the Gentiles might hear; and I was delivered out of the mouth of the lion.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>And the Lord will deliver me from every evil work, and will preserve me for his heavenly Kingdom; to whom be the glory forever and ever. Amen.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>Greet Prisca and Aquila, and the house of Onesiphorus.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>Erastus remained at Corinth, but I left Trophimus at Miletus sick.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>Be diligent to come before winter. Eubulus salutes you, as do Pudens, Linus, Claudia, and all the brothers.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-2TI">
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>The Lord Jesus Christ be with your spirit. Grace be with you. Amen.</text>
  </block>
  <UnappliedSplits />
</book>