<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<book id="HAG" singlevoice="false" pageheader="Haggai">
  <block style="mt" chapter="0" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-HAG">
    <text>Haggai</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" book="HAG" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-HAG">
    <text>1</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-HAG">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>In the second year of Darius the king, in the sixth month, in the first day of the month, the Word of God came by Haggai, the prophet, to Zerubbabel, the son of Shealtiel, governor of Judah, and to Joshua, the son of Jehozadak, the high priest, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-HAG">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>This is what God of Armies says: These people say, 'The time hasn't yet come, the time for God's house to be built.'</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-HAG">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>Then the Word of God came by Haggai, the prophet, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-HAG">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>Is it a time for you yourselves to dwell in your paneled houses, while this house lies waste?</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-HAG">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>Now therefore this is what God of Armies says: Consider your ways.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-HAG">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>You have sown much, and bring in little. You eat, but you don't have enough. You drink, but you aren't filled with drink. You clothe yourselves, but no one is warm, and he who earns wages earns wages to put them into a bag with holes in it.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-HAG">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>This is what God of Armies says: «Consider your ways.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-HAG">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>Go up to the mountain, bring wood, and build the house. I will take pleasure in it, and I will be glorified,» says God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-HAG">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>You looked for much, and, behold, it came to little; and when you brought it home, I blew it away. Why? says God of Armies, «Because of my house that lies waste, while each of you is busy with his own house.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-HAG">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>Therefore for your sake the heavens withhold the dew, and the earth withholds its fruit.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-HAG">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>I called for a drought on the land, on the mountains, on the grain, on the new wine, on the oil, on that which the ground brings forth, on men, on livestock, and on all the labor of the hands.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-HAG">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>Then Zerubbabel, the son of Shealtiel, and Joshua, the son of Jehozadak, the high priest, with all the remnant of the people, obeyed the voice of God, their God, and the words of Haggai, the prophet, as God, their God, had sent him; and the people feared God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-HAG">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>Then Haggai, God's messenger, spoke God's message to the people, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-HAG">
    <text>«I am with you,» says God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-HAG">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>God stirred up the spirit of Zerubbabel, the son of Shealtiel, governor of Judah, and the spirit of Joshua, the son of Jehozadak, the high priest, and the spirit of all the remnant of the people; and they came and worked on the house of God of Armies, their God, </text>
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>in the twenty-fourth day of the month, in the sixth month, in the second year of Darius the king.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" book="HAG" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-HAG">
    <text>2</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-HAG">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>In the seventh month, in the twenty-first day of the month, the Word of God came by Haggai the prophet, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-HAG">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>Speak now to Zerubbabel, the son of Shealtiel, governor of Judah, and to Joshua, the son of Jehozadak, the high priest, and to the remnant of the people, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-HAG">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>Who is left among you who saw this house in its former glory? How do you see it now? Isn't it in your eyes as nothing?</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-HAG">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>Yet now be strong, Zerubbabel,' says God. 'Be strong, Joshua, son of Jehozadak, the high priest. Be strong, all you people of the land,' says God, 'and work, for I am with you,' says God of Armies.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-HAG">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>This is the word that I covenanted with you when you came out of Egypt, and my Spirit lived among you. 'Don't be afraid.'</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-HAG">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>For this is what God of Armies says: 'Yet once, it is a little while, and I will shake the heavens, the earth, the sea, and the dry land;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-HAG">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>and I will shake all nations. The precious things of all nations will come, and I will fill this house with glory, says God of Armies.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-HAG">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>The silver is mine, and the gold is mine,' says God of Armies.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-HAG">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>The latter glory of this house will be greater than the former,' says God of Armies; 'and in this place will I give peace,' says God of Armies.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-HAG">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>In the twenty-fourth day of the ninth month, in the second year of Darius, the Word of God came by Haggai the prophet, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-HAG">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>Thus says God of Armies: Ask now the priests concerning the law, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-HAG">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>If someone carries holy meat in the fold of his garment, and with his fold touches bread, stew, wine, oil, or any food, will it become holy?'</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-HAG">
    <text>The priests answered,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-HAG">
    <text>«No.».</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-HAG">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>Then Haggai said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-HAG">
    <text>«If one who is unclean by reason of a dead body touch any of these, will it be unclean?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-HAG">
    <text>The priests answered,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-HAG">
    <text>«It will be unclean.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-HAG">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>Then Haggai answered,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-HAG">
    <text>«'So is this people, and so is this nation before me,' says God; 'and so is every work of their hands. That which they offer there is unclean.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-HAG">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>Now, please consider from this day and backward, before a stone was laid on a stone in the temple of God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-HAG">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>Through all that time, when one came to a heap of twenty measures, there were only ten. When one came to the wine vat to draw out fifty, there were only twenty.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-HAG">
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>I struck you with blight, mildew, and hail in all the work of your hands; yet you didn't turn to me,' says God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-HAG">
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>Consider, please, from this day and backward, from the twenty-fourth day of the ninth month, since the day that the foundation of God's temple was laid, consider it.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-HAG">
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>Is the seed yet in the barn? Yes, the vine, the fig tree, the pomegranate, and the olive tree haven't brought forth. From this day will I bless you.'»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-HAG">
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>The Word of God came the second time to Haggai in the twenty-fourth day of the month, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-HAG">
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>Speak to Zerubbabel, governor of Judah, saying, 'I will shake the heavens and the earth.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-HAG">
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>I will overthrow the throne of kingdoms. I will destroy the strength of the kingdoms of the nations. I will overthrow the chariots, and those who ride in them. The horses and their riders will come down, everyone by the sword of his brother.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="narrator-HAG">
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>In that day, says God of Armies, will I take you, Zerubbabel, my servant, the son of Shealtiel,' says God, 'and will make you as a signet, for I have chosen you,' says God of Armies.</text>
  </block>
  <UnappliedSplits />
</book>