<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<book id="JDG" singlevoice="false" pageheader="Judges">
  <block style="mt" chapter="0" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-JDG">
    <text>Judges</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" book="JDG" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-JDG">
    <text>1</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>It happened after the death of Joshua, the children of Israel asked of God, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="Israelites">
    <text>“Who should go up for us first against the Canaanites, to fight against them?”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>God said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="God">
    <text>“Judah shall go up. Behold, I have delivered the land into his hand.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>Judah said to Simeon his brother,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="Judah, men of">
    <text>“Come up with me into my lot, that we may fight against the Canaanites; and I likewise will go with you into your lot.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <text>So Simeon went with him.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>Judah went up; and God delivered the Canaanites and the Perizzites into their hand: and they struck of them in Bezek ten thousand men.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>They found Adoni-Bezek in Bezek; and they fought against him, and they struck the Canaanites and the Perizzites.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>But Adoni-Bezek fled; and they pursued after him, and caught him, and cut off his thumbs and his great toes. </text>
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>Adoni-Bezek said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="Adoni-Bezek">
    <text>“Seventy kings, having their thumbs and their great toes cut off, gathered [their food] under my table: as I have done, so God has requited me.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <text>They brought him to Jerusalem, and he died there.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>The children of Judah fought against Jerusalem, and took it, and struck it with the edge of the sword, and set the city on fire.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>Afterward the children of Judah went down to fight against the Canaanites who lived in the hill country, and in the South, and in the lowland.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>Judah went against the Canaanites who lived in Hebron (now the name of Hebron before was Kiriath Arba); and they struck Sheshai, and Ahiman, and Talmai.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>From there he went against the inhabitants of Debir. (Now the name of Debir before was Kiriath Sepher.) </text>
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>Caleb said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="Caleb">
    <text>“He who strikes Kiriath Sepher, and takes it, to him will I give Achsah my daughter as wife.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>Othniel the son of Kenaz, Caleb's younger brother, took it: and he gave him Achsah his daughter as wife.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>It happened, when she came [to him], that she moved him to ask of her father a field: and she alighted from off her donkey; and Caleb said to her,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="Caleb">
    <text>“What would you like?”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>She said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="Achsah, Caleb's daughter">
    <text>“Give me a blessing; for that you have set me in the land of the South, give me also springs of water.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <text>Then Caleb gave her the upper springs and the lower springs.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>The children of the Kenite, Moses' brother-in-law, went up out of the city of palm trees with the children of Judah into the wilderness of Judah, which is in the south of Arad; and they went and lived with the people.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>Judah went with Simeon his brother, and they struck the Canaanites who inhabited Zephath, and utterly destroyed it. The name of the city was called Hormah.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>Also Judah took Gaza with its border, and Ashkelon with its border, and Ekron with its border.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>God was with Judah; and drove out [the inhabitants of] the hill country; for he could not drive out the inhabitants of the valley, because they had chariots of iron.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>They gave Hebron to Caleb, as Moses had spoken: and he drove out there the three sons of Anak.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>The children of Benjamin did not drive out the Jebusites who inhabited Jerusalem; but the Jebusites dwell with the children of Benjamin in Jerusalem to this day.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>The house of Joseph, they also went up against Bethel; and God was with them.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>The house of Joseph sent to spy out Bethel. (Now the name of the city before was Luz.) </text>
    <verse num="24" />
    <text>The watchers saw a man come forth out of the city, and they said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="Israelite spies from house of Joseph">
    <text>“Please show us the entrance into the city, and we will deal kindly with you.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="25" />
    <text>He showed them the entrance into the city; and they struck the city with the edge of the sword; but they let the man go and all his family.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="26" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="26" />
    <text>The man went into the land of the Hittites, and built a city, and called its name Luz, which is its name to this day.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="27" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="27" />
    <text>Manasseh did not drive out [the inhabitants of] Beth Shean and its towns, nor [of] Taanach and its towns, nor the inhabitants of Dor and its towns, nor the inhabitants of Ibleam and its towns, nor the inhabitants of Megiddo and its towns; but the Canaanites would dwell in that land.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="28" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="28" />
    <text>It happened, when Israel had grown strong, that they put the Canaanites to forced labor, and did not utterly drive them out.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="29" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="29" />
    <text>Ephraim didn't drive out the Canaanites who lived in Gezer; but the Canaanites lived in Gezer among them.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="30" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="30" />
    <text>Zebulun didn't drive out the inhabitants of Kitron, nor the inhabitants of Nahalol; but the Canaanites lived among them, and became subject to forced labor.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="31" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="31" />
    <text>Asher didn't drive out the inhabitants of Acco, nor the inhabitants of Sidon, nor of Ahlab, nor of Achzib, nor of Helbah, nor of Aphik, nor of Rehob;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="32" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="32" />
    <text>but the Asherites lived among the Canaanites, the inhabitants of the land; for they did not drive them out.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="33" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="33" />
    <text>Naphtali didn't drive out the inhabitants of Beth Shemesh, nor the inhabitants of Beth Anath; but he lived among the Canaanites, the inhabitants of the land: nevertheless the inhabitants of Beth Shemesh and of Beth Anath became subject to forced labor.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="34" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="34" />
    <text>The Amorites forced the children of Dan into the hill country; for they would not allow them to come down to the valley;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="35" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="35" />
    <text>but the Amorites would dwell in Mount Heres, in Aijalon, and in Shaalbim: yet the hand of the house of Joseph prevailed, so that they became subject to forced labor.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="36" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="36" />
    <text>The border of the Amorites was from the ascent of Akrabbim, from the rock, and upward.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" book="JDG" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-JDG">
    <text>2</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>The angel of God came up from Gilgal to Bochim. He said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="angel of the LORD, the">
    <text>“I made you to go up out of Egypt, and have brought you to the land which I swore to your fathers; and I said, 'I will never break my covenant with you:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="angel of the LORD, the">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>and you shall make no covenant with the inhabitants of this land; you shall break down their altars.' But you have not listened to my voice: why have you done this?</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="angel of the LORD, the">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>Therefore I also said, I will not drive them out from before you; but they shall be [as thorns] in your sides, and their gods shall be a snare to you.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>It happened, when the angel of God spoke these words to all the children of Israel, that the people lifted up their voice, and wept.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>They called the name of that place Bochim: and they sacrificed there to God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>Now when Joshua had sent the people away, the children of Israel went every man to his inheritance to possess the land.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>The people served God all the days of Joshua, and all the days of the elders who outlived Joshua, who had seen all the great work of God that he had worked for Israel.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>Joshua the son of Nun, the servant of God, died, being one hundred ten years old.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>They buried him in the border of his inheritance in Timnath Heres, in the hill country of Ephraim, on the north of the mountain of Gaash.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>Also all that generation were gathered to their fathers: and there arose another generation after them, who didn't know God, nor yet the work which he had worked for Israel.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>The children of Israel did that which was evil in the sight of God, and served the Baals;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>and they forsook God, the God of their fathers, who brought them out of the land of Egypt, and followed other gods, of the gods of the peoples who were around them, and bowed themselves down to them: and they provoked God to anger. </text>
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>They forsook God, and served Baal and the Ashtaroth.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>The anger of God was kindled against Israel, and he delivered them into the hands of spoilers who despoiled them; and he sold them into the hands of their enemies all around, so that they could not any longer stand before their enemies.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>Wherever they went out, the hand of God was against them for evil, as God had spoken, and as God had sworn to them: and they were very distressed.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>God raised up judges, who saved them out of the hand of those who despoiled them.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>Yet they didn't listen to their judges; for they played the prostitute after other gods, and bowed themselves down to them: they turned aside quickly out of the way in which their fathers walked, obeying the commandments of God; [but] they didn't do so.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>When God raised them up judges, then God was with the judge, and saved them out of the hand of their enemies all the days of the judge: for it grieved God because of their groaning by reason of those who oppressed them and troubled them.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>But it happened, when the judge was dead, that they turned back, and dealt more corruptly than their fathers, in following other gods to serve them, and to bow down to them; they didn't cease from their doings, nor from their stubborn way.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>The anger of God was kindled against Israel; and he said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="God">
    <text>“Because this nation have transgressed my covenant which I commanded their fathers, and have not listened to my voice;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="God">
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>I also will not henceforth drive out any from before them of the nations that Joshua left when he died;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="God">
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>that by them I may prove Israel, whether they will keep the way of God to walk therein, as their fathers did keep it, or not.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>So God left those nations, without driving them out hastily; neither delivered he them into the hand of Joshua.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" book="JDG" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-JDG">
    <text>3</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Now these are the nations which God left, to prove Israel by them, even as many [of Israel] as had not known all the wars of Canaan;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>only that the generations of the children of Israel might know, to teach them war, at the least such as before knew nothing of it:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>[namely], the five lords of the Philistines, and all the Canaanites, and the Sidonians, and the Hivites who lived on Mount Lebanon, from Mount Baal Hermon to the entrance of Hamath.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>They were [left], to prove Israel by them, to know whether they would listen to the commandments of God, which he commanded their fathers by Moses.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>The children of Israel lived among the Canaanites, the Hittites, and the Amorites, and the Perizzites, and the Hivites, and the Jebusites:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>and they took their daughters to be their wives, and gave their own daughters to their sons and served their gods.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>The children of Israel did that which was evil in the sight of God, and forgot God their God, and served the Baals and the Asheroth.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>Therefore the anger of God was kindled against Israel, and he sold them into the hand of Cushan Rishathaim king of Mesopotamia: and the children of Israel served Cushan Rishathaim eight years.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>When the children of Israel cried to God, God raised up a savior to the children of Israel, who saved them, even Othniel the son of Kenaz, Caleb's younger brother.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>The Spirit of God came on him, and he judged Israel; and he went out to war, and God delivered Cushan Rishathaim king of Mesopotamia into his hand: and his hand prevailed against Cushan Rishathaim.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>The land had rest forty years. Othniel the son of Kenaz died.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>The children of Israel again did that which was evil in the sight of God: and God strengthened Eglon the king of Moab against Israel, because they had done that which was evil in the sight of God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>He gathered to him the children of Ammon and Amalek; and he went and struck Israel, and they possessed the city of palm trees.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>The children of Israel served Eglon the king of Moab eighteen years.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>But when the children of Israel cried to God, God raised them up a savior, Ehud the son of Gera, the Benjamite, a man left-handed. The children of Israel sent tribute by him to Eglon the king of Moab.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>Ehud made him a sword which had two edges, a cubit in length; and he wore it under his clothing on his right thigh.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>He offered the tribute to Eglon king of Moab: now Eglon was a very fat man.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>When he had made an end of offering the tribute, he sent away the people who bore the tribute. </text>
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>But he himself turned back from the quarries that were by Gilgal, and said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="Ehud, Israelite deliverer">
    <text>“I have a secret errand to you, king.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <text>The king said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="Eglon, king of Moab">
    <text>“Keep silence!”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <text>All who stood by him went out from him. </text>
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>Ehud came to him; and he was sitting by himself alone in the cool upper room. Ehud said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="Ehud, Israelite deliverer">
    <text>“I have a message from God to you.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <text>He arose out of his seat. </text>
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>Ehud put forth his left hand, and took the sword from his right thigh, and thrust it into his body:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>and the handle also went in after the blade; and the fat closed on the blade, for he didn't draw the sword out of his body; and it came out behind.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>Then Ehud went forth into the porch, and shut the doors of the upper room on him, and locked them.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="24" />
    <text>Now when he was gone out, his servants came; and they saw, and behold, the doors of the upper room were locked; and they said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="servants of Eglon, king of Moab">
    <text>“Surely he is covering his feet in the upper room.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="25" />
    <text>They waited until they were ashamed; and behold, he didn't open the doors of the upper room: therefore they took the key, and opened [them], and behold, their lord was fallen down dead on the earth.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="26" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="26" />
    <text>Ehud escaped while they waited, and passed beyond the quarries, and escaped to Seirah.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="27" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="27" />
    <text>It happened, when he had come, that he blew a trumpet in the hill country of Ephraim; and the children of Israel went down with him from the hill country, and he before them. </text>
    <verse num="28" />
    <text>He said to them,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="28" characterId="Ehud, Israelite deliverer">
    <text>“Follow me; for God has delivered your enemies the Moabites into your hand.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="28" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <text>They followed him, and took the fords of the Jordan against the Moabites, and didn't allow any man to pass over.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="29" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="29" />
    <text>They struck of Moab at that time about ten thousand men, every lusty man, and every man of valor; and there escaped not a man.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="30" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="30" />
    <text>So Moab was subdued that day under the hand of Israel. The land had rest eighty years.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="31" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="31" />
    <text>After him was Shamgar the son of Anath, who struck of the Philistines six hundred men with an oxgoad: and he also saved Israel.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" book="JDG" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-JDG">
    <text>4</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>The children of Israel again did that which was evil in the sight of God, when Ehud was dead.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>God sold them into the hand of Jabin king of Canaan, who reigned in Hazor; the captain of whose army was Sisera, who lived in Harosheth of the Gentiles.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>The children of Israel cried to God: for he had nine hundred chariots of iron; and twenty years he mightily oppressed the children of Israel.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>Now Deborah, a prophetess, the wife of Lappidoth, she judged Israel at that time.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>She lived under the palm tree of Deborah between Ramah and Bethel in the hill country of Ephraim: and the children of Israel came up to her for judgment.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>She sent and called Barak the son of Abinoam out of Kedesh Naphtali, and said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="Deborah">
    <text>“Hasn't God, the God of Israel, commanded, 'Go and draw to Mount Tabor, and take with you ten thousand men of the children of Naphtali and of the children of Zebulun?</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="Deborah">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>I will draw to you, to the river Kishon, Sisera, the captain of Jabin's army, with his chariots and his multitude; and I will deliver him into your hand.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>Barak said to her,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="Barak">
    <text>“If you will go with me, then I will go; but if you will not go with me, I will not go.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>She said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="Deborah">
    <text>“I will surely go with you: nevertheless, the journey that you take shall not be for your honor; for God will sell Sisera into the hand of a woman.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <text>Deborah arose, and went with Barak to Kedesh. </text>
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>Barak called Zebulun and Naphtali together to Kedesh; and there went up ten thousand men at his feet: and Deborah went up with him.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>Now Heber the Kenite had separated himself from the Kenites, even from the children of Hobab the brother-in-law of Moses, and had pitched his tent as far as the oak in Zaanannim, which is by Kedesh.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>They told Sisera that Barak the son of Abinoam was gone up to Mount Tabor.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>Sisera gathered together all his chariots, even nine hundred chariots of iron, and all the people who were with him, from Harosheth of the Gentiles, to the river Kishon. </text>
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>Deborah said to Barak,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="Deborah">
    <text>“Go; for this is the day in which God has delivered Sisera into your hand. Hasn't God gone out before you?”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <text>So Barak went down from Mount Tabor, and ten thousand men after him.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>God confused Sisera, and all his chariots, and all his army, with the edge of the sword before Barak; and Sisera alighted from his chariot, and fled away on his feet.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>But Barak pursued after the chariots, and after the army, to Harosheth of the Gentiles: and all the army of Sisera fell by the edge of the sword; there was not a man left.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>However Sisera fled away on his feet to the tent of Jael the wife of Heber the Kenite; for there was peace between Jabin the king of Hazor and the house of Heber the Kenite.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>Jael went out to meet Sisera, and said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="Jael">
    <text>“Turn in, my lord, turn in to me; don't be afraid.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <text>He came in to her into the tent, and she covered him with a rug. </text>
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>He said to her,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="Sisera">
    <text>“Please give me a little water to drink; for I am thirsty.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <text>She opened a bottle of milk, and gave him drink, and covered him. </text>
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>He said to her,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="Sisera">
    <text>“Stand in the door of the tent, and it shall be, when any man comes and inquires of you, and says, Is there any man here? that you shall say, No.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>Then Jael Heber's wife took a tent peg, and took a hammer in her hand, and went softly to him, and struck the pin into his temples, and it pierced through into the ground; for he was in a deep sleep; so he swooned and died.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>Behold, as Barak pursued Sisera, Jael came out to meet him, and said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="Jael">
    <text>“Come, and I will show you the man whom you seek.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <text>He came to her; and behold, Sisera lay dead, and the tent peg was in his temples.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>So God subdued on that day Jabin the king of Canaan before the children of Israel.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="24" />
    <text>The hand of the children of Israel prevailed more and more against Jabin the king of Canaan, until they had destroyed Jabin king of Canaan.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" book="JDG" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-JDG">
    <text>5</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Then Deborah and Barak the son of Abinoam sang on that day, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="Deborah/Barak" characterIdOverrideForScript="Deborah" delivery="singing">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>Because the leaders took the lead in Israel, because the people offered themselves willingly, be blessed, God!</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="Deborah/Barak" characterIdOverrideForScript="Deborah" delivery="singing">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>Hear, you kings! Give ear, you princes! I, [even] I, will sing to God. I will sing praise to God, the God of Israel.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="Deborah/Barak" characterIdOverrideForScript="Deborah" delivery="singing">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>God, when you went forth out of Seir, when you marched out of the field of Edom, the earth trembled, the sky also dropped. Yes, the clouds dropped water.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="Deborah/Barak" characterIdOverrideForScript="Deborah" delivery="singing">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>The mountains quaked at the presence of God, even Sinai, at the presence of God, the God of Israel.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="Deborah/Barak" characterIdOverrideForScript="Deborah" delivery="singing">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>In the days of Shamgar the son of Anath, in the days of Jael, the highways were unoccupied. The travelers walked through byways.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="Deborah/Barak" characterIdOverrideForScript="Deborah" delivery="singing">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>The rulers ceased in Israel. They ceased until I, Deborah, arose; Until I arose a mother in Israel.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="Deborah/Barak" characterIdOverrideForScript="Deborah" delivery="singing">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>They chose new gods. Then war was in the gates. Was there a shield or spear seen among forty thousand in Israel?</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="Deborah/Barak" characterIdOverrideForScript="Deborah" delivery="singing">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>My heart is toward the governors of Israel, who offered themselves willingly among the people. Bless God!</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="Deborah/Barak" characterIdOverrideForScript="Deborah" delivery="singing">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>Tell [of it], you who ride on white donkeys, you who sit on rich carpets, and you who walk by the way.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="Deborah/Barak" characterIdOverrideForScript="Deborah" delivery="singing">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>Far from the noise of archers, in the places of drawing water, there they will rehearse the righteous acts of God, [Even] the righteous acts of his rule in Israel. Then the people of God went down to the gates.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="Deborah/Barak" characterIdOverrideForScript="Deborah" delivery="singing">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>'Awake, awake, Deborah! Awake, awake, utter a song! Arise, Barak, and lead away your captives, you son of Abinoam.'</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="Deborah/Barak" characterIdOverrideForScript="Deborah" delivery="singing">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>Then a remnant of the nobles [and] the people came down. God came down for me against the mighty.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="Deborah/Barak" characterIdOverrideForScript="Deborah" delivery="singing">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>Those whose root is in Amalek came out of Ephraim, after you, Benjamin, among your peoples. Governors come down out of Machir. Those who handle the marshal's staff came out of Zebulun.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="Deborah/Barak" characterIdOverrideForScript="Deborah" delivery="singing">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>The princes of Issachar were with Deborah. As was Issachar, so was Barak. They rushed into the valley at his feet. By the watercourses of Reuben, there were great resolves of heart.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="Deborah/Barak" characterIdOverrideForScript="Deborah" delivery="singing">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>Why did you sit among the sheepfolds, To hear the whistling for the flocks? At the watercourses of Reuben There were great searchings of heart.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="Deborah/Barak" characterIdOverrideForScript="Deborah" delivery="singing">
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>Gilead lived beyond the Jordan. Why did Dan remain in ships? Asher sat still at the haven of the sea, and lived by his creeks.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="Deborah/Barak" characterIdOverrideForScript="Deborah" delivery="singing">
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>Zebulun was a people that jeopardized their lives to the deaths; Naphtali also, on the high places of the field.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="Deborah/Barak" characterIdOverrideForScript="Deborah" delivery="singing">
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>The kings came and fought, then the kings of Canaan fought at Taanach by the waters of Megiddo. They took no plunder of silver.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="Deborah/Barak" characterIdOverrideForScript="Deborah" delivery="singing">
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>From the sky the stars fought. From their courses, they fought against Sisera.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="Deborah/Barak" characterIdOverrideForScript="Deborah" delivery="singing">
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>The river Kishon swept them away, that ancient river, the river Kishon. My soul, march on with strength.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="Deborah/Barak" characterIdOverrideForScript="Deborah" delivery="singing">
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>Then the horse hoofs stamped because of the prancings, the prancings of their strong ones.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="Deborah/Barak" characterIdOverrideForScript="Deborah" delivery="singing">
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>Curse Meroz,' said the angel of God. 'Curse bitterly its inhabitants, because they didn't come to help God, to help God against the mighty.'</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="Deborah/Barak" characterIdOverrideForScript="Deborah" delivery="singing">
    <verse num="24" />
    <text>Jael shall be blessed above women, the wife of Heber the Kenite; blessed shall she be above women in the tent.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="Deborah/Barak" characterIdOverrideForScript="Deborah" delivery="singing">
    <verse num="25" />
    <text>He asked for water. She gave him milk. She brought him butter in a lordly dish.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="26" characterId="Deborah/Barak" characterIdOverrideForScript="Deborah" delivery="singing">
    <verse num="26" />
    <text>She put her hand to the tent peg, and her right hand to the workmen's hammer. With the hammer she struck Sisera. She struck through his head. Yes, she pierced and struck through his temples.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="27" characterId="Deborah/Barak" characterIdOverrideForScript="Deborah" delivery="singing">
    <verse num="27" />
    <text>At her feet he bowed, he fell, he lay. At her feet he bowed, he fell. Where he bowed, there he fell down dead.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="28" characterId="Deborah/Barak" characterIdOverrideForScript="Deborah" delivery="singing">
    <verse num="28" />
    <text>Through the window she looked out, and cried: Sisera's mother looked through the lattice. 'Why is his chariot so long in coming? Why do the wheels of his chariots wait?'</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="29" characterId="Deborah/Barak" characterIdOverrideForScript="Deborah" delivery="singing">
    <verse num="29" />
    <text>Her wise ladies answered her, Yes, she returned answer to herself, </text>
    <verse num="30" />
    <text>'Have they not found, have they not divided the spoil? A lady, two ladies to every man; to Sisera a spoil of dyed garments, a spoil of dyed garments embroidered, of dyed garments embroidered on both sides, on the necks of the spoil?'</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="31" characterId="Deborah/Barak" characterIdOverrideForScript="Deborah" delivery="singing">
    <verse num="31" />
    <text>So let all your enemies perish, God, but let those who love him be as the sun when it rises forth in its strength.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="31" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <text>Then the land had rest forty years.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="6" book="JDG" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-JDG">
    <text>6</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>The children of Israel did that which was evil in the sight of God: and God delivered them into the hand of Midian seven years.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>The hand of Midian prevailed against Israel; and because of Midian the children of Israel made them the dens which are in the mountains, and the caves, and the strongholds.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>So it was, when Israel had sown, that the Midianites came up, and the Amalekites, and the children of the east; they came up against them;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>and they encamped against them, and destroyed the increase of the earth, until you come to Gaza, and left no sustenance in Israel, neither sheep, nor ox, nor donkey.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>For they came up with their livestock and their tents; they came in as locusts for multitude; both they and their camels were without number: and they came into the land to destroy it.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>Israel was brought very low because of Midian; and the children of Israel cried to God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>It happened, when the children of Israel cried to God because of Midian, </text>
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>that God sent a prophet to the children of Israel: and he said to them,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="prophet">
    <text>“Thus says God, the God of Israel, 'I brought you up from Egypt, and brought you forth out of the house of bondage;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="prophet">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>and I delivered you out of the hand of the Egyptians, and out of the hand of all who oppressed you, and drove them out from before you, and gave you their land;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="prophet">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>and I said to you, “I am God your God; you shall not fear the gods of the Amorites, in whose land you dwell.” But you have not listened to my voice.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>The angel of God came, and sat under the oak which was in Ophrah, that pertained to Joash the Abiezrite: and his son Gideon was beating out wheat in the winepress, to hide it from the Midianites.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>The angel of God appeared to him, and said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="angel of the LORD, the">
    <text>“God is with you, you mighty man of valor!”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>Gideon said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="Gideon (Jerubbaal)">
    <text>“Oh, my lord, if God is with us, why then has all this happened to us? Where are all his wondrous works which our fathers told us of, saying, 'Didn't God bring us up from Egypt?' But now God has cast us off, and delivered us into the hand of Midian.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>God looked at him, and said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="God">
    <text>“Go in this your might, and save Israel from the hand of Midian. Haven't I sent you?”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>He said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="Gideon (Jerubbaal)">
    <text>“O Lord, how shall I save Israel? Behold, my family is the poorest in Manasseh, and I am the least in my father's house.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>God said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="God">
    <text>“Surely I will be with you, and you shall strike the Midianites as one man.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>He said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="Gideon (Jerubbaal)">
    <text>“If now I have found favor in your sight, then show me a sign that it is you who talk with me.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="Gideon (Jerubbaal)">
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>Please don't go away, until I come to you, and bring out my present, and lay it before you.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <text>He said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="angel of the LORD, the">
    <text>“I will wait until you come back.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>Gideon went in, and prepared a young goat, and unleavened cakes of an ephah of meal. He put the meat in a basket and he put the broth in a pot, and brought it out to him under the oak, and presented it.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>The angel of God said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="angel of the LORD, the">
    <text>“Take the meat and the unleavened cakes, and lay them on this rock, and pour out the broth.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <text>He did so. </text>
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>Then the angel of God stretched out the end of the staff that was in his hand, and touched the meat and the unleavened cakes; and fire went up out of the rock, and consumed the meat and the unleavened cakes; and the angel of God departed out of his sight.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>Gideon saw that he was the angel of God; and Gideon said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="Gideon (Jerubbaal)">
    <text>“Alas, Lord God! Because I have seen the angel of God face to face!”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>God said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="God">
    <text>“Peace be to you! Don't be afraid. You shall not die.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="24" />
    <text>Then Gideon built an altar there to God, and called it God is Peace. To this day it is still in Ophrah of the Abiezrites. </text>
    <verse num="25" />
    <text>It happened the same night, that God said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="God">
    <text>“Take your father's bull, even the second bull seven years old, and throw down the altar of Baal that your father has, and cut down the Asherah that is by it;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="26" characterId="God">
    <verse num="26" />
    <text>and build an altar to God your God on the top of this stronghold, in an orderly way, and take the second bull, and offer a burnt offering with the wood of the Asherah which you shall cut down.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="27" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="27" />
    <text>Then Gideon took ten men of his servants, and did as God had spoken to him: and it happened, because he feared his father's household and the men of the city, so that he could not do it by day, that he did it by night.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="28" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="28" />
    <text>When the men of the city arose early in the morning, behold, the altar of Baal was broken down, and the Asherah was cut down that was by it, and the second bull was offered on the altar that was built.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="29" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="29" />
    <text>They said one to another,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="29" characterId="townsmen of Ophrah">
    <text>“Who has done this thing?”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="29" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <text>When they inquired and asked, they said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="29" characterId="person who informed townsmen of Ophrah">
    <text>“Gideon the son of Joash has done this thing.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="30" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="30" />
    <text>Then the men of the city said to Joash,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="30" characterId="townsmen of Ophrah">
    <text>“Bring out your son, that he may die, because he has broken down the altar of Baal, and because he has cut down the Asherah that was by it.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="31" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="31" />
    <text>Joash said to all who stood against him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="31" characterId="Joash, father of Gideon (Jerubbaal)">
    <text>“Will you contend for Baal? Or will you save him? He who will contend for him, let him be put to death while [it is yet] morning. If he is a god, let him contend for himself, because someone has broken down his altar.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="32" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="32" />
    <text>Therefore on that day he named him Jerub-Baal, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="32" characterId="Joash, father of Gideon (Jerubbaal)">
    <text>“Let Baal contend against him, because he has broken down his altar.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="33" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="33" />
    <text>Then all the Midianites and the Amalekites and the children of the east assembled themselves together; and they passed over, and encamped in the valley of Jezreel.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="34" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="34" />
    <text>But the Spirit of God came on Gideon; and he blew a trumpet; and Abiezer was gathered together after him.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="35" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="35" />
    <text>He sent messengers throughout all Manasseh; and they also were gathered together after him: and he sent messengers to Asher, and to Zebulun, and to Naphtali; and they came up to meet them. </text>
    <verse num="36" />
    <text>Gideon said to God,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="36" characterId="Gideon (Jerubbaal)">
    <text>“If you will save Israel by my hand, as you have spoken, </text>
    <verse num="37" />
    <text>behold, I will put a fleece of wool on the threshing floor; if there be dew on the fleece only, and it be dry on all the ground, then shall I know that you will save Israel by my hand, as you have spoken.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="38" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="38" />
    <text>It was so; for he rose up early on the next day, and pressed the fleece together, and wrung the dew out of the fleece, a bowl full of water. </text>
    <verse num="39" />
    <text>Gideon said to God,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="39" characterId="Gideon (Jerubbaal)">
    <text>“Don't let your anger be kindled against me, and I will speak but this once. Please let me make a trial just this once with the fleece. Let it now be dry only on the fleece, and on all the ground let there be dew.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="40" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="40" />
    <text>God did so that night: for it was dry on the fleece only, and there was dew on all the ground.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="7" book="JDG" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-JDG">
    <text>7</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Then Jerubbaal, who is Gideon, and all the people who were with him, rose up early, and encamped beside the spring of Harod: and the camp of Midian was on the north side of them, by the hill of Moreh, in the valley. </text>
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>God said to Gideon,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="God">
    <text>“The people who are with you are too many for me to give the Midianites into their hand, lest Israel vaunt themselves against me, saying, 'My own hand has saved me.'</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="God">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>Now therefore proclaim in the ears of the people, saying, Whoever is fearful and trembling, let him return and depart from Mount Gilead.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <text>Twenty-two thousand of the people returned, and ten thousand remained. </text>
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>God said to Gideon,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="God">
    <text>“The people are still too many. Bring them down to the water, and I will test them for you there. It shall be, that of whom I tell you, 'This shall go with you,' the same shall go with you; and of whoever I tell you, 'This shall not go with you,' the same shall not go.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>So he brought down the people to the water; and God said to Gideon,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="God">
    <text>“Everyone who laps of the water with his tongue, like a dog laps, you shall set him by himself; likewise everyone who bows down on his knees to drink.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>The number of those who lapped, putting their hand to their mouth, was three hundred men; but all the rest of the people bowed down on their knees to drink water. </text>
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>God said to Gideon,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="God">
    <text>“By the three hundred men who lapped will I save you, and deliver the Midianites into your hand. Let all the other people go, each to his own place.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>So the people took food in their hand, and their trumpets; and he sent all the men of Israel every man to his tent, but retained the three hundred men: and the camp of Midian was beneath him in the valley.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>It happened the same night, that God said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="God">
    <text>“Arise, go down into the camp; for I have delivered it into your hand.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="God">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>But if you are afraid to go down, go with Purah your servant down to the camp: </text>
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>and you shall hear what they say; and afterward your hands will be strengthened to go down into the camp.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <text>Then went he down with Purah his servant to the outermost part of the armed men who were in the camp.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>The Midianites and the Amalekites and all the children of the east lay along in the valley like locusts for multitude; and their camels were without number, as the sand which is on the seashore for multitude.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>When Gideon had come, behold, there was a man telling a dream to his fellow; and he said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="Midianite soldier who had a dream">
    <text>“Behold, I dreamed a dream; and behold, a cake of barley bread tumbled into the camp of Midian, and came to the tent, and struck it so that it fell, and turned it upside down, so that the tent lay flat.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>His fellow answered,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="Midianite soldier who interprets dream">
    <text>“This is nothing other than the sword of Gideon the son of Joash, a man of Israel. God has delivered Midian into his hand, with all the army.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>It was so, when Gideon heard the telling of the dream, and its interpretation, that he worshiped; and he returned into the camp of Israel, and said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="Gideon (Jerubbaal)">
    <text>“Arise; for God has delivered the army of Midian into your hand!”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>He divided the three hundred men into three companies, and he put into the hands of all of them trumpets, and empty pitchers, with torches within the pitchers. </text>
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>He said to them,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="Gideon (Jerubbaal)">
    <text>“Watch me, and do likewise. Behold, when I come to the outermost part of the camp, it shall be that, as I do, so you shall do.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="Gideon (Jerubbaal)">
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>When I blow the trumpet, I and all who are with me, then blow the trumpets also on every side of all the camp, and shout, For God and for Gideon!”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>So Gideon, and the hundred men who were with him, came to the outermost part of the camp in the beginning of the middle watch, when they had but newly set the watch: and they blew the trumpets, and broke in pieces the pitchers that were in their hands.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>The three companies blew the trumpets, and broke the pitchers, and held the torches in their left hands, and the trumpets in their right hands with which to blow; and they shouted,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="Israelite fighting men">
    <text>“The sword of God and of Gideon!”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>They stood every man in his place around the camp; and all the army ran; and they shouted, and put [them] to flight.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>They blew the three hundred trumpets, and God set every man's sword against his fellow, and against all the army; and the army fled as far as Beth Shittah toward Zererah, as far as the border of Abel Meholah, by Tabbath.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>The men of Israel were gathered together out of Naphtali, and out of Asher, and out of all Manasseh, and pursued after Midian.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="24" />
    <text>Gideon sent messengers throughout all the hill country of Ephraim, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="Gideon (Jerubbaal)">
    <text>“Come down against Midian, and take before them the waters, as far as Beth Barah, even the Jordan!”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <text>So all the men of Ephraim were gathered together, and took the waters as far as Beth Barah, even the Jordan.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="25" />
    <text>They took the two princes of Midian, Oreb and Zeeb; and they killed Oreb at the rock of Oreb, and Zeeb they killed at the winepress of Zeeb, and pursued Midian: and they brought the heads of Oreb and Zeeb to Gideon beyond the Jordan.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="8" book="JDG" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-JDG">
    <text>8</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>The men of Ephraim said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="Ephraimites" delivery="critical">
    <text>“Why have you treated us this way, that you didn't call us, when you went to fight with Midian?”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <text>They rebuked him sharply. </text>
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>He said to them,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="Gideon (Jerubbaal)">
    <text>“What have I now done in comparison with you? Isn't the gleaning of the grapes of Ephraim better than the vintage of Abiezer?</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="Gideon (Jerubbaal)">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>God has delivered into your hand the princes of Midian, Oreb and Zeeb! What was I able to do in comparison with you?”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <text>Then their anger was abated toward him, when he had said that.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>Gideon came to the Jordan, [and] passed over, he, and the three hundred men who were with him, faint, yet pursuing. </text>
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>He said to the men of Succoth,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="Gideon (Jerubbaal)">
    <text>“Please give loaves of bread to the people who follow me; for they are faint, and I am pursuing after Zebah and Zalmunna, the kings of Midian.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>The princes of Succoth said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="officials of Succoth" delivery="mocking">
    <text>“Are the hands of Zebah and Zalmunna now in your hand, that we should give bread to your army?”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>Gideon said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="Gideon (Jerubbaal)">
    <text>“Therefore when God has delivered Zebah and Zalmunna into my hand, then I will tear your flesh with the thorns of the wilderness and with briers.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>He went up there to Penuel, and spoke to them in the same way; and the men of Penuel answered him as the men of Succoth had answered. </text>
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>He spoke also to the men of Penuel, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="Gideon (Jerubbaal)">
    <text>“When I come again in peace, I will break down this tower.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>Now Zebah and Zalmunna were in Karkor, and their armies with them, about fifteen thousand men, all who were left of all the army of the children of the east; for there fell one hundred twenty thousand men who drew sword.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>Gideon went up by the way of those who lived in tents on the east of Nobah and Jogbehah, and struck the army; for the army was secure.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>Zebah and Zalmunna fled; and he pursued after them; and he took the two kings of Midian, Zebah and Zalmunna, and confused all the army.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>Gideon the son of Joash returned from the battle from the ascent of Heres.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>He caught a young man of the men of Succoth, and inquired of him: and he described for him the princes of Succoth, and its elders, seventy-seven men.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>He came to the men of Succoth, and said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="Gideon (Jerubbaal)">
    <text>“See Zebah and Zalmunna, concerning whom you taunted me, saying, Are the hands of Zebah and Zalmunna now in your hand, that we should give bread to your men who are weary?”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>He took the elders of the city, and thorns of the wilderness and briers, and with them he taught the men of Succoth.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>He broke down the tower of Penuel, and killed the men of the city. </text>
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>Then he said to Zebah and Zalmunna,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="Gideon (Jerubbaal)">
    <text>“What kind of men were they whom you killed at Tabor?”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <text>They answered,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="Zebah/Zalmunna" characterIdOverrideForScript="Zebah">
    <text>“They were like you. Each one resembled the children of a king.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>He said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="Gideon (Jerubbaal)">
    <text>“They were my brothers, the sons of my mother. As God lives, if you had saved them alive, I would not kill you.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>He said to Jether his firstborn,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="Gideon (Jerubbaal)">
    <text>“Get up, and kill them!”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <text>But the youth didn't draw his sword; for he was afraid, because he was yet a youth. </text>
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>Then Zebah and Zalmunna said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="Zebah/Zalmunna" characterIdOverrideForScript="Zebah">
    <text>“Rise and fall on us; for as the man is, so is his strength.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <text>Gideon arose, and killed Zebah and Zalmunna, and took the crescents that were on their camels' necks. </text>
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>Then the men of Israel said to Gideon,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="Israelites">
    <text>“Rule over us, both you, and your son, and your son's son also; for you have saved us out of the hand of Midian.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>Gideon said to them,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="Gideon (Jerubbaal)">
    <text>“I will not rule over you, neither shall my son rule over you. God shall rule over you.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="24" />
    <text>Gideon said to them,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="Gideon (Jerubbaal)">
    <text>“I would make a request of you, that you would give me every man the earrings of his spoil.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <text>(For they had golden earrings, because they were Ishmaelites.) </text>
    <verse num="25" />
    <text>They answered,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="Israelites">
    <text>“We will willingly give them.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <text>They spread a garment, and every man threw the earrings of his spoil into it.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="26" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="26" />
    <text>The weight of the golden earrings that he requested was one thousand and seven hundred [shekels] of gold, besides the crescents, and the pendants, and the purple clothing that was on the kings of Midian, and besides the chains that were about their camels' necks.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="27" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="27" />
    <text>Gideon made an ephod of it, and put it in his city, even in Ophrah: and all Israel played the prostitute after it there; and it became a snare to Gideon, and to his house.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="28" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="28" />
    <text>So Midian was subdued before the children of Israel, and they lifted up their heads no more. The land had rest forty years in the days of Gideon.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="29" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="29" />
    <text>Jerubbaal the son of Joash went and lived in his own house.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="30" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="30" />
    <text>Gideon had seventy sons conceived from his body; for he had many wives.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="31" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="31" />
    <text>His concubine who was in Shechem, she also bore him a son, and he named him Abimelech.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="32" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="32" />
    <text>Gideon the son of Joash died in a good old age, and was buried in the tomb of Joash his father, in Ophrah of the Abiezrites.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="33" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="33" />
    <text>It happened, as soon as Gideon was dead, that the children of Israel turned again, and played the prostitute after the Baals, and made Baal Berith their god.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="34" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="34" />
    <text>The children of Israel didn't remember God their God, who had delivered them out of the hand of all their enemies on every side;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="35" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="35" />
    <text>neither did they show kindness to the house of Jerubbaal, [who is] Gideon, according to all the goodness which he had shown to Israel.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="9" book="JDG" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-JDG">
    <text>9</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Abimelech the son of Jerubbaal went to Shechem to his mother's brothers, and spoke with them, and with all the family of the house of his mother's father, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="Abimelech, son of Gideon (Jerubbaal)">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>Please speak in the ears of all the men of Shechem, 'Is it better for you that all the sons of Jerubbaal, who are seventy persons, rule over you, or that one rule over you?' Remember also that I am your bone and your flesh.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>His mother's brothers spoke of him in the ears of all the men of Shechem all these words: and their hearts inclined to follow Abimelech; for they said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="citizens of Shechem">
    <text>“He is our brother.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>They gave him seventy [pieces] of silver out of the house of Baal Berith, with which Abimelech hired vain and light fellows, who followed him.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>He went to his father's house at Ophrah, and killed his brothers the sons of Jerubbaal, being seventy persons, on one stone: but Jotham the youngest son of Jerubbaal was left; for he hid himself.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>All the men of Shechem assembled themselves together, and all the house of Millo, and went and made Abimelech king, by the oak of the pillar that was in Shechem.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>When they told it to Jotham, he went and stood on the top of Mount Gerizim, and lifted up his voice, and cried, and said to them,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="Jotham, son of Gideon (Jerubbaal)">
    <text>“Listen to me, you men of Shechem, that God may listen to you.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="Jotham, son of Gideon (Jerubbaal)">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>The trees went forth on a time to anoint a king over them; and they said to the olive tree, 'Reign over us.'</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="Jotham, son of Gideon (Jerubbaal)">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>But the olive tree said to them, 'Should I leave my fatness, with which by me they honor God and man, and go to wave back and forth over the trees?'</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="Jotham, son of Gideon (Jerubbaal)">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>The trees said to the fig tree, 'Come and reign over us.'</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="Jotham, son of Gideon (Jerubbaal)">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>But the fig tree said to them, 'Should I leave my sweetness, and my good fruit, and go to wave back and forth over the trees?'</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="Jotham, son of Gideon (Jerubbaal)">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>The trees said to the vine, 'Come and reign over us.'</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="Jotham, son of Gideon (Jerubbaal)">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>The vine said to them, 'Should I leave my new wine, which cheers God and man, and go to wave back and forth over the trees?'</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="Jotham, son of Gideon (Jerubbaal)">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>Then all the trees said to the bramble, 'Come and reign over us.'</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="Jotham, son of Gideon (Jerubbaal)">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>The bramble said to the trees, 'If in truth you anoint me king over you, then come and take refuge in my shade; and if not, let fire come out of the bramble, and devour the cedars of Lebanon.'</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="Jotham, son of Gideon (Jerubbaal)">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>Now therefore, if you have dealt truly and righteously, in that you have made Abimelech king, and if you have dealt well with Jerubbaal and his house, and have done to him according to the deserving of his hands</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="Jotham, son of Gideon (Jerubbaal)">
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>(for my father fought for you, and risked his life, and delivered you out of the hand of Midian:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="Jotham, son of Gideon (Jerubbaal)">
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>and you have risen up against my father's house this day, and have slain his sons, seventy persons, on one stone, and have made Abimelech, the son of his female servant, king over the men of Shechem, because he is your brother);</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="Jotham, son of Gideon (Jerubbaal)">
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>if you then have dealt truly and righteously with Jerubbaal and with his house this day, then rejoice in Abimelech, and let him also rejoice in you:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="Jotham, son of Gideon (Jerubbaal)">
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>but if not, let fire come out from Abimelech, and devour the men of Shechem, and the house of Millo; and let fire come out from the men of Shechem, and from the house of Millo, and devour Abimelech.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>Jotham ran away, and fled, and went to Beer, and lived there, for fear of Abimelech his brother.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>Abimelech was prince over Israel three years.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>God sent an evil spirit between Abimelech and the men of Shechem; and the men of Shechem dealt treacherously with Abimelech:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="24" />
    <text>that the violence done to the seventy sons of Jerubbaal might come, and that their blood might be laid on Abimelech their brother, who killed them, and on the men of Shechem, who strengthened his hands to kill his brothers.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="25" />
    <text>The men of Shechem set an ambush for him on the tops of the mountains, and they robbed all who came along that way by them: and it was told Abimelech.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="26" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="26" />
    <text>Gaal the son of Ebed came with his brothers, and went over to Shechem; and the men of Shechem put their trust in him.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="27" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="27" />
    <text>They went out into the field, and gathered their vineyards, and trod [the grapes], and held festival, and went into the house of their god, and did eat and drink, and cursed Abimelech. </text>
    <verse num="28" />
    <text>Gaal the son of Ebed said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="28" characterId="Gaal, son of Ebed">
    <text>“Who is Abimelech, and who is Shechem, that we should serve him? Isn't he the son of Jerubbaal? and Zebul his officer? Serve the men of Hamor the father of Shechem: but why should we serve him?</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="29" characterId="Gaal, son of Ebed">
    <verse num="29" />
    <text>Would that this people were under my hand! Then I would remove Abimelech.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="29" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <text>He said to Abimelech,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="29" characterId="Gaal, son of Ebed">
    <text>“Increase your army, and come out!”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="30" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="30" />
    <text>When Zebul the ruler of the city heard the words of Gaal the son of Ebed, his anger was kindled.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="31" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="31" />
    <text>He sent messengers to Abimelech craftily, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="31" characterId="Zebul, governor of Shechem">
    <text>“Behold, Gaal the son of Ebed and his brothers are come to Shechem; and behold, they constrain the city [to take part] against you.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="32" characterId="Zebul, governor of Shechem">
    <verse num="32" />
    <text>Now therefore, go up by night, you and the people who are with you, and lie in wait in the field:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="33" characterId="Zebul, governor of Shechem">
    <verse num="33" />
    <text>and it shall be, that in the morning, as soon as the sun is up, you shall rise early, and rush on the city; and behold, when he and the people who are with him come out against you, then may you do to them as you shall find occasion.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="34" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="34" />
    <text>Abimelech rose up, and all the people who were with him, by night, and they laid wait against Shechem in four companies.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="35" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="35" />
    <text>Gaal the son of Ebed went out, and stood in the entrance of the gate of the city: and Abimelech rose up, and the people who were with him, from the ambush.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="36" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="36" />
    <text>When Gaal saw the people, he said to Zebul,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="36" characterId="Gaal, son of Ebed">
    <text>“Behold, people are coming down from the tops of the mountains.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="36" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <text>Zebul said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="36" characterId="Zebul, governor of Shechem">
    <text>“You see the shadow of the mountains as if they were men.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="37" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="37" />
    <text>Gaal spoke again and said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="37" characterId="Gaal, son of Ebed">
    <text>“Behold, people are coming down by the middle of the land, and one company comes by the way of the oak of Meonenim.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="38" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="38" />
    <text>Then Zebul said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="38" characterId="Zebul, governor of Shechem">
    <text>“Now where is your mouth, that you said, 'Who is Abimelech, that we should serve him?' Isn't this the people that you have despised? Please go out now and fight with them.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="39" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="39" />
    <text>Gaal went out before the men of Shechem, and fought with Abimelech.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="40" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="40" />
    <text>Abimelech chased him, and he fled before him, and many fell wounded, even to the entrance of the gate.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="41" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="41" />
    <text>Abimelech lived at Arumah: and Zebul drove out Gaal and his brothers, that they should not dwell in Shechem.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="42" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="42" />
    <text>It happened on the next day, that the people went out into the field; and they told Abimelech.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="43" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="43" />
    <text>He took the people, and divided them into three companies, and laid wait in the field; and he looked, and behold, the people came forth out of the city; He rose up against them, and struck them.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="44" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="44" />
    <text>Abimelech, and the companies that were with him, rushed forward, and stood in the entrance of the gate of the city: and the two companies rushed on all who were in the field, and struck them.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="45" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="45" />
    <text>Abimelech fought against the city all that day; and he took the city, and killed the people who were therein: and he beat down the city, and sowed it with salt.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="46" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="46" />
    <text>When all the men of the tower of Shechem heard of it, they entered into the stronghold of the house of Elberith.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="47" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="47" />
    <text>It was told Abimelech that</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="47" characterId="messenger to Abimelech">
    <text>all the men of the tower of Shechem were gathered together.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="48" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="48" />
    <text>Abimelech went up to Mount Zalmon, he and all the people who were with him; and Abimelech took an axe in his hand, and cut down a bough from the trees, and took it up, and laid it on his shoulder: and he said to the people who were with him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="48" characterId="Abimelech, son of Gideon (Jerubbaal)">
    <text>“What you have seen me do, make haste, and do as I have done!”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="49" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="49" />
    <text>All the people likewise each cut down his bough, and followed Abimelech, and put them at the base of the stronghold, and set the stronghold on fire on them; so that all the people of the tower of Shechem died also, about a thousand men and women.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="50" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="50" />
    <text>Then went Abimelech to Thebez, and encamped against Thebez, and took it.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="51" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="51" />
    <text>But there was a strong tower within the city, and there fled all the men and women, and all they of the city, and shut themselves in, and went up to the roof of the tower.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="52" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="52" />
    <text>Abimelech came to the tower, and fought against it, and drew near to the door of the tower to burn it with fire. </text>
    <verse num="53" />
    <text>A certain woman cast an upper millstone on Abimelech's head, and broke his skull.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="54" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="54" />
    <text>Then he called hastily to the young man his armor bearer, and said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="54" characterId="Abimelech, son of Gideon (Jerubbaal)">
    <text>“Draw your sword, and kill me, that men not say of me, 'A woman killed him.'</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="54" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <text>His young man thrust him through, and he died.” </text>
    <verse num="55" />
    <text>When the men of Israel saw that Abimelech was dead, they departed every man to his place.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="56" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="56" />
    <text>Thus God requited the wickedness of Abimelech, which he did to his father, in killing his seventy brothers;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="57" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="57" />
    <text>and all the wickedness of the men of Shechem did God requite on their heads: and on them came the curse of Jotham the son of Jerubbaal.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="10" book="JDG" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-JDG">
    <text>10</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>After Abimelech there arose to save Israel Tola the son of Puah, the son of Dodo, a man of Issachar; and he lived in Shamir in the hill country of Ephraim.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>He judged Israel twenty-three years, and died, and was buried in Shamir.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>After him arose Jair, the Gileadite; and he judged Israel twenty-two years.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>He had thirty sons who rode on thirty donkey colts, and they had thirty cities, which are called Havvoth Jair to this day, which are in the land of Gilead.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>Jair died, and was buried in Kamon.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>The children of Israel again did that which was evil in the sight of God, and served the Baals, and the Ashtaroth, and the gods of Syria, and the gods of Sidon, and the gods of Moab, and the gods of the children of Ammon, and the gods of the Philistines; and they forsook God, and didn't serve him.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>The anger of God was kindled against Israel, and he sold them into the hand of the Philistines, and into the hand of the children of Ammon.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>They troubled and oppressed the children of Israel that year: eighteen years [oppressed they] all the children of Israel that were beyond the Jordan in the land of the Amorites, which is in Gilead.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>The children of Ammon passed over the Jordan to fight also against Judah, and against Benjamin, and against the house of Ephraim; so that Israel was very distressed.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>The children of Israel cried to God, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="Israelites">
    <text>“We have sinned against you, even because we have forsaken our God, and have served the Baals.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>God said to the children of Israel,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="God">
    <text>“Didn't I save you from the Egyptians, and from the Amorites, from the children of Ammon, and from the Philistines?</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="God">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>The Sidonians also, and the Amalekites, and the Maonites, did oppress you; and you cried to me, and I saved you out of their hand.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="God">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>Yet you have forsaken me, and served other gods: therefore I will save you no more.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="God">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>Go and cry to the gods which you have chosen. Let them save you in the time of your distress!”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>The children of Israel said to God,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="Israelites">
    <text>“We have sinned: do you to us whatever seems good to you; only deliver us, please, this day.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>They put away the foreign gods from among them, and served God; and his soul was grieved for the misery of Israel.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>Then the children of Ammon were gathered together, and encamped in Gilead. The children of Israel assembled themselves together, and encamped in Mizpah.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>The people, the princes of Gilead, said one to another,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="Gilead, leaders of">
    <text>“What man is he who will begin to fight against the children of Ammon? He shall be head over all the inhabitants of Gilead.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="11" book="JDG" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-JDG">
    <text>11</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Now Jephthah the Gileadite was a mighty man of valor, and he was the son of a prostitute: and Gilead became the father of Jephthah.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>Gilead's wife bore him sons; and when his wife's sons grew up, they drove out Jephthah, and said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="Jephthah's half-brothers">
    <text>“You shall not inherit in our father's house; for you are the son of another woman.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>Then Jephthah fled from his brothers, and lived in the land of Tob: and there were gathered vain fellows to Jephthah, and they went out with him.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>It happened after a while, that the children of Ammon made war against Israel.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>It was so, that when the children of Ammon made war against Israel, the elders of Gilead went to get Jephthah out of the land of Tob; </text>
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>and they said to Jephthah,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="Gilead, elders of">
    <text>“Come and be our chief, that we may fight with the children of Ammon.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>Jephthah said to the elders of Gilead,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="Jephthah">
    <text>“Didn't you hate me, and drive me out of my father's house? Why have you come to me now when you are in distress?”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>The elders of Gilead said to Jephthah,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="Gilead, elders of">
    <text>“Therefore we have turned again to you now, that you may go with us, and fight with the children of Ammon; and you shall be our head over all the inhabitants of Gilead.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>Jephthah said to the elders of Gilead,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="Jephthah">
    <text>“If you bring me home again to fight with the children of Ammon, and God deliver them before me, shall I be your head?”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>The elders of Gilead said to Jephthah,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="Gilead, elders of">
    <text>“God shall be witness between us; surely according to your word so will we do.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>Then Jephthah went with the elders of Gilead, and the people made him head and chief over them: and Jephthah spoke all his words before God in Mizpah.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>Jephthah sent messengers to the king of the children of Ammon, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="messengers from Jephthah">
    <text>“What have you to do with me, that you have come to me to fight against my land?”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>The king of the children of Ammon answered to the messengers of Jephthah,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="king of the Ammonites">
    <text>“Because Israel took away my land, when he came up out of Egypt, from the Arnon even to the Jabbok, and to the Jordan: now therefore restore those [lands] again peaceably.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>Jephthah sent messengers again to the king of the children of Ammon; </text>
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>and he said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="messengers from Jephthah">
    <text>“Thus says Jephthah: Israel didn't take away the land of Moab, nor the land of the children of Ammon, </text>
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>but when they came up from Egypt, and Israel went through the wilderness to the Red Sea, and came to Kadesh;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="messengers from Jephthah">
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>then Israel sent messengers to the king of Edom, saying, 'Please let me pass through your land;' but the king of Edom didn't listen. In the same way, he sent to the king of Moab; but he would not: and Israel stayed in Kadesh.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="messengers from Jephthah">
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>Then they went through the wilderness, and went around the land of Edom, and the land of Moab, and came by the east side of the land of Moab, and they encamped on the other side of the Arnon; but they didn't come within the border of Moab, for the Arnon was the border of Moab.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="messengers from Jephthah">
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>Israel sent messengers to Sihon king of the Amorites, the king of Heshbon; and Israel said to him, 'Please let us pass through your land to my place.'</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="messengers from Jephthah">
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>But Sihon didn't trust Israel to pass through his border; but Sihon gathered all his people together, and encamped in Jahaz, and fought against Israel.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="messengers from Jephthah">
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>God, the God of Israel, delivered Sihon and all his people into the hand of Israel, and they struck them: so Israel possessed all the land of the Amorites, the inhabitants of that country.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="messengers from Jephthah">
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>They possessed all the border of the Amorites, from the Arnon even to the Jabbok, and from the wilderness even to the Jordan.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="messengers from Jephthah">
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>So now God, the God of Israel, has dispossessed the Amorites from before his people Israel, and should you possess them?</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="messengers from Jephthah">
    <verse num="24" />
    <text>Won't you possess that which Chemosh your god gives you to possess? So whoever God our God has dispossessed from before us, them will we possess.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="messengers from Jephthah">
    <verse num="25" />
    <text>Now are you anything better than Balak the son of Zippor, king of Moab? Did he ever strive against Israel, or did he ever fight against them?</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="26" characterId="messengers from Jephthah">
    <verse num="26" />
    <text>While Israel lived in Heshbon and its towns, and in Aroer and its towns, and in all the cities that are along by the side of the Arnon, three hundred years; why didn't you recover them within that time?</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="27" characterId="messengers from Jephthah">
    <verse num="27" />
    <text>I therefore have not sinned against you, but you do me wrong to war against me. God, the Judge, be judge this day between the children of Israel and the children of Ammon.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="28" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="28" />
    <text>However the king of the children of Ammon didn't listen to the words of Jephthah which he sent him.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="29" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="29" />
    <text>Then the Spirit of God came on Jephthah, and he passed over Gilead and Manasseh, and passed over Mizpeh of Gilead, and from Mizpeh of Gilead he passed over to the children of Ammon.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="30" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="30" />
    <text>Jephthah vowed a vow to God, and said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="30" characterId="Jephthah">
    <text>“If you will indeed deliver the children of Ammon into my hand, </text>
    <verse num="31" />
    <text>then it shall be, that whatever comes forth from the doors of my house to meet me, when I return in peace from the children of Ammon, it shall be God's, and I will offer it up for a burnt offering.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="32" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="32" />
    <text>So Jephthah passed over to the children of Ammon to fight against them; and God delivered them into his hand.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="33" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="33" />
    <text>He struck them from Aroer until you come to Minnith, even twenty cities, and to Abelcheramim, with a very great slaughter. So the children of Ammon were subdued before the children of Israel.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="34" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="34" />
    <text>Jephthah came to Mizpah to his house; and behold, his daughter came out to meet him with tambourines and with dances: and she was his only child; besides her he had neither son nor daughter.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="35" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="35" />
    <text>It happened, when he saw her, that he tore his clothes, and said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="35" characterId="Jephthah">
    <text>“Alas, my daughter! You have brought me very low, and you are one of those who trouble me; for I have opened my mouth to God, and I can't go back.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="36" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="36" />
    <text>She said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="36" characterId="Jephthah's daughter">
    <text>“My father, you have opened your mouth to God; do to me according to that which has proceeded out of your mouth, because God has taken vengeance for you on your enemies, even on the children of Ammon.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="37" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="37" />
    <text>She said to her father,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="37" characterId="Jephthah's daughter">
    <text>“Let this thing be done for me: let me alone two months, that I may depart and go down on the mountains, and bewail my virginity, I and my companions.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="38" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="38" />
    <text>He said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="38" characterId="Jephthah">
    <text>“Go.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="38" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <text>He sent her away for two months: and she departed, she and her companions, and mourned her virginity on the mountains.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="39" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="39" />
    <text>It happened at the end of two months, that she returned to her father, who did with her according to his vow which he had vowed: and she was a virgin. It was a custom in Israel, </text>
    <verse num="40" />
    <text>that the daughters of Israel went yearly to celebrate the daughter of Jephthah the Gileadite four days in a year.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="12" book="JDG" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-JDG">
    <text>12</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>The men of Ephraim were gathered together, and passed northward; and they said to Jephthah,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="Ephraimites">
    <text>“Why did you pass over to fight against the children of Ammon, and didn't call us to go with you? We will burn your house around you with fire!”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>Jephthah said to them,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="Jephthah">
    <text>“I and my people were at great strife with the children of Ammon; and when I called you, you didn't save me out of their hand.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="Jephthah">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>When I saw that you didn't save me, I put my life in my hand, and passed over against the children of Ammon, and God delivered them into my hand. Why then have you come up to me this day, to fight against me?”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>Then Jephthah gathered together all the men of Gilead, and fought with Ephraim; and the men of Gilead struck Ephraim, because they said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="Ephraimites">
    <text>“You are fugitives of Ephraim, you Gileadites, in the midst of Ephraim, [and] in the midst of Manasseh.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>The Gileadites took the fords of the Jordan against the Ephraimites. It was so, that when [any of] the fugitives of Ephraim said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="Ephraimites">
    <text>Let me go over,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <text>the men of Gilead said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="Gilead, men of">
    <text>“Are you an Ephraimite?”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <text>If he said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="Ephraimites">
    <text>“No;”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>then they said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="Gilead, men of">
    <text>“Now say Shibboleth;”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <text>and he said</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="Ephraimites">
    <text>Sibboleth;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <text>for he couldn't manage to pronounce it right: then they laid hold of him, and killed him at the fords of the Jordan. At that time, forty-two thousand of Ephraim fell.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>Jephthah judged Israel six years. Then died Jephthah the Gileadite, and was buried in [one of] the cities of Gilead.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>After him Ibzan of Bethlehem judged Israel.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>He had thirty sons; and thirty daughters he sent abroad, and thirty daughters he brought in from abroad for his sons. He judged Israel seven years.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>Ibzan died, and was buried at Bethlehem.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>After him Elon the Zebulunite judged Israel; and he judged Israel ten years.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>Elon the Zebulunite died, and was buried in Aijalon in the land of Zebulun.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>After him Abdon the son of Hillel the Pirathonite judged Israel.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>He had forty sons and thirty sons' sons, who rode on seventy donkey colts: and he judged Israel eight years.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>Abdon the son of Hillel the Pirathonite died, and was buried in Pirathon in the land of Ephraim, in the hill country of the Amalekites.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="13" book="JDG" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-JDG">
    <text>13</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>The children of Israel again did that which was evil in the sight of God; and God delivered them into the hand of the Philistines forty years.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>There was a certain man of Zorah, of the family of the Danites, whose name was Manoah; and his wife was barren, and didn't bear.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>The angel of God appeared to the woman, and said to her,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="angel of the LORD, the">
    <text>“See now, you are barren, and don't bear; but you shall conceive, and bear a son.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="angel of the LORD, the">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>Now therefore please beware and drink no wine nor strong drink, and don't eat any unclean thing:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="angel of the LORD, the">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>for, behold, you shall conceive, and bear a son; and no razor shall come on his head; for the child shall be a Nazirite to God from the womb: and he shall begin to save Israel out of the hand of the Philistines.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>Then the woman came and told her husband, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="Manoah's wife, mother of Samson">
    <text>“A man of God came to me, and his face was like the face of the angel of God, very awesome; and I didn't ask him where he was from, neither did he tell me his name:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="Manoah's wife, mother of Samson">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>but he said to me, Behold, you shall conceive, and bear a son; and now drink no wine nor strong drink, and eat not any unclean thing; for the child shall be a Nazirite to God from the womb to the day of his death.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>Then Manoah entreated God, and said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="Manoah, father of Samson">
    <text>“Oh, Lord, please let the man of God whom you did send come again to us, and teach us what we shall do to the child who shall be born.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>God listened to the voice of Manoah; and the angel of God came again to the woman as she sat in the field: but Manoah, her husband, wasn't with her.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>The woman made haste, and ran, and told her husband, and said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="Manoah's wife, mother of Samson">
    <text>“Behold, the man has appeared to me, who came to me the [other] day.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>Manoah arose, and went after his wife, and came to the man, and said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="Manoah, father of Samson">
    <text>“Are you the man who spoke to the woman?”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <text>He said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="angel of the LORD, the">
    <text>“I am.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>Manoah said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="Manoah, father of Samson">
    <text>“Now let your words happen. What shall be the ordering of the child, and [how] shall we do to him?”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>The angel of God said to Manoah,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="angel of the LORD, the">
    <text>“Of all that I said to the woman let her beware.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="angel of the LORD, the">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>She may not eat of anything that comes of the vine, neither let her drink wine or strong drink, nor eat any unclean thing; all that I commanded her let her observe.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>Manoah said to the angel of God,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="Manoah, father of Samson">
    <text>“Please, let us detain you, that we may make a young goat ready for you.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>The angel of God said to Manoah,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="angel of the LORD, the">
    <text>“Though you detain me, I won't eat of your bread; and if you will prepare a burnt offering, you must offer it to God.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <text>For Manoah didn't know that he was the angel of God. </text>
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>Manoah said to the angel of God,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="Manoah, father of Samson">
    <text>“What is your name, that when your words happen, we may honor you?”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>The angel of God said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="angel of the LORD, the">
    <text>“Why do you ask about my name, since it is wonderful?”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>So Manoah took the young goat with the meal offering, and offered it on the rock to God: and [the angel] did wondrously, and Manoah and his wife looked on.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>For it happened, when the flame went up toward the sky from off the altar, that the angel of God ascended in the flame of the altar: and Manoah and his wife looked on; and they fell on their faces to the ground.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>But the angel of God did no more appear to Manoah or to his wife. Then Manoah knew that he was the angel of God. </text>
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>Manoah said to his wife,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="Manoah, father of Samson">
    <text>“We shall surely die, because we have seen God.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>But his wife said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="Manoah's wife, mother of Samson">
    <text>“If God were pleased to kill us, he wouldn't have received a burnt offering and a meal offering at our hand, neither would he have shown us all these things, nor would at this time have told such things as these.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="24" />
    <text>The woman bore a son, and named him Samson: and the child grew, and God blessed him.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="25" />
    <text>The Spirit of God began to move him in Mahaneh Dan, between Zorah and Eshtaol.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="14" book="JDG" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-JDG">
    <text>14</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Samson went down to Timnah, and saw a woman in Timnah of the daughters of the Philistines.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>He came up, and told his father and his mother, and said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="Samson">
    <text>“I have seen a woman in Timnah of the daughters of the Philistines: now therefore get her for me as wife.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>Then his father and his mother said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="Manoah, father of Samson/Manoah's wife, mother of Samson" characterIdOverrideForScript="Manoah, father of Samson">
    <text>“Is there never a woman among the daughters of your brothers, or among all my people, that you go to take a wife of the uncircumcised Philistines?”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <text>Samson said to his father,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="Samson">
    <text>“Get her for me; for she pleases me well.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>But his father and his mother didn't know that it was of God; for he sought an occasion against the Philistines. Now at that time the Philistines had rule over Israel.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>Then went Samson down, and his father and his mother, to Timnah, and came to the vineyards of Timnah: and behold, a young lion roared against him.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>The Spirit of God came mightily on him, and he tore him as he would have torn a young goat; and he had nothing in his hand: but he didn't tell his father or his mother what he had done.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>He went down, and talked with the woman, and she pleased Samson well.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>After a while he returned to take her; and he turned aside to see the carcass of the lion: and behold, there was a swarm of bees in the body of the lion, and honey.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>He took it into his hands, and went on, eating as he went; and he came to his father and mother, and gave to them, and they ate: but he didn't tell them that he had taken the honey out of the body of the lion.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>His father went down to the woman: and Samson made there a feast; for so used the young men to do.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>It happened, when they saw him, that they brought thirty companions to be with him. </text>
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>Samson said to them,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="Samson">
    <text>“Let me tell you a riddle now. If you can declare it to me within the seven days of the feast, and find it out, then I will give you thirty linen garments and thirty changes of clothing;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="Samson">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>but if you can't declare it to me, then you shall give me thirty linen garments and thirty changes of clothing.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <text>They said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="Samson's 30 Philistine companions">
    <text>“Put forth your riddle, that we may hear it.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>He said to them,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="Samson">
    <text>“Out of the eater came forth food. Out of the strong came forth sweetness.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <text>They couldn't in three days declare the riddle. </text>
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>It happened on the seventh day, that they said to Samson's wife,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="Samson's 30 Philistine companions">
    <text>“Entice your husband, that he may declare to us the riddle, lest we burn you and your father's house with fire. Have you called us to impoverish us? Is it not [so]?”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>Samson's wife wept before him, and said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="Samson's Philistine wife">
    <text>“You just hate me, and don't love me. You have put forth a riddle to the children of my people, and haven't told it me.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <text>He said to her,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="Samson">
    <text>“Behold, I haven't told it my father nor my mother, and shall I tell you?”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>She wept before him the seven days, while their feast lasted: and it happened on the seventh day, that he told her, because she pressed him severely; and she told the riddle to the children of her people.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>The men of the city said to him on the seventh day before the sun went down,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="Samson's 30 Philistine companions">
    <text>“What is sweeter than honey? What is stronger than a lion?”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <text>He said to them,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="Samson">
    <text>“If you hadn't plowed with my heifer, you wouldn't have found out my riddle.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>The Spirit of God came mightily on him, and he went down to Ashkelon, and struck thirty men of them, and took their spoil, and gave the changes [of clothing] to those who declared the riddle. His anger was kindled, and he went up to his father's house.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>But Samson's wife was [given] to his companion, whom he had used as his friend.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="15" book="JDG" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-JDG">
    <text>15</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>But it happened after a while, in the time of wheat harvest, that Samson visited his wife with a young goat; and he said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="Samson">
    <text>“I will go in to my wife into the room.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <text>But her father wouldn't allow him to go in. </text>
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>Her father said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="Samson's father-in-law">
    <text>“I most certainly thought that you had utterly hated her; therefore I gave her to your companion. Isn't her younger sister more beautiful than she? Please take her, instead.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>Samson said to them,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="Samson">
    <text>“This time I will be blameless in regard of the Philistines, when I harm them.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>Samson went and caught three hundred foxes, and took torches, and turned tail to tail, and put a torch in the midst between every two tails.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>When he had set the brands on fire, he let them go into the standing grain of the Philistines, and burnt up both the shocks and the standing grain, and also the olive groves.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>Then the Philistines said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="Philistines">
    <text>“Who has done this?”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <text>They said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="informer">
    <text>“Samson, the son-in-law of the Timnite, because he has taken his wife, and given her to his companion.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <text>The Philistines came up, and burnt her and her father with fire. </text>
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>Samson said to them,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="Samson">
    <text>“If you behave like this, surely I will be avenged of you, and after that I will cease.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>He struck them hip and thigh with a great slaughter: and he went down and lived in the cleft of the rock of Etam.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>Then the Philistines went up, and encamped in Judah, and spread themselves in Lehi. </text>
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>The men of Judah said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="Judah, men of">
    <text>“Why have you come up against us?”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <text>They said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="Philistines">
    <text>“We have come up to bind Samson, to do to him as he has done to us.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>Then three thousand men of Judah went down to the cleft of the rock of Etam, and said to Samson,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="Judah, men of">
    <text>“Don't you know that the Philistines are rulers over us? What then is this that you have done to us?”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <text>He said to them,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="Samson">
    <text>“As they did to me, so have I done to them.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>They said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="Judah, men of">
    <text>“We have come down to bind you, that we may deliver you into the hand of the Philistines.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <text>Samson said to them,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="Samson">
    <text>“Swear to me that you will not fall on me yourselves.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>They spoke to him, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="Judah, men of">
    <text>“No; but we will bind you fast, and deliver you into their hand; but surely we will not kill you.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <text>They bound him with two new ropes, and brought him up from the rock.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>When he came to Lehi, the Philistines shouted as they met him: and the Spirit of God came mightily on him, and the ropes that were on his arms became as flax that was burnt with fire, and his bands dropped from off his hands.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>He found a fresh jawbone of a donkey, and put forth his hand, and took it, and struck a thousand men therewith. </text>
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>Samson said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="Samson">
    <text>“With the jawbone of a donkey, heaps on heaps; with the jawbone of a donkey I have struck a thousand men.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>It happened, when he had made an end of speaking, that he cast away the jawbone out of his hand; and that place was called Ramath Lehi.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>He was very thirsty, and called on God, and said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="Samson">
    <text>“You have given this great deliverance by the hand of your servant; and now shall I die for thirst, and fall into the hand of the uncircumcised?”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>But God split the hollow place that is in Lehi, and water came out of it. When he had drunk, his spirit came again, and he revived: therefore its name was called En Hakkore, which is in Lehi, to this day.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>He judged Israel in the days of the Philistines twenty years.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="16" book="JDG" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-JDG">
    <text>16</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Samson went to Gaza, and saw there a prostitute, and went in to her. </text>
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>[It was told] the Gazites, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="person who informed people of Gaza">
    <text>“Samson is here!”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <text>They surrounded him, and laid wait for him all night in the gate of the city, and were quiet all the night, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="Gaza, people of (wicked)">
    <text>[Let be] until morning light, then we will kill him.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>Samson lay until midnight, and arose at midnight, and laid hold of the doors of the gate of the city, and the two posts, and plucked them up, bar and all, and put them on his shoulders, and carried them up to the top of the mountain that is before Hebron.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>It came to pass afterward, that he loved a woman in the valley of Sorek, whose name was Delilah.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>The lords of the Philistines came up to her, and said to her,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="Philistine rulers">
    <text>“Entice him, and see in which his great strength lies, and by what means we may prevail against him, that we may bind him to afflict him; and we will each give you eleven hundred [pieces] of silver.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>Delilah said to Samson,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="Delilah">
    <text>“Please tell me where your great strength lies, and what you might be bound to afflict you.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>Samson said to her,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="Samson">
    <text>“If they bind me with seven green cords that were never dried, then shall I become weak, and be as another man.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>Then the lords of the Philistines brought up to her seven green cords which had not been dried, and she bound him with them.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>Now she had an ambush waiting in the inner room. She said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="Delilah">
    <text>“The Philistines are on you, Samson!”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <text>He broke the cords, as a string of tow is broken when it touches the fire. So his strength was not known. </text>
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>Delilah said to Samson,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="Delilah">
    <text>“Behold, you have mocked me, and told me lies: now please tell me with which you might be bound.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>He said to her,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="Samson">
    <text>“If they only bind me with new ropes with which no work has been done, then shall I become weak, and be as another man.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>So Delilah took new ropes, and bound him therewith, and said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="Delilah">
    <text>“The Philistines are on you, Samson!”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <text>The ambush was waiting in the inner room. He broke them off his arms like a thread. </text>
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>Delilah said to Samson,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="Delilah">
    <text>“Until now, you have mocked me and told me lies. Tell me with what you might be bound.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <text>He said to her,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="Samson">
    <text>“If you weave the seven locks of my head with the web.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>She fastened it with the pin, and said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="Delilah">
    <text>“The Philistines are on you, Samson!”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <text>He awakened out of his sleep, and plucked away the pin of the beam, and the web. </text>
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>She said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="Delilah">
    <text>“How can you say, 'I love you,' when your heart is not with me? You have mocked me these three times, and have not told me where your great strength lies.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>It happened, when she pressed him daily with her words, and urged him, that his soul was troubled to death.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>He told her all his heart, and said to her,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="Samson">
    <text>“No razor has ever come on my head; for I have been a Nazirite to God from my mother's womb. If I am shaved, then my strength will go from me, and I will become weak, and be like any other man.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>When Delilah saw that he had told her all his heart, she sent and called for the lords of the Philistines, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="Delilah">
    <text>“Come up this once, for he has told me all his heart.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <text>Then the lords of the Philistines came up to her, and brought the money in their hand.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>She made him sleep on her knees; and she called for a man, and shaved off the seven locks of his head; and she began to afflict him, and his strength went from him. </text>
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>She said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="Delilah">
    <text>“The Philistines are upon you, Samson!”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <text>He awoke out of his sleep, and said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="Samson">
    <text>“I will go out as at other times, and shake myself free.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <text>But he didn't know that God had departed from him.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>The Philistines laid hold on him, and put out his eyes; and they brought him down to Gaza, and bound him with fetters of brass; and he ground at the mill in the prison.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>However the hair of his head began to grow again after he was shaved.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>The lords of the Philistines gathered them together to offer a great sacrifice to Dagon their god, and to rejoice; for they said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="Philistine rulers">
    <text>“Our god has delivered Samson our enemy into our hand.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="24" />
    <text>When the people saw him, they praised their god; for they said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="Philistines">
    <text>“Our god has delivered our enemy and the destroyer of our country, who has slain many of us, into our hand.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="25" />
    <text>It happened, when their hearts were merry, that they said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="Philistines">
    <text>“Call for Samson, that he may entertain us.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <text>They called for Samson out of the prison; and he performed before them. They set him between the pillars; </text>
    <verse num="26" />
    <text>and Samson said to the boy who held him by the hand,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="26" characterId="Samson">
    <text>“Allow me to feel the pillars whereupon the house rests, that I may lean on them.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="27" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="27" />
    <text>Now the house was full of men and women; and all the lords of the Philistines were there; and there were on the roof about three thousand men and women, who saw while Samson performed.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="28" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="28" />
    <text>Samson called to God, and said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="28" characterId="Samson">
    <text>“Lord God, remember me, please, and strengthen me, please, only this once, God, that I may be at once avenged of the Philistines for my two eyes.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="29" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="29" />
    <text>Samson took hold of the two middle pillars on which the house rested, and leaned on them, the one with his right hand, and the other with his left. </text>
    <verse num="30" />
    <text>Samson said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="30" characterId="Samson">
    <text>“Let me die with the Philistines!”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="30" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <text>He bowed himself with all his might; and the house fell on the lords, and on all the people who were therein. So the dead that he killed at his death were more than those who he killed in his life.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="31" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="31" />
    <text>Then his brothers and all the house of his father came down, and took him, and brought him up, and buried him between Zorah and Eshtaol in the burial site of Manoah his father. He judged Israel twenty years.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="17" book="JDG" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-JDG">
    <text>17</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>There was a man of the hill country of Ephraim, whose name was Micah. </text>
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>He said to his mother,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="Micah of Ephraim">
    <text>“The eleven hundred [pieces] of silver that were taken from you, about which you uttered a curse, and also spoke it in my ears, behold, the silver is with me; I took it.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <text>His mother said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="Micah's mother">
    <text>“Blessed be my son of God.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>He restored the eleven hundred [pieces] of silver to his mother; and his mother said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="Micah's mother">
    <text>“I most certainly dedicate the silver to God from my hand for my son, to make an engraved image and a molten image. Now therefore I will restore it to you.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>When he restored the money to his mother, his mother took two hundred [pieces] of silver, and gave them to the founder, who made of it an engraved image and a molten image: and it was in the house of Micah.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>The man Micah had a house of gods, and he made an ephod, and teraphim, and consecrated one of his sons, who became his priest.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>In those days there was no king in Israel: every man did that which was right in his own eyes.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>There was a young man out of Bethlehem Judah, of the family of Judah, who was a Levite; and he lived there.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>The man departed out of the city, out of Bethlehem Judah, to live where he could find [a place], and he came to the hill country of Ephraim to the house of Micah, as he traveled. </text>
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>Micah said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="Micah of Ephraim">
    <text>“Where did you come from?”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <text>He said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="Levite, young, from Bethlehem">
    <text>“I am a Levite of Bethlehem Judah, and I am looking for a place to live.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>Micah said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="Micah of Ephraim">
    <text>“Dwell with me, and be to me a father and a priest, and I will give you ten [pieces] of silver per year, a suit of clothing, and your food.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <text>So the Levite went in. </text>
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>The Levite was content to dwell with the man; and the young man was to him as one of his sons.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>Micah consecrated the Levite, and the young man became his priest, and was in the house of Micah. </text>
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>Then Micah said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="17" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="Micah of Ephraim">
    <text>“Now know I that God will do good to me, since I have a Levite to my priest.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="18" book="JDG" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-JDG">
    <text>18</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>In those days there was no king in Israel: and in those days the tribe of the Danites sought them an inheritance to dwell in; for to that day [their] inheritance had not fallen to them among the tribes of Israel.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>The children of Dan sent of their family five men from their whole number, men of valor, from Zorah, and from Eshtaol, to spy out the land, and to search it; and they said to them,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="Danites">
    <text>“Go, explore the land!”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <text>They came to the hill country of Ephraim, to the house of Micah, and lodged there.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>When they were by the house of Micah, they knew the voice of the young man the Levite; and they turned aside there, and said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="warriors from Zorah and Eshtaol, five">
    <text>“Who brought you here? What do you do in this place? What do you have here?”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>He said to them,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="Levite, young, from Bethlehem">
    <text>“Thus and thus has Micah dealt with me, and he has hired me, and I am become his priest.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>They said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="warriors from Zorah and Eshtaol, five">
    <text>“Please ask counsel of God, that we may know whether our way which we go shall be prosperous.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>The priest said to them,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="Levite, young, from Bethlehem">
    <text>“Go in peace. Your way in which you go is before God.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>Then the five men departed, and came to Laish, and saw the people who were therein, how they lived in security, in the way of the Sidonians, quiet and secure; for there was none in the land, possessing authority, that might put [them] to shame in anything, and they were far from the Sidonians, and had no dealings with any man.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>They came to their brothers to Zorah and Eshtaol: and their brothers said to them,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="Danites">
    <text>“What do you say?”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>They said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="warriors from Zorah and Eshtaol, five">
    <text>“Arise, and let us go up against them; for we have seen the land, and behold, it is very good. Do you stand still? Don't be slothful to go and to enter in to possess the land.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="warriors from Zorah and Eshtaol, five">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>When you go, you shall come to a secure people, and the land is large; for God has given it into your hand, a place where there is no want of anything that is in the earth.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>There set forth from there of the family of the Danites, out of Zorah and out of Eshtaol, six hundred men girt with weapons of war.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>They went up, and encamped in Kiriath Jearim, in Judah: therefore they called that place Mahaneh Dan, to this day; behold, it is behind Kiriath Jearim.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>They passed there to the hill country of Ephraim, and came to the house of Micah.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>Then the five men who went to spy out the country of Laish answered, and said to their brothers,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="warriors from Zorah and Eshtaol, five">
    <text>“Do you know that there is in these houses an ephod, and teraphim, and an engraved image, and a molten image? Now therefore consider what you have to do.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>They turned aside there, and came to the house of the young man the Levite, even to the house of Micah, and asked him of his welfare.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>The six hundred men girt with their weapons of war, who were of the children of Dan, stood by the entrance of the gate.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>The five men who went to spy out the land went up, and came in there, and took the engraved image, and the ephod, and the teraphim, and the molten image: and the priest stood by the entrance of the gate with the six hundred men girt with weapons of war.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>When these went into Micah's house, and fetched the engraved image, the ephod, and the teraphim, and the molten image, the priest said to them,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="Levite, young, from Bethlehem">
    <text>“What are you doing?”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>They said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="warriors from Zorah and Eshtaol, five">
    <text>“Hold your peace, put your hand on your mouth, and go with us, and be to us a father and a priest. Is it better for you to be priest to the house of one man, or to be priest to a tribe and a family in Israel?”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>The priest's heart was glad, and he took the ephod, and the teraphim, and the engraved image, and went in the midst of the people.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>So they turned and departed, and put the little ones and the livestock and the goods before them.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>When they were a good way from the house of Micah, the men who were in the houses near to Micah's house were gathered together, and overtook the children of Dan.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>They cried to the children of Dan. They turned their faces, and said to Micah,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="Danites">
    <text>“What ails you, that you come with such a company?”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="24" />
    <text>He said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="Micah of Ephraim">
    <text>“You have taken away my gods which I made, and the priest, and have gone away, and what more do I have? How then do you say to me, What ails you?”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="25" />
    <text>The children of Dan said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="Danites">
    <text>“Don't let your voice be heard among us, lest angry fellows fall on you, and you lose your life, with the lives of your household.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="26" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="26" />
    <text>The children of Dan went their way: and when Micah saw that they were too strong for him, he turned and went back to his house.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="27" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="27" />
    <text>They took that which Micah had made, and the priest whom he had, and came to Laish, to a people quiet and secure, and struck them with the edge of the sword; and they burnt the city with fire.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="28" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="28" />
    <text>There was no deliverer, because it was far from Sidon, and they had no dealings with any man; and it was in the valley that lies by Beth Rehob. They built the city, and lived therein.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="29" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="29" />
    <text>They called the name of the city Dan, after the name of Dan their father, who was born to Israel: however the name of the city was Laish at the first.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="30" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="30" />
    <text>The children of Dan set up for themselves the engraved image: and Jonathan, the son of Gershom, the son of Moses, he and his sons were priests to the tribe of the Danites until the day of the captivity of the land.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="18" initialStartVerse="31" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="31" />
    <text>So they set them up Micah's engraved image which he made, all the time that the house of God was in Shiloh.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="19" book="JDG" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-JDG">
    <text>19</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>It happened in those days, when there was no king in Israel, that there was a certain Levite living on the farther side of the hill country of Ephraim, who took to him a concubine out of Bethlehem Judah.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>His concubine played the prostitute against him, and went away from him to her father's house to Bethlehem Judah, and was there the space of four months.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>Her husband arose, and went after her, to speak kindly to her, to bring her again, having his servant with him, and a couple of donkeys: and she brought him into her father's house; and when the father of the young lady saw him, he rejoiced to meet him.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>His father-in-law, the young lady's father, retained him; and he stayed with him three days: so they ate and drink, and lodged there.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>It happened on the fourth day, that they arose early in the morning, and he rose up to depart: and the young lady's father said to his son-in-law,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="father of concubine">
    <text>“Strengthen your heart with a morsel of bread, and afterward you shall go your way.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>So they sat down, ate, and drank, both of them together: and the young lady's father said to the man,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="father of concubine">
    <text>“Please be pleased to stay all night, and let your heart be merry.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>The man rose up to depart; but his father-in-law urged him, and he lodged there again.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>He arose early in the morning on the fifth day to depart; and the young lady's father said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="father of concubine">
    <text>“Please strengthen your heart and stay until the day declines;”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <text>and they both ate. </text>
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>When the man rose up to depart, he, and his concubine, and his servant, his father-in-law, the young lady's father, said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="father of concubine">
    <text>“Behold, now the day draws toward evening, please stay all night: behold, the day grows to an end, lodge here, that your heart may be merry; and tomorrow go on your way early, that you may go home.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>But the man wouldn't stay that night, but he rose up and departed, and came over against Jebus (the same is Jerusalem): and there were with him a couple of donkeys saddled; his concubine also was with him.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>When they were by Jebus, the day was far spent; and the servant said to his master,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="servant of concubine's husband">
    <text>“Please come and let us turn aside into this city of the Jebusites, and lodge in it.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>His master said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="Levite husband of concubine">
    <text>“We won't turn aside into the city of a foreigner, that is not of the children of Israel; but we will pass over to Gibeah.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>He said to his servant,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="Levite husband of concubine">
    <text>“Come and let us draw near to one of these places; and we will lodge in Gibeah, or in Ramah.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>So they passed on and went their way; and the sun went down on them near to Gibeah, which belongs to Benjamin.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>They turned aside there, to go in to lodge in Gibeah: and he went in, and sat him down in the street of the city; for there was no man who took them into his house to lodge.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>Behold, there came an old man from his work out of the field at evening: now the man was of the hill country of Ephraim, and he lived in Gibeah; but the men of the place were Benjamites.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>He lifted up his eyes, and saw the wayfaring man in the street of the city; and the old man said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="old man in Gibeah">
    <text>“Where are you going? Where did you come from?”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>He said to him,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="Levite husband of concubine">
    <text>“We are passing from Bethlehem Judah to the farther side of the hill country of Ephraim. I am from there, and I went to Bethlehem Judah. I am going to the house of God; and there is no man who takes me into his house.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="Levite husband of concubine">
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>Yet there is both straw and provender for our donkeys; and there is bread and wine also for me, and for your handmaid, and for the young man who is with your servants: there is no want of anything.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>The old man said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="old man in Gibeah">
    <text>“Peace be to you; howsoever let all your wants lie on me; only don't lodge in the street.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>So he brought him into his house, and gave the donkeys fodder; and they washed their feet, and ate and drink.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>As they were making their hearts merry, behold, the men of the city, certain base fellows, surrounded the house, beating at the door; and they spoke to the master of the house, the old man, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="wicked men of Gibeah">
    <text>“Bring out the man who came into your house, that we may have sex with him!”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>The man, the master of the house, went out to them, and said to them,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="old man in Gibeah">
    <text>“No, my brothers, please don't act so wickedly; since this man is come into my house, don't do this folly.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="old man in Gibeah">
    <verse num="24" />
    <text>Behold, here is my virgin daughter and his concubine. I will bring them out now. Humble them, and do with them what seems good to you; but to this man don't do any such folly.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="25" />
    <text>But the men wouldn't listen to him: so the man laid hold of his concubine, and brought her out to them; and they had sex with her, and abused her all night until the morning: and when the day began to dawn, they let her go.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="26" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="26" />
    <text>Then came the woman in the dawning of the day, and fell down at the door of the man's house where her lord was, until it was light.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="27" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="27" />
    <text>Her lord rose up in the morning, and opened the doors of the house, and went out to go his way; and behold, the woman his concubine was fallen down at the door of the house, with her hands on the threshold. </text>
    <verse num="28" />
    <text>He said to her,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="28" characterId="Levite husband of concubine">
    <text>“Get up, and let us be going!”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="28" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <text>but no one answered. Then he took her up on the donkey; and the man rose up, and went to his place.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="29" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="29" />
    <text>When he was come into his house, he took a knife, and laid hold on his concubine, and divided her, limb by limb, into twelve pieces, and sent her throughout all the borders of Israel.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="30" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="30" />
    <text>It was so, that all who saw it said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="19" initialStartVerse="30" characterId="Israelites">
    <text>“There was no such deed done nor seen from the day that the children of Israel came up out of the land of Egypt to this day! Consider it, take counsel, and speak.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="20" book="JDG" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-JDG">
    <text>20</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Then all the children of Israel went out, and the congregation was assembled as one man, from Dan even to Beersheba, with the land of Gilead, to God at Mizpah.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>The chiefs of all the people, even of all the tribes of Israel, presented themselves in the assembly of the people of God, four hundred thousand footmen who drew sword.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>(Now the children of Benjamin heard that the children of Israel had gone up to Mizpah.) The children of Israel said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="Israelites">
    <text>“Tell us, how did this wickedness happen?”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>The Levite, the husband of the woman who was murdered, answered,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="Levite husband of concubine">
    <text>“I came into Gibeah that belongs to Benjamin, I and my concubine, to lodge.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="Levite husband of concubine">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>The men of Gibeah rose against me, and surrounded the house by night. They thought to have slain me, and they forced my concubine, and she is dead.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="Levite husband of concubine">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>I took my concubine, and cut her in pieces, and sent her throughout all the country of the inheritance of Israel; for they have committed lewdness and folly in Israel.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="Levite husband of concubine">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>Behold, you children of Israel, all of you, give here your advice and counsel.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>All the people arose as one man, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="Israelites">
    <text>“We will not any of us go to his tent, neither will we any of us turn to his house.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="Israelites">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>But now this is the thing which we will do to Gibeah: [we will go up] against it by lot;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="Israelites">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>and we will take ten men of one hundred throughout all the tribes of Israel, and one hundred of one thousand, and a thousand out of ten thousand, to get food for the people, that they may do, when they come to Gibeah of Benjamin, according to all the folly that they have worked in Israel.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>So all the men of Israel were gathered against the city, knit together as one man.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>The tribes of Israel sent men through all the tribe of Benjamin, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="Israelites" delivery="mourning">
    <text>“What wickedness is this that is happen among you?</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="Israelites" delivery="mourning">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>Now therefore deliver up the men, the base fellows, who are in Gibeah, that we may put them to death, and put away evil from Israel.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <text>But Benjamin would not listen to the voice of their brothers the children of Israel.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>The children of Benjamin gathered themselves together out of the cities to Gibeah, to go out to battle against the children of Israel.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>The children of Benjamin were numbered on that day out of the cities twenty-six thousand men who drew the sword, besides the inhabitants of Gibeah, who were numbered seven hundred chosen men.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>Among all this people there were seven hundred chosen men left-handed; everyone could sling stones at a hair-breadth, and not miss.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>The men of Israel, besides Benjamin, were numbered four hundred thousand men who drew sword: all these were men of war.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>The children of Israel arose, and went up to Bethel, and asked counsel of God; and they said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="Israelites">
    <text>“Who shall go up for us first to battle against the children of Benjamin?”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <text>God said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="God">
    <text>“Judah [shall go up] first.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>The children of Israel rose up in the morning, and encamped against Gibeah.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>The men of Israel went out to battle against Benjamin; and the men of Israel set the battle in array against them at Gibeah.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>The children of Benjamin came forth out of Gibeah, and destroyed down to the ground of the Israelites on that day Twenty-two thousand men.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>The people, the men of Israel, encouraged themselves, and set the battle again in array in the place where they set themselves in array the first day.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>The children of Israel went up and wept before God until evening; and they asked of God, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="Israelites (excluding Benjamites)" delivery="weeping">
    <text>“Shall I again draw near to battle against the children of Benjamin my brother?”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <text>God said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="God">
    <text>“Go up against him.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="24" />
    <text>The children of Israel came near against the children of Benjamin the second day.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="25" />
    <text>Benjamin went forth against them out of Gibeah the second day, and destroyed down to the ground of the children of Israel again eighteen thousand men; all these drew the sword.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="26" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="26" />
    <text>Then all the children of Israel, and all the people, went up, and came to Bethel, and wept, and sat there before God, and fasted that day until evening; and they offered burnt offerings and peace offerings before God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="27" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="27" />
    <text>The children of Israel asked of God (for the ark of the covenant of God was there in those days, </text>
    <verse num="28" />
    <text>and Phinehas, the son of Eleazar, the son of Aaron, stood before it in those days), saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="28" characterId="Israelites (excluding Benjamites)" delivery="weeping">
    <text>“Shall I yet again go out to battle against the children of Benjamin my brother, or shall I cease?”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="28" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <text>God said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="28" characterId="God">
    <text>“Go up; for tomorrow I will deliver him into your hand.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="29" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="29" />
    <text>Israel set ambushes all around Gibeah.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="30" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="30" />
    <text>The children of Israel went up against the children of Benjamin on the third day, and set themselves in array against Gibeah, as at other times.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="31" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="31" />
    <text>The children of Benjamin went out against the people, and were drawn away from the city; and they began to strike and kill of the people, as at other times, in the highways, of which one goes up to Bethel, and the other to Gibeah, in the field, about thirty men of Israel.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="32" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="32" />
    <text>The children of Benjamin said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="32" characterId="Benjamites">
    <text>“They are struck down before us, as at the first.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="32" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <text>But the children of Israel said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="32" characterId="Israelites">
    <text>“Let us flee, and draw them away from the city to the highways.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="33" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="33" />
    <text>All the men of Israel rose up out of their place, and set themselves in array at Baal Tamar: and the ambushers of Israel broke forth out of their place, even out of Maareh Geba.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="34" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="34" />
    <text>There came over against Gibeah ten thousand chosen men out of all Israel, and the battle was severe; but they didn't know that evil was close on them.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="35" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="35" />
    <text>God struck Benjamin before Israel; and the children of Israel destroyed of Benjamin that day twenty-five thousand one hundred men: all these drew the sword.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="36" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="36" />
    <text>So the children of Benjamin saw that they were struck; for the men of Israel gave place to Benjamin, because they trusted the ambushers whom they had set against Gibeah.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="37" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="37" />
    <text>The ambushers hurried, and rushed on Gibeah; and the ambushers drew themselves along, and struck all the city with the edge of the sword.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="38" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="38" />
    <text>Now the appointed sign between the men of Israel and the ambushers was that they should make a great cloud of smoke rise up out of the city.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="39" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="39" />
    <text>The men of Israel turned in the battle, and Benjamin began to strike and kill of the men of Israel about thirty persons; for they said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="39" characterId="Benjamites">
    <text>“Surely they are struck down before us, as in the first battle.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="40" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="40" />
    <text>But when the cloud began to arise up out of the city in a pillar of smoke, the Benjamites looked behind them; and behold, the whole of the city went up in smoke to the sky.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="41" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="41" />
    <text>The men of Israel turned, and the men of Benjamin were dismayed; for they saw that evil had come on them.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="42" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="42" />
    <text>Therefore they turned their backs before the men of Israel to the way of the wilderness; but the battle followed hard after them; and those who came out of the cities destroyed them in its midst.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="43" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="43" />
    <text>They surrounded the Benjamites, chased them, [and] trod them down at [their] resting place, as far as over against Gibeah toward the sunrise.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="44" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="44" />
    <text>There fell of Benjamin eighteen thousand men; all these [were] men of valor.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="45" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="45" />
    <text>They turned and fled toward the wilderness to the rock of Rimmon: and they gleaned of them in the highways five thousand men, and followed hard after them to Gidom, and struck of them two thousand men.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="46" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="46" />
    <text>So that all who fell that day of Benjamin were twenty-five thousand men who drew the sword; all these [were] men of valor.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="47" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="47" />
    <text>But six hundred men turned and fled toward the wilderness to the rock of Rimmon, and stayed in the rock of Rimmon four months.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="20" initialStartVerse="48" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="48" />
    <text>The men of Israel turned again on the children of Benjamin, and struck them with the edge of the sword, both the entire city, and the livestock, and all that they found: moreover all the cities which they found they set on fire.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="21" book="JDG" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-JDG">
    <text>21</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Now the men of Israel had sworn in Mizpah, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="Israel, men of">
    <text>“There shall not any of us give his daughter to Benjamin as wife.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>The people came to Bethel, and sat there until evening before God, and lifted up their voices, and wept severely. </text>
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>They said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="Israelites" delivery="weeping">
    <text>“God, the God of Israel, why has this happened in Israel, that there should be today one tribe lacking in Israel?”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>It happened on the next day that the people rose early, and built there an altar, and offered burnt offerings and peace offerings. </text>
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>The children of Israel said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="Israelites">
    <text>“Who is there among all the tribes of Israel who didn't come up in the assembly to God?”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <text>For they had made a great oath concerning him who didn't come up to God to Mizpah, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="Israelites">
    <text>“He shall surely be put to death.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>The children of Israel grieved for Benjamin their brother, and said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="Israelites">
    <text>“There is one tribe cut off from Israel this day.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="Israelites">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>How shall we provide wives for those who remain, since we have sworn by God that we will not give them of our daughters to wives?”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>They said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="Israelites">
    <text>“What one is there of the tribes of Israel who didn't come up to God to Mizpah?”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <text>Behold, there came none to the camp from Jabesh Gilead to the assembly.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>For when the people were numbered, behold, there were none of the inhabitants of Jabesh Gilead there.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>The congregation sent there twelve thousand men of the most valiant, and commanded them, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="Israelite assembly">
    <text>“Go and strike the inhabitants of Jabesh Gilead with the edge of the sword, with the women and the little ones.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="Israelite assembly">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>This is the thing that you shall do: you shall utterly destroy every male, and every woman who has lain with a man.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>They found among the inhabitants of Jabesh Gilead four hundred young virgins, who had not known man by lying with him; and they brought them to the camp to Shiloh, which is in the land of Canaan.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>The whole congregation sent and spoke to the children of Benjamin who were in the rock of Rimmon, and proclaimed peace to them.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>Benjamin returned at that time; and they gave them the women whom they had saved alive of the women of Jabesh Gilead: and yet so they weren't enough for them.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>The people grieved for Benjamin, because that God had made a breach in the tribes of Israel.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>Then the elders of the congregation said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="Israelite assembly, elders of">
    <text>“How shall we provide wives for those who remain, since the women are destroyed out of Benjamin?”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>They said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="Israelite assembly, elders of">
    <text>“There must be an inheritance for those who are escaped of Benjamin, that a tribe not be blotted out from Israel.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="Israelite assembly, elders of">
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>However we may not give them wives of our daughters, for the children of Israel had sworn, saying, Cursed is he who gives a wife to Benjamin.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>They said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="Israelite assembly, elders of">
    <text>“Behold, there is a feast of God from year to year in Shiloh, which is on the north of Bethel, on the east side of the highway that goes up from Bethel to Shechem, and on the south of Lebonah.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>They commanded the children of Benjamin, saying,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="Israelite assembly, elders of">
    <text>“Go and lie in wait in the vineyards, </text>
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>and see, and behold, if the daughters of Shiloh come out to dance in the dances, then come out of the vineyards, and each man catch his wife of the daughters of Shiloh, and go to the land of Benjamin.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="Israelite assembly, elders of">
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>It shall be, when their fathers or their brothers come to complain to us, that we will say to them, Grant them graciously to us, because we didn't take for each man his wife in battle, neither did you give them to them, otherwise you would now be guilty.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>The children of Benjamin did so, and took them wives, according to their number, of those who danced, whom they carried off. They went and returned to their inheritance, built the cities, and lived in them.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="24" />
    <text>The children of Israel departed there at that time, every man to his tribe and to his family, and they went out from there every man to his inheritance.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="21" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="narrator-JDG">
    <verse num="25" />
    <text>In those days there was no king in Israel: every man did that which was right in his own eyes.</text>
  </block>
  <UnappliedSplits />
</book>