<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<book id="ROM" singlevoice="false" pageheader="ROMANS CHP">
  <block style="mt" chapter="0" book="ROM" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-ROM">
    <text>ROMANS</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" book="ROM" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-ROM">
    <text>1</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Paul, a servant of Jesus Christ our Lord, was called to be an apostle, set apart for the Good News of God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>This Good News is that which he promised before through his prophets in the holy Scriptures,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>It concerns his Son, who was born of the seed of David according to the flesh.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>He was declared to be the Son of God with power, according to the Spirit of holiness, by the resurrection from the dead, Jesus Christ our Lord,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>through whom we received grace and apostleship, for obedience of faith among all the nations, for his name’s sake;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>among whom you are also called to belong to Jesus Christ;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>to all who are in Rome, beloved of God, called to be saints: Grace to you and peace from God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>First, I thank my God through Jesus Christ for all of you, that your faith is proclaimed throughout the whole world.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>For God is my witness, whom I serve in my spirit in the Good News of his Son, how unceasingly I make mention of you always in my prayers.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>I pray that at last, by God’s will, the way may be opened for me to visit you.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>For I long to see you, that I may impart to you some spiritual gift, to the end that you may be established;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>that is, that I with you may be encouraged in you, each of us by the other’s faith, both yours and mine.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>Now I don’t desire to have you unaware, brothers, that I often planned to come to you, and was hindered so far, that I might have some fruit among you also, even as among the rest of the Gentiles.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>I am debtor both to Greeks and to foreigners, both to the wise and to the foolish.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>So, as much as is in me, I am eager to preach the Good News to you also who are in Rome.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>For I am not ashamed of the Good News of Christ, for it is the power of God for salvation for everyone who believes; for the Jew first, and also for the Greek.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>For in it is revealed God’s righteousness from faith to faith. As it is written,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="scripture">
    <text>«But the righteous shall live by faith.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>For the wrath of God is revealed from heaven against all ungodliness and unrighteousness of men, who hold the truth in unrighteousness.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>That which is known of God is revealed in men for God revealed it to them.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>For the invisible things of him since the creation of the world are clearly seen, being perceived through the things that are made, even his everlasting power and divinity; that they may be without excuse.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>Because, knowing God, they didn’t glorify him as God, neither did they give thanks. Instead, they became vain in their reasoning, and their senseless heart was darkened.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>Professing themselves to be wise, they became fools.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>They traded the glory of the incorruptible God for the likeness of an image of corruptible man, and of birds, and four-footed animals, and creeping things.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="24" />
    <text>Therefore God also gave them up in the lusts of their hearts to uncleanness, that their bodies should be dishonored among themselves.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="25" />
    <text>They exchanged the truth of God for a lie, and worshiped and served the creature rather than the Creator, who is blessed forever. Amen.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="26" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="26" />
    <text>For this reason, God gave them up to vile passions. For their women changed the natural function into that which is against nature.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="27" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="27" />
    <text>Likewise also the men, leaving the natural function of the woman, burned in their lust toward one another. They were doing what is inappropriate with men, and receiving in themselves the due penalty of their error.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="28" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="28" />
    <text>Even as they refused to have God in their knowledge, God gave them up to a reprobate mind, to do those things which are not fitting.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="29" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="29" />
    <text>They are filled with all unrighteousness, sexual immorality, wickedness, covetousness, malice; full of envy, murder, strife, deceit, evil habits, secret slanderers,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="30" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="30" />
    <text>backbiters, hateful to God, insolent, haughty, boastful, inventors of evil things, disobedient to parents,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="31" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="31" />
    <text>without understanding, covenant breakers, without natural affection, unforgiving, unmerciful;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="32" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="32" />
    <text>They know that God said that those who practice such things are worthy of death. Yet not only do they do them, they also approve of others who practice them.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" book="ROM" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-ROM">
    <text>2</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Therefore you are without excuse, O man, whoever you are who judge. For in that which you judge another, you condemn yourself. For you who judge practice the same things.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>We know that the judgment of God is according to truth against those who practice such things.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>Do you think this, O man who judges those who practice such things, and do the same, that you will escape the judgment of God?</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>Will you ignore the wealth of His mercy, his patience and his broad-mindedness? Do you not know that God’s purpose of grace is to lead you to repentance?</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>But according to your hardness and unrepentant heart you are treasuring up for yourself wrath in the day of wrath, revelation, and of the righteous judgment of God;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="scripture">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>who «will pay back to everyone according to their works:»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>Those who by patience in well-doing seek for glory, honor, and incorruptibility, they will receive eternal life.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>But to those who are self-seeking, and don’t obey the truth, but obey unrighteousness, there will be wrath and indignation.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>Oppression and anguish will be on every soul of man who works evil, to the Jew first, and also to the Greek.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>But glory, honor, and peace go to every man who works good, to the Jew first, and also to the Greek.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>For there is no partiality with God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>For as many as have sinned without law will also perish without the law. As many as have sinned under the law will be judged by the law.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>For it isn’t the hearers of the law who are righteous before God, but the doers of the law will be justified.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>(For when Gentiles who don’t have the law do by nature the things of the law, they are a law to themselves, even though they do not have the law.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>They show that the work of the law is written in their hearts. Their conscience testifies with them and their thoughts among themselves accusing or else excusing them).</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>There will be a day when God will judge the secrets of men, according to the Good News that I preach.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>Indeed you bear the name of a Jew, and rest on the law, and glory in God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>You know his will, and approve the things that are excellent, being instructed out of the law.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>You are confident that you yourself are a guide of the blind, a light to those who are in darkness.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>You think you are a corrector of the foolish, a teacher of babies, having in the law the form of knowledge and of the truth.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>You therefore who teach another, don’t you teach yourself? You who preach that a man shouldn’t steal, do you steal?</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>You who say a man shouldn’t commit adultery. Do you commit adultery? You who abhor idols, do you rob temples?</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>You who glory in the law, through your disobedience of the law do you dishonor God? </text>
    <verse num="24" />
    <text>For just as it is written:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="scripture">
    <text>«the name of God is blasphemed among the Gentiles because of you,»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="25" />
    <text>For circumcision indeed profits, if you are a doer of the law. But if you are a transgressor of the law, your circumcision has become uncircumcision.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="26" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="26" />
    <text>If therefore the uncircumcised keep the ordinances of the law, won’t his uncircumcision be accounted as circumcision?</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="27" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="27" />
    <text>Won’t the uncircumcision which is by nature, if it fulfills the law, judge you, who with the letter and circumcision are a transgressor of the law?</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="28" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="28" />
    <text>For he is not a Jew who is one outwardly, neither is that circumcision which is outward in the flesh;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="29" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="29" />
    <text>but he is a Jew who is one inwardly, and circumcision is that of the heart. It is in the spirit not in the letter; His praise is not from men, but from God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" book="ROM" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-ROM">
    <text>3</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Then what advantage does the Jew have? Or what is the profit of circumcision?</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>Much in every way! Because first of all, they were entrusted with the oracles of God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>For what if some were without faith? Will their lack of faith nullify the faithfulness of God?</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>May it never be! Yes, let God be found true, but every man a liar. As it is written,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="scripture">
    <text>«That you might be justified in your words, and might prevail when you come into judgment.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>But if our unrighteousness commends the righteousness of God, what will we say? Is God unrighteous who inflicts wrath? I speak like men do.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>May it never be! For then how will God judge the world?</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>For if the truth of God through my lie abounded to his glory, why am I also still judged as a sinner?</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>Why not (as we are slanderously reported, and as some affirm that we say), «Let us do evil, that good may come?» Those who say so are justly condemned.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>What then? Are we better than they? No, in no way! For we previously warned both Jews and Greeks, that they are all under sin. </text>
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>As it is written,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="scripture">
    <text>«There is no one righteous; no, not one.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="scripture">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>There is no one who understands. There is no one who seeks after God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="scripture">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>They have all turned away. They have together become unprofitable. There is no one who does good, no, not, so much as one.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="scripture">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>«Their throat is an open tomb. With their tongues they have used deceit.» «The poison of vipers is under their lips.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="scripture">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>«Their mouth is full of cursing and bitterness.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="scripture">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>«Their feet are swift to shed blood. </text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="scripture">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>Destruction and misery are in their ways.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="scripture">
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>The way of peace, they haven’t known.» </text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="scripture">
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>«There is no fear of God before their eyes.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>Now we know that whatever things the law says, it speaks to those who are under the law. No one can say that he does not know what sin is, and all the world may be held accountable to the judgment of God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>Because by the works of the law, no flesh will be justified in his sight. For through the law comes the knowledge of sin.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>But now apart from the law, a righteousness of God has been revealed, being testified by the law and the prophets;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>This righteousness of God comes through faith in Jesus Christ to all and on all those who believe. For there is no distinction.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>For all have sinned, and fall short of the glory of God;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="24" />
    <text>Anyone can be justified freely by his grace through the redemption that is in Christ Jesus.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="25" />
    <text>God gave him to be an atoning sacrifice, through faith in his blood, for a demonstration of his righteousness through the passing over of prior sins, in God’s forbearance;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="26" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="26" />
    <text>God demonstrates his righteousness at this present time; that he might himself be just, and the justifier of him who has faith in Jesus.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="27" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="27" />
    <text>Where then is the boasting? It is excluded. By what kind of law? Of works? No, but by a law of faith.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="28" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="28" />
    <text>We maintain therefore that a man is justified by faith apart from the works of the law.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="29" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="29" />
    <text>Or is God the God of Jews only? Isn’t he the God of Gentiles also? Yes, of Gentiles also.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="30" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="30" />
    <text>Indeed there is one God who will justify the circumcised by faith, and the uncircumcised through faith.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="31" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="31" />
    <text>Do we then nullify the law through faith? May it never be! No, we establish the law.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" book="ROM" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-ROM">
    <text>4</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>What then will we say that Abraham, our forefather, has found according to the flesh?</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>For if Abraham was justified by works, he has something to boast about, but not toward God. </text>
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>For what does the Scripture say?</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="scripture">
    <text>«Abraham believed God, and it was accounted to him for righteousness.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>Now to him who works, the reward is not counted as grace, but as something owed.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>But to him who doesn’t work, but believes in him who justifies the ungodly, his faith is accounted for righteousness.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>Even as David also pronounces blessing on the man to whom God counts righteousness apart from works. </text>
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>David said:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="scripture">
    <text>«Blessed are they whose iniquities are forgiven, whose sins are covered.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="scripture">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>Blessed is the man whom the Lord will by no means charge with sin.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>Is this blessing then pronounced on the circumcised, or on the uncircumcised also? For we say that faith was accounted to Abraham for righteousness.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>How then was it counted? When he was in circumcision, or in uncircumcision? Not in circumcision, but in uncircumcision.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>He received the sign of circumcision, a seal of the righteousness of the faith which he had while he was in uncircumcision. In this way Abraham is the spiritual father of all those who believe, though they might be in uncircumcision, that righteousness might also be accounted to them.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>He is the father of circumcision to those who not only are of the circumcision, but who also walk in the steps of that faith of our father Abraham, which he had in uncircumcision.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>God promised Abraham and his descendants that they would be heirs to the world. This promise was made not because Abraham had obeyed the law , but because he believed in God and had been accepted by him.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>For if those who are of the law are heirs, faith is made void, and the promise is made of no effect.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>For the law works wrath, for where there is no law, neither is there disobedience.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>Therefore, God’s promise depends on faith, in order that the promise may be guaranteed as God’s gift to all the descendants of Abraham.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <text>It is not only for those who obey the law but also for those who believe as Abraham believed in God because he is the spiritual father of us all. </text>
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>As the Scriptures say:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="scripture">
    <text>«I have made you a father of many nations.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <text>Abraham is our father in the sight of God, in whom he believed --- The God who gives life to the dead, and calls the things that are not, as though they were.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>Who in hope believed against hope, to the end that he might become a father of many nations, according to that which had been spoken,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="scripture">
    <text>«So will your seed be.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>Without being weakened in faith, he didn’t consider his own body, already having been worn out, (he being about a hundred years old), and the deadness of Sarah’s womb.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>Yet, looking to the promise of God, he didn’t waver through unbelief, but grew strong through faith, giving glory to God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>He was fully assured that what God had promised, God was also able to perform.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>Therefore it also was «reckoned to him for righteousness.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>Now it was not written that it was accounted to him for his sake alone.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="24" />
    <text>It was accounted for our sake also, to whom it will be accounted, who believe in him who raised Jesus, our Lord, from the dead.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="25" />
    <text>Jesus was delivered up for our trespasses, and was raised for our justification.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" book="ROM" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-ROM">
    <text>5</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Being therefore justified by faith, we have peace with God through our Lord Jesus Christ;</text>
    <sound startVerse="-999" userSpecifiesLocation="true" />
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>Through Jesus we also have our access, by faith, into this grace in which we stand. We rejoice in hope of the glory of God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>Not only this, but we also rejoice in our sufferings, knowing that suffering works perseverance; </text>
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>and perseverance, proven character; and proven character, hope:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>and hope doesn’t disappoint us, because God’s love has been poured out into our hearts through the Holy Spirit who was given to us.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>For while we were yet weak, at the right time Christ died for the ungodly.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>For one will hardly die for a righteous man. Yet perhaps for a righteous person someone would even dare to die.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>But God commends his own love toward us, in that while we were yet sinners, Christ died for us.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>Much more then, being now justified by his blood, we will be saved from God’s wrath through him.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>For if, while we were enemies, we were reconciled to God through the death of his Son, much more, being reconciled, we will be saved by his life.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>Not only so, but we also rejoice in God through our Lord Jesus Christ, through whom we have now received the reconciliation.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>Sin entered the world through one man, and his sin brought death. As a result, death has spread throughout the whole human race because everyone has sinned.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>For until the law, sin was in the world; but sin is not charged when there is no law.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>Nevertheless death reigned from Adam until Moses, even over those whose sins weren’t like Adam’s disobedience, who is a foreshadowing of him who was to come.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>But the free gift isn’t like the trespass. For if by the trespass of the one the many died, much more did the grace of God, and the gift by the grace of the one man, Jesus Christ, abound to the many.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>The gift is not as through one who sinned: for the judgment came by one to condemnation, but the free gift came of many trespasses to justification.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>For if by the trespass of the one, death reigned through the one, so much more will those who receive the abundance of grace and of the gift of righteousness reign in life through the one, Jesus Christ.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>So then as through one trespass, all men were condemned; even so through one act of righteousness, all men were justified to life.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>For as through the one man’s disobedience many were made sinners, even so through the obedience of the one, many will be made righteous.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>The law came in besides, that the trespass might abound; but where sin abounded, grace abounded more exceedingly.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>As sin reigned in death, even so grace might reign through righteousness to eternal life through Jesus Christ our Lord.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="6" book="ROM" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-ROM">
    <text>6</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>What shall we say then? Shall we continue in sin, that grace may abound?</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>May it never be! We who died to sin, how could we live in it any longer?</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>Or don’t you know that all we who were baptized into Christ Jesus were baptized into his death?</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>So when we were baptized, we were buried with him because we died with him. And therefore, just as Christ was raised by the power of the glorious Father, we too may live a new life.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>For if we have become united with him in the likeness of his death, we will also be part of his resurrection.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>We know this, that our old man was crucified with him, that the body of sin might be done away with, so that we would no longer be in bondage to sin.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>For he who has died has been freed from sin.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>But if we be dead with Christ, we believe that we will also live with him.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>We know that Christ, being raised from the dead, dies no more. Death no more has dominion over him!</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>For the death that he died, he died to sin one time; but the life that he lives, he lives to God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>Thus consider yourselves also to be dead to sin, but alive to God in Christ Jesus our Lord.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>Therefore don’t let sin reign in your mortal body, that you should obey it in its lusts.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>Neither present your members to sin as instruments of unrighteousness. Rather, present yourselves to God, as alive from the dead, and your members as instruments of righteousness to God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>For sin will not have dominion over you. For you are not under law, but under grace.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>What then? Shall we sin, because we are not under law, but under grace? May it never be!</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>You do not know this? When you are put in the service of someone as slaves, you are slaves of the master whom you obey. So, either you are slaves to sin, and sin leads you to death, or you are servants of God, and God makes you righteous because you obey him.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>But thanks be to God, that, whereas you were bondservants of sin, you became obedient from the heart to that form of teaching whereunto you were delivered.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>Being made free from sin, you became bondservants of righteousness.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>I use a human comparison because you have trouble understanding. Formerly, as slaves, you put your body in the service of an immoral life and ever increasing wickedness, and the result was disobedience to God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <text>Similarly, today, as slaves, put your body in the service of what is right, and the result will be a life that pleases God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>For when you were servants of sin, you were free in regard to righteousness.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>What fruit then did you have at that time in the things of which you are now ashamed? For the end of those things is death.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>But now you have been set free from sin and are slaves of God. With that you get a life completely devoted to him, and the result is that you have eternal life.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>For the wages of sin is death, but the free gift of God is eternal life in Christ Jesus our Lord.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="7" book="ROM" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-ROM">
    <text>7</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Or don’t you know, brothers (for I speak to men who know the law), that the law has dominion over a man for as long as he lives?</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>For the woman that has a husband is bound by law to the husband while he lives. But if the husband dies, she is discharged from the law of the husband.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>So then if, while the husband lives, she is joined to another man, she would be called an adulteress. But if the husband dies, she is free from the law, so that she is no adulteress, though she is joined to another man.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>Therefore, my brothers, you also were made dead to the law through the body of Christ, that you would be joined to another, to him who was raised from the dead, that we might bring forth fruit to God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>For when we were in the flesh, the sinful passions which were through the law, worked in our members to bring forth fruit to death.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>But now we have been discharged from the law, having died to that in which we were held; so that we serve in newness of the spirit, and not in oldness of the letter.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>What shall we say then? Is the law sin? May it never be! However, I wouldn’t have known sin, except through the law. For I wouldn’t have known coveting, unless the law had said,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="scripture">
    <text>«You shall not covet.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>But sin, finding occasion through the commandment, produced in me all kinds of coveting. For apart from the law, sin is dead.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>I was alive apart from the law once, but when the commandment came, sin revived, </text>
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>and I died. The commandment, which was for life, this I found to be for death;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>For sin, finding occasion through the commandment, deceived me, and through it killed me.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>Therefore the law indeed is holy, and the commandment holy, and righteous, and good.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>Did then that which is good become death to me? May it never be! In order that sin might be recognized as sin, it produced death in me through what was good. That way, through the commandment, sin might become utterly sinful.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>For we know that the law is spiritual, but I am fleshly, sold under sin.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>For I don’t know what I am doing. For I don’t practice what I desire to do; but what I hate, that I do.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>But if what I don’t desire, that I do, I consent to the law that it is good.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>So now it is no more I that do it, but sin which dwells in me.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>For I know that in me, that is, in my flesh, dwells no good thing. For desire is present with me, but I don’t find it doing that which is good.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>For the good which I desire, I don’t do; but the evil which I don’t desire, that I practice.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>But if what I don’t desire, that I do, it is no more I that do it, but sin which dwells in me.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>I find then the law, that, to me, while I desire to do good, evil is present.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>For in my inward man, I delight in God’s law.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>But I see a different law in my members, warring against the law of my mind, and bringing me into captivity under the law of sin which is in my members.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="24" />
    <text>What a wretched man I am! Who will deliver me out of the body of this death?</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="7" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="25" />
    <text>I thank God through Jesus Christ, our Lord! So then with the mind, I myself serve God’s law, but with the flesh, the sin’s law.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="8" book="ROM" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-ROM">
    <text>8</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>There is therefore now no condemnation to those who are in Christ Jesus, who don’t walk according to the flesh, but according to the Spirit.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>For the law of the Spirit of life in Christ Jesus made me free from the law of sin and of death.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>For what the law couldn’t do because it was weak through the flesh, God did. By sending his own Son in the likeness of sinful flesh and for sin, He condemned sin in the flesh.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>In that way, the ordinance of the law might be fulfilled in us, who walk not after the flesh, but after the Spirit.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>For those who live according to the flesh set their minds on the things of the flesh, but those who live according to the Spirit, the things of the Spirit.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>For the mind of the flesh is death, but the mind of the Spirit is life and peace.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>The mind of the flesh is hostile towards God; for it is not subject to God’s law, neither indeed can it be.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>Those who are in the flesh can’t please God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>But you are not in the flesh but in the Spirit and so the Spirit of God Dwells in you. But if any man does not have the Spirit of Christ, he does not belong to God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>If Christ is in you, the body is dead because of sin, but the spirit is alive because of righteousness.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>But if the Spirit of him who raised up Jesus from the dead dwells in you, he who raised up Christ Jesus from the dead will also give life to your mortal bodies through his Spirit who dwells in you.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>So then, brothers, we are debtors, not to the flesh, to live after the flesh.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>For if you live after the flesh, you must die; but if by the Spirit you put to death the deeds of the body, you will live.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>For as many as are led by the Spirit of God, these are children of God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>For you didn’t receive the spirit of slavery that leads you back into fear again. You received the Spirit of adoption, by whom we cry, «Abba! Father!»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>The Spirit himself testifies with our spirit that we are children of God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>And if we are children, then heirs; heirs of God, and joint heirs with Christ. Therefore, if we share in his suffering, we also share in his glory.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>For I consider that the sufferings of this present time are not worthy to be compared with the glory which will be revealed toward us.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>For the creation waits with eager expectation for the children of God to be revealed.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>For the creation was subjected to vanity, not of its own will, but because of him who subjected it, in hope</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>that the creation itself also will be delivered from the bondage of decay into the liberty of the glory of the children of God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>For we know that the whole creation groans and travails in pain together until now.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>Not only so, but ourselves also, who have the first fruits of the Spirit, even we ourselves groan within ourselves, waiting for adoption, the redemption of our body.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="24" />
    <text>For we were saved in hope, but hope that is seen is not hope. For who hopes for that which he sees?</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="25" />
    <text>But if we hope for that which we don’t see, we wait for it with patience.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="26" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="26" />
    <text>In the same way, the Spirit also helps our weaknesses, for we don’t know how to pray as we ought. But the Spirit himself makes intercession for us with groanings which can’t be uttered.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="27" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="27" />
    <text>He who searches the hearts knows what is on the Spirit’s mind, because he makes intercession for the saints according to God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="28" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="28" />
    <text>We know that all things work together for good for those who love God, to those who are called according to his purpose.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="29" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="29" />
    <text>For whom he foreknew, he also predestined to be conformed to the image of his Son, that he might be the firstborn among many brothers.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="30" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="30" />
    <text>Whom he predestined, those he also called. Whom he called, those he also justified. Whom he justified, those he also glorified.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="31" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="31" />
    <text>What then shall we say about these things? If God is for us, who can be against us?</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="32" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="32" />
    <text>He who didn’t spare his own Son, but delivered him up for us all, how would he not also with him freely give us all things?</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="33" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="33" />
    <text>Who could bring a charge against God’s chosen ones? It is God who justifies.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="34" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="34" />
    <text>Who is he who condemns? It is Christ who died, yes rather, who was raised from the dead, who is at the right hand of God, who also makes intercession for us.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="35" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="35" />
    <text>Who shall separate us from the love of Christ? Could oppression, or anguish, or persecution, or famine, or nakedness, or peril, or sword?</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="36" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="36" />
    <text>Even as it is written,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="36" characterId="scripture">
    <text>«For your sake we are killed all day long. We were accounted as sheep for the slaughter.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="37" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="37" />
    <text>No, in all these things, we are more than conquerors through him who loved us.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="38" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="38" />
    <text>For I am persuaded, that neither death, nor life, nor angels, nor principalities, nor things present, nor things to come, nor powers,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="8" initialStartVerse="39" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="39" />
    <text>nor height, nor depth, nor any other created thing, will be able to separate us from the love of God, which is in Christ Jesus our Lord.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="9" book="ROM" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-ROM">
    <text>9</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>I tell the truth in Christ. I am not lying, my conscience confirms it in the Holy Spirit.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>I have great sorrow and unceasing pain in my heart.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>For I could wish that I myself were accursed from Christ for my brothers’ sake, my relatives according to the flesh.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>They are Israelites and are the people God chose for himself; the glory, the covenants, the giving of the law, the service, and the promises;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>Theirs are the patriarchs, and from them is traced the human ancestry of Christ, who is God over all, forever praised! Amen.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>But it is not as though the word of God has come to nothing. For they are not all Israel, that are of Israel.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>Neither, because they are Abraham’s seed, are they all children. But,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="scripture">
    <text>«In Isaac will your seed be called.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>That is, it is not the children of the flesh who are children of God, but the children of the promise are counted as a seed. </text>
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>For this is a word of promise,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="scripture">
    <text>«At the appointed time I will come, and Sarah will have a son.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>Not only so, but Rebecca also conceived by one, by our father Isaac.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>For being not yet born, neither having done anything good or bad, that the purpose of God according to election might stand, not of works, but of him who calls, </text>
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>it was said to her,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="scripture">
    <text>«The elder will serve the younger.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>Even as it is written,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="scripture">
    <text>«Jacob I loved, but Esau I hated.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>What shall we say then? Is there unrighteousness with God? May it never be! </text>
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>For he said to Moses,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="scripture">
    <text>«I will have mercy on whom I have mercy, and I will have compassion on whom I have compassion.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>So then it is not of him who wills, nor of him who runs, but of God who has mercy. </text>
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>For the Scripture says to Pharaoh,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="scripture">
    <text>«For this very purpose I caused you to be raised up, that I might show in you my power, and that my name might be proclaimed in all the earth.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>So then, he has mercy on whom he desires, and he hardens whom he desires.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>You will say then to me, «Why does he still find fault? For who withstands his will?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>But indeed, O man, who are you to reply against God?</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="scripture">
    <text>«Will the thing formed ask him who formed it, ‹Why did you make me like this?› »</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>Or hasn’t the potter a right over the clay, from the same lump to make one part a vessel for honor, and another for dishonor?</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>What if God, willing to show his wrath, and to make his power known, endured with much patience vessels of wrath made for destruction.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>What if he did this to make known the riches of his glory on vessels of mercy, which he prepared beforehand for glory.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="24" />
    <text>We are the ones he chose, not only from the Jews, but also from the Gentiles.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="25" />
    <text>As he says also in Hosea,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="scripture">
    <text>«I will call them ‹my people,› which were not my people; and her ‹beloved,› who was not beloved.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="26" characterId="scripture">
    <verse num="26" />
    <text>«It will be that in the place where it was said to them, ‹You are not my people,› There they will be called ‹children of the living God.› »</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="27" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="27" />
    <text>Isaiah cries concerning Israel,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="27" characterId="scripture">
    <text>«If the number of the children of Israel are as the sand of the sea, it is the remnant who will be saved;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="28" characterId="scripture">
    <verse num="28" />
    <text>for He will finish the work and cut it short in righteousness, because the LORD will make a short work upon the earth.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="29" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="29" />
    <text>As Isaiah has said before,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="29" characterId="scripture">
    <text>«Unless the Lord of Armies had left us a seed, we would have become like Sodom, and would have been made like Gomorrah.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="30" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="30" />
    <text>What shall we say then? That the Gentiles, who didn’t follow after righteousness, attained to righteousness, even the righteousness which is of faith.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="31" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="31" />
    <text>But Israel, following after a law of righteousness, didn’t arrive at the law of righteousness.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="32" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="32" />
    <text>Why? Because they didn’t seek it by faith, but as it were by works of the law. They stumbled over the stumbling stone; </text>
    <verse num="33" />
    <text>even as it is written,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="9" initialStartVerse="33" characterId="scripture">
    <text>«Behold, I lay in Zion a stumbling stone and a rock of offense; and no one who believes in him will be disappointed.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="10" book="ROM" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-ROM">
    <text>10</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Brothers, my heart’s desire and my prayer to God is for Israel, that they may be saved.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>For I testify about them that they have a zeal for God, but not according to knowledge.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>For being ignorant of God’s righteousness, and seeking to establish their own righteousness, they didn’t subject themselves to the righteousness of God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>For Christ is the fulfillment of the law for righteousness to everyone who believes.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>For Moses writes about the righteousness of the law,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="scripture">
    <text>«The one who does them will live by them.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>But the righteousness which is of faith says this,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="God">
    <text>«Don’t say in your heart, ‹Who will ascend into heaven?›</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <text>(that is, to bring Christ down); </text>
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>or,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="God">
    <text>‹Who will descend into the abyss?›</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <text>(that is, to bring Christ up from the dead.)»</text>
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>But what does it say?</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="scripture">
    <text>«The word is near you, in your mouth, and in your heart»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <text>that is, the word of faith, which we preach:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>that if you will confess with your mouth that Jesus is Lord, and believe in your heart that God raised him from the dead, you will be saved.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>For with the heart, one believes unto righteousness; and with the mouth confession is made unto salvation. </text>
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>For the Scripture says,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="scripture">
    <text>«Whoever believes in him will not be disappointed.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>For there is no distinction between Jew and Greek; for the same Lord is Lord of all, and is rich to all who call on him. </text>
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>For,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="scripture">
    <text>«Whoever will call on the name of the Lord will be saved.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>How then will they call on him in whom they have not believed? How will they believe in him whom they have not heard? How will they hear without a preacher?</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>And how will they preach unless they are sent? As it is written:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="scripture">
    <text>«How beautiful are the feet of those who preach the Good News of peace, who bring glad tidings of good things!»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>But they didn’t all listen to the glad news. For Isaiah says,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="scripture">
    <text>«Lord, who has believed our report?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>So faith comes by hearing, and hearing by the word of God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>But I ask, didn’t they hear? Yes, most certainly,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="scripture">
    <text>«Their sound went out into all the earth, their words to the ends of the world.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>But I ask, didn’t Israel know? First Moses says,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="scripture">
    <text>«I will provoke you to jealousy with that which is no nation, with a nation void of understanding I will make you angry.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>Isaiah is very bold, and says,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="scripture">
    <text>«I was found by those who didn’t seek me. I was revealed to those who didn’t ask for me.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>But as to Israel he says,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="10" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="scripture">
    <text>«All day long I stretched out my hands to a disobedient and contrary people.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="11" book="ROM" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-ROM">
    <text>11</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>I ask then, did God reject his people? May it never be! For I also am an Israelite, a descendant of Abraham, of the tribe of Benjamin.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>God didn’t reject his people, which he foreknew. Or don’t you know what the Scripture says about Elijah? How he pleads with God against Israel:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="scripture">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>«Lord, they have killed your prophets, they have broken down your altars; and I am left alone, and they seek my life.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>But how does God answer him?</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="scripture">
    <text>«I have reserved for myself seven thousand men, who have not bowed the knee to Baal.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>Even so then at this present time also there is a remnant according to the election of grace.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>And if by grace, then it is no longer of works; otherwise grace is no longer grace. But if it is of works, it is no longer grace; otherwise work is no longer work.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>What then? That which Israel seeks for, that he didn’t obtain, but the chosen ones obtained it, and the rest were hardened. </text>
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>According as it is written,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="scripture">
    <text>«God gave them a spirit of stupor, eyes that they should not see, and ears that they should not hear, to this very day.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>David says,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="scripture">
    <text>«Let their table be made a snare, and a trap, a stumbling block, and a retribution to them.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="scripture">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>Let their eyes be darkened, that they may not see. Bow down their back always.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>I ask then, did they stumble that they might fall? May it never be! But by their fall salvation has come to the Gentiles, to provoke them to jealousy.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>Their disobedience has brought great benefits to the world, and their failure as a people has brought great benefits to those who are not Jewish. So when the Jews participate fully in salvation, the benefits are even greater.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>For I speak to you who are Gentiles. Since then as I am an apostle to Gentiles, I glorify my ministry.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>I do this so that by any means I may provoke to jealousy those who are my flesh, and may save some of them.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>For if the rejection of them is the reconciling of the world, what would their acceptance be, but life from the dead?</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>If the first fruit is holy, so is the lump. If the root is holy, so are the branches.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>But some of the branches were broken off, and you, being a wild olive, were grafted in among them. You became partakers with them of the root and of the richness of the olive tree.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>Don’t boast over the branches. If you boast, it is not you who support the root, but the root supports you.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>You will say then, «Branches were broken off, that I might be grafted in.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>True; by their unbelief they were broken off, and you stand by your faith. Don’t be conceited, but fear;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>for if God didn’t spare the natural branches, neither will he spare you.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>See then the goodness and severity of God. Toward those who fell, severity; but toward you, goodness, if you continue in his goodness; otherwise you also will be cut off.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>They also, if they don’t continue in their unbelief, will be grafted in, for God is able to graft them in again.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="24" />
    <text>For if you were cut out of that which is by nature a wild olive tree, and were grafted contrary to nature into a good olive tree, how much more will these, which are the natural branches, be grafted into their own olive tree?</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="25" />
    <text>For I don’t desire you to be ignorant, brothers, of this mystery, so that you won’t be wise in your own conceits: A partial hardening has happened to Israel until the fullness of the Gentiles has come in.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="26" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="26" />
    <text>Then all Israel will be saved. Even as it is written,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="26" characterId="scripture">
    <text>«There will come out of Zion the Deliverer, and he will turn away ungodliness from Jacob.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="27" characterId="scripture">
    <verse num="27" />
    <text>This is my covenant to them, when I will take away their sins.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="28" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="28" />
    <text>Concerning the Good News, they are enemies for your sake. But concerning the election, they are beloved for the fathers’ sake.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="29" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="29" />
    <text>For the gifts and the calling of God are irrevocable.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="30" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="30" />
    <text>For in time past you were disobedient to God, but now you have obtained mercy by their disobedience.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="31" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="31" />
    <text>The jews also have now been disobedient. By the mercy shown to you they may also obtain mercy some day.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="32" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="32" />
    <text>For God has shut up all to disobedience, that he might have mercy on all.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="33" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="33" />
    <text>Oh the depth of the riches both of the wisdom and the knowledge of God! How unsearchable are his judgments, and his ways past tracing out!</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="34" characterId="scripture">
    <verse num="34" />
    <text>«For who has known the mind of the Lord? Or who has been his counselor?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="35" characterId="scripture">
    <verse num="35" />
    <text>«Or who has first given to him, and it will be repaid to him again?»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="11" initialStartVerse="36" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="36" />
    <text>For of him, and through him, and to him, are all things. To him be the glory for ever! Amen.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="12" book="ROM" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-ROM">
    <text>12</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Therefore I urge you, brothers, by the mercies of God, to present your bodies a living sacrifice, holy, acceptable to God, which is your spiritual service.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>Don’t be conformed to this world, but be transformed by the renewing of your mind. That way you may prove what is the good, well-pleasing, and perfect will of God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>For I say, through the grace that was given me, to every man who is among you: Do not think of yourself more highly than you ought, but rather think reasonably, as God has apportioned to each of you a measure of faith.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>For we have many members in one body, and all the members don’t have the same function.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>In the same way, we who are many, are one body in Christ, and individually members one of another.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>We each have gifts differing according to the grace that was given to us. If we have been given prophecy, let us prophesy according to the proportion of our faith;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>if service, let us give ourselves to service; or he who teaches, to his teaching;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>or he who exhorts, to his exhorting: he who gives, let him do it with liberality; he who rules, with diligence; he who shows mercy, with cheerfulness.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>Let love be without hypocrisy. Abhor that which is evil. Cling to that which is good.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>In love of the brothers be tenderly affectionate one to another; in honor preferring one another.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>Do not lag in diligence. Be fervent in spirit; serving the Lord.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>Rejoice in hope; endure in troubles; continue steadfastly in prayer.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>contribute to the needs of the saints; give to hospitality.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>Bless those who persecute you; bless, and don’t curse.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>Rejoice with those who rejoice. Weep with those who weep.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>Be of the same mind one toward another. Don’t set your mind on high things, but associate with the humble. Don’t be wise in your own conceits.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>Repay no one evil for evil. Respect what is honorable in the sight of all men.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>If it is possible, as much as it is up to you, be at peace with all men.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>Don’t seek revenge yourselves, beloved, but give place to God’s wrath. For it is written,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="scripture">
    <text>«Vengeance belongs to me; I will repay, says the Lord.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>Therefore</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="scripture">
    <text>«If your enemy is hungry, feed him. If he is thirsty, give him a drink; for in doing so, you will heap coals of fire on his head.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="12" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>Don’t be overcome by evil, but overcome evil with good.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="13" book="ROM" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-ROM">
    <text>13</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Let every soul be in subjection to the higher authorities, for there is no authority except from God, and those who exist are ordained by God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>Therefore he who resists the authority, withstands the ordinance of God; and those who withstand will receive to themselves damnation.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>For rulers are not a terror for those who do right, but for those who do wrong. Do you desire to have no fear of those in authority? Do that which is right and they will commend you.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>A leader is a servant of God to you for good. But if you do that which is evil, be afraid, for he doesn’t bear the sword in vain; for he is a servant of God, an avenger for wrath to him who does evil.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>Therefore you need to be in subjection, not only because of the wrath, but also for conscience’ sake.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>For this reason you also pay taxes, for they are servants of God’s service, attending continually on this very thing.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>Give therefore to everyone what you owe: taxes to whom taxes are due; customs to whom customs; respect to whom respect; honor to whom honor.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>Owe no one anything, except to love one another; for he who loves his neighbor has fulfilled the law. </text>
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>For the commandments,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="scripture">
    <text>«You shall not commit adultery, You shall not murder, You shall not steal, You shall not give false testimony, You shall not covet,»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <text>and whatever other commandments there are, are all summed up in this saying, namely,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="scripture">
    <text>«You shall love your neighbor as yourself.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>Love doesn’t harm a neighbor. Love therefore is the fulfillment of the law.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>Do this, knowing the time, that it is already time for you to awaken out of sleep, for salvation is now nearer to us than when we first believed.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>The night is far gone, and the day is near. Let’s therefore throw off the works of darkness, and let’s put on the armor of light.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>Let us walk properly, as in the day; not in reveling and drunkenness, not in sexual promiscuity and lustful acts, and not in strife and jealousy.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="13" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>But put on the Lord Jesus Christ, and make no provision for the flesh, for its lusts.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="14" book="ROM" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-ROM">
    <text>14</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Now accept one who is weak in faith, but not for disputes over opinions.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>One man has faith to eat all things, but he who is weak eats only vegetables.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>Don’t let him who eats despise him who doesn’t eat. Don’t let him who doesn’t eat judge him who eats, for God has accepted him.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>Who are you who judge another’s servant? To his own lord he stands or falls. Yes, he will be made to stand, for God has power to make him stand.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>One man esteems one day as more important. Another esteems every day alike. Let each man be fully assured in his own mind.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>He who observes the day, observes it to the Lord; and he who does not observe the day, to the Lord he does not observe it. He who eats, eats to the Lord, for he gives God thanks. He who doesn’t eat, to the Lord he doesn’t eat, and gives God thanks.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>For none of us lives to himself, and none dies to himself.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>For if we live, we live to the Lord. Or if we die, we die to the Lord. If therefore we live or die, we are the Lord’s.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>For to this end Christ died, rose, and lived again, that he might be Lord of both the dead and the living.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>But you, why do you judge your brother? Or you again, why do you despise your brother? For we will all stand before the judgment seat of Christ. </text>
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>For it is written,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="scripture">
    <text>« ‹As I live,› says the Lord, ‹to me every knee will bow. Every tongue will confess to God.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>So then each one of us will give account of himself to God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>Therefore let’s not judge one another any more. But judge this rather, that no man put a stumbling block in his brother’s way, or an occasion for falling.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>I know, and am persuaded in the Lord Jesus, that nothing is unclean of itself; Except that to him who considers anything to be unclean, to him it is unclean.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>Yet if because of food your brother is grieved, you walk no longer in love. Don’t destroy with your food him for whom Christ died.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>Then don’t let your good be slandered,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>for the Kingdom of God is not eating and drinking, but righteousness, peace, and joy in the Holy Spirit.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>For he who serves Christ in these things is acceptable to God and approved by men.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>So then, let us follow after things which make for peace, and things by which we may build one another up.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>Don’t overthrow God’s work for food’s sake. All things indeed are clean, however it is evil for that man who creates a stumbling block by eating.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>It is good to not eat meat, drink wine, nor do anything by which your brother stumbles, is offended, or is made weak.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>Do you have faith? Have it to yourself before God. Happy is he who doesn’t judge himself in that which he approves.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="14" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>But he who doubts is damned if he eats, because it isn’t of faith; and whatever is not of faith is sin.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="15" book="ROM" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-ROM">
    <text>15</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Now we who are strong ought to bear the weaknesses of the weak, and not to please ourselves.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>Let each one of us please his neighbor for that which is good, to be building him up.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>For even Christ didn’t please himself. But, as it is written,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="scripture">
    <text>«The reproaches of those who reproached you fell on me.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>For whatever things were written before were written for our learning. That through patience and through encouragement of the Scriptures we might have hope.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>Now the God of patience and of encouragement grant you to be of the same mind one with another according to Christ Jesus,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>that with one accord you may with one mouth glorify the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>Therefore accept one another, even as Christ also accepted you, to the glory of God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>Now I say that Jesus Christ has been made a servant of the circumcision for the truth of God, that he might confirm the promises given to the fathers,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>and that the Gentiles might glorify God for his mercy. As it is written,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="scripture">
    <text>«Therefore will I give praise to you among the Gentiles, and sing to your name.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>Again he says,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="scripture">
    <text>«Rejoice, you Gentiles, with his people.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>Again,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="scripture">
    <text>«Praise the Lord, all you Gentiles! Let all the peoples praise him.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>Again, Isaiah says,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="scripture">
    <text>«There will be the root of Jesse, he who arises to rule over the Gentiles; in him the Gentiles will hope.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>Now may the God of hope fill you with all joy and peace in believing, that you may abound in hope, in the power of the Holy Spirit.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>I myself am also persuaded about you, my brothers, that you yourselves are full of goodness. You are filled with all knowledge, able also to admonish others.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>But I write the more boldly to you in part, as reminding you, because of the grace that was given to me by God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>That I should be a servant of Christ Jesus to the Gentiles, serving as a priest the Good News of God, that the offering up of the Gentiles might be made acceptable, sanctified by the Holy Spirit.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>I have therefore my boasting in Christ Jesus in things pertaining to God.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>For I will not dare to speak of any things except those which Christ worked through me, for the obedience of the Gentiles, by word and deed,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>in the power of signs and wonders, in the power of God’s Spirit; so that from Jerusalem, and around as far as to Illyricum, I have fully preached the Good News of Christ;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>yes, making it my aim to preach the Good News, not where Christ was already named, that I might not build on another’s foundation. </text>
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>But, as it is written,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="scripture">
    <text>«They will see, to whom no news of him came. They who haven’t heard will understand.»</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>Therefore also I was hindered these many times from coming to you.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>But now, no longer having any place in these regions, and having these many years a longing to come to you,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="24" />
    <text>when I journey to Spain, I will come to you. For I hope to see you on my journey, and to be helped on my way there by you, if first I may enjoy your company for a while.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="25" />
    <text>But now, I say, I am going to Jerusalem, serving the saints.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="26" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="26" />
    <text>For it has been the good pleasure of Macedonia and Achaia to make a certain contribution for the poor among the saints who are at Jerusalem.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="27" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="27" />
    <text>Yes, it has been their good pleasure, and they are their debtors. For if the Gentiles have been made partakers of their spiritual things, they owe it to them also to serve them in fleshly things.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="28" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="28" />
    <text>When therefore I have accomplished this, and have sealed to them this fruit, I will go on by way of you to Spain.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="29" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="29" />
    <text>I know that, when I come to you, I will come in the fullness of the blessing of the Good News of Christ.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="30" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="30" />
    <text>Now I beg you, brothers, by our Lord Jesus Christ, and by the love of the Spirit, that you strive together with me in your prayers to God for me,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="31" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="31" />
    <text>that I may be delivered from those who are disobedient in Judea, and that my service which I have for Jerusalem may be acceptable to the saints;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="32" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="32" />
    <text>that I may come to you in joy through the will of God, and together with you, find rest.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="15" initialStartVerse="33" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="33" />
    <text>Now the God of peace be with you all. Amen.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="16" book="ROM" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-ROM">
    <text>16</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>I commend to you Phoebe, our sister, who is a servant of the assembly that is at Cenchreae.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>Receive her in the Lord, in a way worthy of the saints, and assist her in whatever matter she may need from you. She herself also has been a helper of many, and of my own self.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>Greet Prisca and Aquila, my fellow workers in Christ Jesus.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>They almost died for me. I and all the assemblies of the Gentiles give thanks for them.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>Greet the assembly that is in their house. Greet Epaenetus, my beloved, who is the first fruits of Achaia to Christ.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>Greet Mary, who labored much for us.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>Greet Andronicus and Junia, my relatives and my fellow prisoners, who are notable among the apostles, who also were in Christ before me.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>Greet Amplias, my beloved in the Lord.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>Greet Urbanus, our fellow worker in Christ, and Stachys, my beloved.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>Greet Apelles, the approved in Christ. Greet those who are of the household of Aristobulus.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>Greet Herodion, my kinsman. Greet them of the household of Narcissus, who are in the Lord.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>Greet Tryphaena and Tryphosa, who labor in the Lord. Greet Persis, the beloved, who labored much in the Lord.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>Greet Rufus, the chosen in the Lord, and his mother and mine.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>Greet Asyncritus, Phlegon, Hermes, Patrobas, Hermas, and the brothers who are with them.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>Greet Philologus and Julia, Nereus and his sister, and Olympas, and all the saints who are with them.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>Greet one another with a holy kiss. The assemblies of Christ greet you.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>Now I beg you, brothers, look out for those who are causing the divisions and occasions of stumbling, contrary to the doctrine which you learned, and turn away from them.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>For those who are such don’t serve our Lord, Jesus Christ, but their own belly; and by their smooth and flattering speech, they deceive the hearts of the innocent.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>For your obedience has become known to all. I rejoice therefore over you. But I desire to have you wise in that which is good, but innocent in that which is evil.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>And the God of peace will quickly crush Satan under your feet. The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with you.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>Timothy, my fellow worker, greets you, as do Lucius, Jason, and Sosipater, my relatives.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="Tertius">
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>I, Tertius, who write the letter, greet you in the Lord.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>Gaius, my host and host of the whole assembly, greets you. Erastus, the treasurer of the city, greets you, as does Quartus, the brother.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="24" />
    <text>The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with you all! Amen.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="25" />
    <text>Now to him who is able to establish you according to my Good News and the preaching of Jesus Christ, according to the revelation of the mystery which has been kept secret through long ages,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="26" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="26" />
    <text>but now is revealed, and by the Scriptures of the prophets. According to the commandment of the eternal God, is made known for obedience of faith to all the nations;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="16" initialStartVerse="27" characterId="narrator-ROM">
    <verse num="27" />
    <text>to the only wise God, through Jesus Christ, to whom be the glory forever! Amen.</text>
  </block>
  <UnappliedSplits />
</book>