<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<book id="1PE" singlevoice="false" pageheader="1 Petrus Pasal">
  <block style="mt" chapter="0" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="mt" chapter="0" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1PE">
      <text>1 PETER</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <text>1 PETRUS</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" book="1PE" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="c" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="0">
      <text>1 PETER CHP 1</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <text>1</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="1" />
      <text>Peter, an apostle of Jesus Christ, to the chosen ones who are living as foreigners in the Dispersion in Pontus, Galatia, Cappadocia, Asia, and Bithynia,</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Dari Petrus, rasul Yesus Kristus, kepada orang-orang pendatang, yang tersebar di Pontus, Galatia, Kapadokia, Asia Kecil dan Bitinia,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="2" />
      <text>according to the foreknowledge of God the Father, in sanctification of the Spirit, that you may obey Jesus Christ and be sprinkled with his blood: Grace to you and peace be multiplied.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>yaitu orang-orang yang dipilih, sesuai dengan rencana Allah, Bapa kita, dan yang dikuduskan oleh Roh, supaya taat kepada Yesus Kristus dan menerima percikan darah-Nya. Kiranya kasih karunia dan damai sejahtera makin melimpah atas kamu.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="3" />
      <text>Blessed be the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ. Who according to his great mercy became our father again to a living hope through the resurrection of Jesus Christ from the dead,</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>Terpujilah Allah dan Bapa Tuhan kita Yesus Kristus, yang karena rahmat-Nya yang besar telah melahirkan kita kembali oleh kebangkitan Yesus Kristus dari antara orang mati, kepada suatu hidup yang penuh pengharapan,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="4" />
      <text>to an incorruptible and undefiled inheritance that doesn't fade away, reserved in Heaven for you.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>untuk menerima suatu bagian yang tidak dapat binasa, yang tidak dapat cemar dan yang tidak dapat layu, yang tersimpan di sorga bagi kamu.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="5" />
      <text>By the power of God you are being guarded through faith for a salvation ready to be revealed in the last time.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>Yaitu kamu, yang dipelihara dalam kekuatan Allah karena imanmu sementara kamu menantikan keselamatan yang telah tersedia untuk dinyatakan pada zaman akhir.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="6" />
      <text>This is why you greatly rejoice, though now for a little while, if need be, you have been put to grief in various trials.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>Bergembiralah akan hal itu, sekalipun sekarang ini kamu seketika harus berdukacita oleh berbagai-bagai pencobaan.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="7" />
      <text>These trials have come so that the proof of your faith, which is more precious than gold that perishes even though it is tested by fire, may be found to result in praise, glory, and honor at the revelation of Jesus Christ.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>Maksud semuanya itu ialah untuk membuktikan kemurnian imanmu—yang jauh lebih tinggi nilainya dari pada emas yang fana, yang diuji kemurniannya dengan api—sehingga kamu memperoleh puji-pujian dan kemuliaan dan kehormatan pada hari Yesus Kristus menyatakan diri-Nya.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="8" />
      <text>Though you have not seen him, you love him; and even though you do not see him now, you believe in him and are filled with inexpressible and glorious joy.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>Sekalipun kamu belum pernah melihat Dia, namun kamu mengasihi-Nya. Kamu percaya kepada Dia, sekalipun kamu sekarang tidak melihat-Nya. Kamu bergembira karena sukacita yang mulia dan yang tidak terkatakan,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="9" />
      <text>For you are receiving the goal of your faith, the salvation of your souls.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>karena kamu telah mencapai tujuan imanmu, yaitu keselamatan jiwamu.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="10" />
      <text>Concerning this salvation, the prophets sought and searched diligently. They prophesied of the grace that would come to you.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>Keselamatan itulah yang diselidiki dan diteliti oleh nabi-nabi, yang telah bernubuat tentang kasih karunia yang diuntukkan bagimu.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="11" />
      <text>They wondered who or what kind of time the Spirit of Christ, which was in them, pointed to, when he predicted the sufferings of Christ, and the glories that would follow them.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>Dan mereka meneliti saat yang mana dan yang bagaimana yang dimaksudkan oleh Roh Kristus, yang ada di dalam mereka, yaitu Roh yang sebelumnya memberi kesaksian tentang segala penderitaan yang akan menimpa Kristus dan tentang segala kemuliaan yang menyusul sesudah itu.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="12" />
      <text>To them it was revealed, that not to themselves, but to you, they ministered these things, which now have been announced to you through those who preached the Good News to you by the Holy Spirit sent out from heaven; which things angels desire to look into.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>Kepada mereka telah dinyatakan, bahwa mereka bukan melayani diri mereka sendiri, tetapi melayani kamu dengan segala sesuatu yang telah diberitakan sekarang kepada kamu dengan perantaraan mereka, yang oleh Roh Kudus, yang diutus dari sorga, menyampaikan berita Injil kepada kamu, yaitu hal-hal yang ingin diketahui oleh malaikat-malaikat.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="13" />
      <text>Therefore prepare your minds for action! Be sober and set your hope fully on the grace that will be brought to you at the revelation of Jesus Christ.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>Sebab itu siapkanlah akal budimu, waspadalah dan letakkanlah pengharapanmu seluruhnya atas kasih karunia yang dianugerahkan kepadamu pada waktu penyataan Yesus Kristus.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="14" />
      <text>Be as children of obedience, not conforming yourselves according to your former lusts as in your ignorance.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>Hiduplah sebagai anak-anak yang taat dan jangan turuti hawa nafsu yang menguasai kamu pada waktu kebodohanmu,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="15" />
      <text>But just as he who called you is holy, you yourselves also be holy in all of your behavior; </text>
      <verse num="16" />
      <text>because it is written,</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>tetapi hendaklah kamu menjadi kudus di dalam seluruh hidupmu sama seperti Dia yang kudus, yang telah memanggil kamu, </text>
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>sebab ada tertulis:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="scripture" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="scripture">
      <text>“You shall be holy; for I am holy.”</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <text>&lt;&lt;Kuduslah kamu, sebab Aku kudus.&gt;&gt;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="17" />
      <text>If you call on him as Father, who without respect of persons judges according to each man's work, pass the time of your living as foreigners here in reverent fear.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>Dan jika kamu menyebut-Nya Bapa, yaitu Dia yang tanpa memandang muka menghakimi semua orang menurut perbuatannya, maka hendaklah kamu hidup dalam ketakutan selama kamu menumpang di dunia ini.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="18" />
      <text>Know that you were redeemed, and not with corruptible things, with silver or gold, from the useless way of life handed down from your fathers.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>Sebab kamu tahu, bahwa kamu telah ditebus dari cara hidupmu yang sia-sia yang kamu warisi dari nenek moyangmu itu bukan dengan barang yang fana, bukan pula dengan perak atau emas,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="19" />
      <text>You were redeemed with precious blood, as of a faultless and pure lamb, the blood of Christ.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>melainkan dengan darah yang mahal, yaitu darah Kristus yang sama seperti darah anak domba yang tak bernoda dan tak bercacat.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="20" />
      <text>Christ was foreknown indeed before the foundation of the world, but was revealed at the end of times for your sake.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>Ia telah dipilih sebelum dunia dijadikan, tetapi karena kamu baru menyatakan diri-Nya pada zaman akhir.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="21" />
      <text>Through him you are believers in God, who raised him from the dead, and gave him glory; so that your faith and hope might be in God.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>Oleh Dialah kamu percaya kepada Allah, yang telah membangkitkan Dia dari antara orang mati dan yang telah memuliakan-Nya, sehingga imanmu dan pengharapanmu tertuju kepada Allah.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="22" />
      <text>Now that you have purified your souls in your obedience to the truth through the Spirit in sincere brotherly affection, love one another from the heart fervently.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>Karena kamu telah menyucikan dirimu oleh ketaatan kepada kebenaran, sehingga kamu dapat mengamalkan kasih persaudaraan yang tulus ikhlas, hendaklah kamu bersungguh-sungguh saling mengasihi dengan segenap hatimu.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="23" />
      <text>For you have been born again, not of corruptible seed, but of incorruptible, through the word of God, which lives and remains forever. </text>
      <verse num="24" />
      <text>For,</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>Karena kamu telah dilahirkan kembali bukan dari benih yang fana, tetapi dari benih yang tidak fana, oleh firman Allah, yang hidup dan yang kekal. </text>
    <verse num="24" />
    <text>Sebab:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="scripture" multiBlockQuote="Start" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="scripture" multiBlockQuote="Start">
      <text>“All flesh is like grass, and all of man's glory like the flower in the grass. The grass withers, and its flower falls;</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <text>&lt;&lt;Semua yang hidup adalah seperti rumput dan segala kemuliaannya seperti bunga rumput, rumput menjadi kering, dan bunga gugur,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="scripture" multiBlockQuote="Continuation" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="scripture" multiBlockQuote="Continuation">
      <verse num="25" />
      <text>but the Lord's word endures forever.”</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="25" />
    <text>tetapi firman Tuhan tetap untuk selama-lamanya.&gt;&gt;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <text>This is the word of Good News which was preached to you.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <text>Inilah firman yang disampaikan Injil kepada kamu.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" book="1PE" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="c" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="0">
      <text>1 PETER CHP 2</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <text>2</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="1" />
      <text>Put away therefore all wickedness, all deceit, hypocrisies, envies, and all evil speaking.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Karena itu buanglah segala kejahatan, segala tipu muslihat dan segala macam kemunafikan, kedengkian dan fitnah.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="2" />
      <text>Be like newborn babes, desiring always the pure spiritual milk, so that drinking it, you can grow and be saved.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>Dan jadilah sama seperti bayi yang baru lahir, yang selalu ingin akan air susu yang murni dan yang rohani, supaya olehnya kamu bertumbuh dan beroleh keselamatan,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="3" />
      <text>For as the Scriptures say: “You have discovered for yourself that the Lord is good.”</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>jika kamu benar-benar telah mengecap kebaikan Tuhan.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="4" />
      <text>Come to him as a living stone, rejected indeed by men, but chosen by God and precious to him.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>Dan datanglah kepada-Nya, batu yang hidup itu, yang memang dibuang oleh manusia, tetapi yang dipilih dan dihormat di hadirat Allah.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="5" />
      <text>You also, as living stones, are built up as a spiritual house, to be a holy priesthood, to offer up spiritual sacrifices, acceptable to God through Jesus Christ.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>Dan biarlah kamu juga dipergunakan sebagai batu hidup untuk pembangunan suatu rumah rohani, bagi suatu imamat kudus, untuk mempersembahkan persembahan rohani yang karena Yesus Kristus berkenan kepada Allah.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="6" />
      <text>Because it is contained in Scripture,</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>Sebab ada tertulis dalam Kitab Suci:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="scripture" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="scripture">
      <text>“Behold, I lay in Zion a chief cornerstone, chosen, and precious: He who believes in him will not be disappointed.”</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <text>&lt;&lt;Sesungguhnya, Aku meletakkan di Sion sebuah batu yang terpilih, sebuah batu penjuru yang mahal, dan siapa yang percaya kepada-Nya, tidak akan dipermalukan.&gt;&gt;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="7" />
      <text>For you who believe therefore is the honor, but for those who are disobedient,</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>Karena itu bagi kamu, yang percaya, ia mahal, tetapi bagi mereka yang tidak percaya:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="scripture" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="scripture">
      <text>“The stone which the builders rejected, has become the chief cornerstone,”</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <text>&lt;&lt;Batu yang telah dibuang oleh tukang-tukang bangunan, telah menjadi batu penjuru, juga telah menjadi batu sentuhan dan suatu batu sandungan.&gt;&gt;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="8" />
      <text>and,</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>Mereka tersandung padanya,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="scripture" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="scripture">
      <text>“a stone of stumbling, and a rock of offense.”</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <text>karena mereka tidak taat kepada Firman Allah;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <text>For they stumble at the word, being disobedient, to which also they were appointed.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <text>dan untuk itu mereka juga telah disediakan.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="9" />
      <text>But you are a chosen race, a royal priesthood, a holy nation. A people for God's own possession, that you may proclaim the excellence of him who called you out of darkness into his marvelous light.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>Tetapi kamulah bangsa yang terpilih, imamat yang rajani, bangsa yang kudus, umat kepunyaan Allah sendiri, supaya kamu memberitakan perbuatan-perbuatan yang besar dari Dia, yang telah memanggil kamu keluar dari kegelapan kepada terang-Nya yang ajaib:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="10" />
      <text>In times past, you were no people, but now you are God's people. At one time you did not have God's mercy, but now you have obtained his mercy.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>kamu, yang dahulu bukan umat Allah, tetapi yang sekarang telah menjadi umat-Nya, yang dahulu tidak dikasihani tetapi yang sekarang telah beroleh belas kasihan.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="11" />
      <text>Beloved, I beg you as foreigners and pilgrims, to abstain from fleshly lusts, which war against the soul.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>Saudara-saudaraku yang kekasih, aku menasihati kamu, supaya sebagai pendatang dan perantau, kamu menjauhkan diri dari keinginan-keinginan daging yang berjuang melawan jiwa.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="12" />
      <text>Have such good behavior among the nations, that when they speak against you as evildoers, they may, by your good works which they see, glorify God in the day of visitation.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>Milikilah cara hidup yang baik di tengah-tengah bangsa-bangsa bukan Yahudi, supaya apabila mereka memfitnah kamu sebagai orang durjana, mereka dapat melihatnya dari perbuatan-perbuatanmu yang baik dan memuliakan Allah pada hari Ia melawat mereka.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="13" />
      <text>Therefore subject yourselves to every ordinance of man for the Lord's sake: whether to the king, as supreme;</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>Tunduklah, karena Allah, kepada semua lembaga manusia, baik kepada raja sebagai pemegang kekuasaan yang tertinggi,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="14" />
      <text>or to governors, as sent by him for vengeance on evildoers and for praise to those who do well.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>maupun kepada wali-wali yang diutusnya untuk menghukum orang-orang yang berbuat jahat dan menghormati orang-orang yang berbuat baik.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="15" />
      <text>For this is the will of God, that by well-doing you should put to silence the ignorance of foolish men:</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>Sebab inilah kehendak Allah, yaitu supaya dengan berbuat baik kamu membungkamkan kepicikan orang-orang yang bodoh.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="16" />
      <text>Live as free men, but do not use your freedom for a cloak of wickedness. Live as bondservants of God.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>Hiduplah sebagai orang merdeka dan bukan seperti mereka yang menyalahgunakan kemerdekaan itu untuk menyelubungi kejahatan-kejahatan mereka, tetapi hiduplah sebagai hamba Allah.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="17" />
      <text>Honor all men. Love the brotherhood. Fear God. Honor the king.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>Hormatilah semua orang, kasihilah saudara-saudaramu, takutlah akan Allah, hormatilah raja!</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="18" />
      <text>Servants, be in subjection to your masters with all fear; not only to the good and gentle, but also to the wicked.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>Hai kamu, hamba-hamba, tunduklah dengan penuh ketakutan kepada tuanmu, bukan saja kepada yang baik dan peramah, tetapi juga kepada yang bengis.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="19" />
      <text>For it is commendable if someone endures pain, suffering unjustly, because of conscience toward God.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>Sebab adalah kasih karunia, jika seorang karena sadar akan kehendak Allah menanggung penderitaan yang tidak harus ia tanggung.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="20" />
      <text>For what glory is it if, when you sin, you patiently endure beating? But if, when you do well, you patiently endure suffering, this is commendable with God.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>Sebab dapatkah disebut pujian, jika kamu menderita pukulan karena kamu berbuat dosa? Tetapi jika kamu berbuat baik dan karena itu kamu harus menderita, maka itu adalah kasih karunia pada Allah.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="21" />
      <text>For to this you were called, because Christ also suffered for us, leaving you an example, that you should follow his steps,</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>Sebab untuk itulah kamu dipanggil, karena Kristuspun telah menderita untuk kamu dan telah meninggalkan teladan bagimu, supaya kamu mengikuti jejak-Nya.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="22" />
      <text>who did not sin, “neither was deceit found in his mouth.”</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>&lt;&lt;Ia tidak berbuat dosa, dan tipu tidak ada dalam mulut-Nya.&gt;&gt;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="23" />
      <text>When he was cursed, he didn't curse back. When he suffered, he didn't threaten, but committed himself to him who judges righteously.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>Ketika Ia dicaci maki, Ia tidak membalas dengan mencaci maki; ketika Ia menderita, Ia tidak mengancam, tetapi Ia menyerahkannya kepada Dia, yang menghakimi dengan adil.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="24" />
      <text>He himself bore our sins in his body on the tree, that we, having died to sins, might live to righteousness; by whose stripes you were healed.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="24" />
    <text>Ia sendiri telah memikul dosa kita di dalam tubuh-Nya di kayu salib, supaya kita, yang telah mati terhadap dosa, hidup untuk kebenaran. Oleh bilur-bilur-Nya kamu telah sembuh.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="25" />
      <text>For you were going astray like sheep; but now have returned to the Shepherd and Overseer of your souls.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="25" />
    <text>Sebab dahulu kamu sesat seperti domba, tetapi sekarang kamu telah kembali kepada gembala dan pemelihara jiwamu.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" book="1PE" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="c" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="0">
      <text>1 PETER CHP 3</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <text>3</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="1" />
      <text>In the same way, wives, be in subjection to your own husbands; so that, even if any don't obey the Word, they may be won by the behavior of their wives without a word;</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Demikian juga kamu, hai isteri-isteri, tunduklah kepada suamimu, supaya jika ada di antara mereka yang tidak taat kepada Firman, mereka juga tanpa perkataan dimenangkan oleh kelakuan isterinya,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="2" />
      <text>seeing your pure behavior in fear.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>jika mereka melihat, bagaimana murni dan salehnya hidup isteri mereka itu.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="3" />
      <text>Let your beauty be not just the outward adorning of braiding the hair, and of wearing jewels of gold, or of putting on fine clothing;</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>Perhiasanmu janganlah secara lahiriah, yaitu dengan mengepang-ngepang rambut, memakai perhiasan emas atau dengan mengenakan pakaian yang indah-indah,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="4" />
      <text>but in the hidden person of the heart, in the incorruptible adornment of a gentle and quiet spirit, which is very precious in the sight of God.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>tetapi perhiasanmu ialah manusia batiniah yang tersembunyi dengan perhiasan yang tidak binasa yang berasal dari roh yang lemah lembut dan tenteram, yang sangat berharga di mata Allah.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="5" />
      <text>For this is how the holy women before, who hoped in God also adorned themselves, being in subjection to their own husbands.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>Sebab demikianlah caranya perempuan-perempuan kudus dahulu berdandan, yaitu perempuan-perempuan yang menaruh pengharapannya kepada Allah; mereka tunduk kepada suaminya,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="6" />
      <text>Sarah obeyed Abraham, calling him lord. You are her children if you do well, and are not put in fear by any terror.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>sama seperti Sara taat kepada Abraham dan menamai dia tuannya. Dan kamu adalah anak-anaknya, jika kamu berbuat baik dan tidak takut akan ancaman.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="7" />
      <text>You husbands, in the same way, live with your wives according to knowledge. Give honor to the woman, as to the weaker vessel, as being also joint heirs of the grace of life; that your prayers may not be hindered.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>Demikian juga kamu, hai suami-suami, hiduplah bijaksana dengan isterimu, sebagai kaum yang lebih lemah! Hormatilah mereka sebagai teman pewaris dari kasih karunia, yaitu kehidupan, supaya doamu jangan terhalang.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="8" />
      <text>Finally, be all like-minded, compassionate, loving as brothers, tenderhearted, courteous.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>Dan akhirnya, hendaklah kamu semua seia sekata, seperasaan, mengasihi saudara-saudara, penyayang dan rendah hati,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="9" />
      <text>Do not render evil for evil, or insult for insult; but instead blessing. Know that to this were you called, that you may inherit a blessing. </text>
      <verse num="10" />
      <text>For,</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>dan janganlah membalas kejahatan dengan kejahatan, atau caci maki dengan caci maki, tetapi sebaliknya, hendaklah kamu memberkati, karena untuk itulah kamu dipanggil, yaitu untuk memperoleh berkat. </text>
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>Sebab:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="scripture" multiBlockQuote="Start" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="scripture" multiBlockQuote="Start">
      <text>“He who would love life, and see good days, let him keep his tongue from evil, and his lips from speaking deceit.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <text>&lt;&lt;Siapa yang mau mencintai hidup dan mau melihat hari-hari baik, ia harus menjaga lidahnya terhadap yang jahat dan bibirnya terhadap ucapan-ucapan yang menipu.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="scripture" multiBlockQuote="Continuation" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="scripture" multiBlockQuote="Continuation">
      <verse num="11" />
      <text>Let him turn away from evil, and do good. Let him seek peace, and pursue it.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>Ia harus menjauhi yang jahat dan melakukan yang baik, ia harus mencari perdamaian dan berusaha mendapatkannya.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="scripture" multiBlockQuote="Continuation" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="scripture" multiBlockQuote="Continuation">
      <verse num="12" />
      <text>For the eyes of the Lord are on the righteous, and his ears open to their prayer; but the face of the Lord is against those who do evil.”</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>Sebab mata Tuhan tertuju kepada orang-orang benar, dan telinga-Nya kepada permohonan mereka yang minta tolong, tetapi wajah Tuhan menentang orang-orang yang berbuat jahat.&gt;&gt;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="13" />
      <text>Now who is he who will harm you, if you become imitators of that which is good?</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>Dan siapakah yang akan berbuat jahat terhadap kamu, jika kamu rajin berbuat baik?</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="14" />
      <text>But even if you should suffer for righteousness’ sake, you are blessed. “Don't fear what they fear, neither be troubled.”</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>Tetapi sekalipun kamu harus menderita juga karena kebenaran, kamu akan berbahagia. &lt;&lt;Sebab itu janganlah kamu takuti apa yang mereka takuti dan janganlah gentar.&gt;&gt;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="15" />
      <text>But sanctify the Lord God in your hearts. Always be ready to give an answer to everyone who asks you a reason concerning the hope that is in you, with humility and fear.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>Tetapi kuduskanlah Kristus di dalam hatimu sebagai Tuhan! Dan siap sedialah pada segala waktu untuk memberi pertanggungan jawab kepada tiap-tiap orang yang meminta pertanggungan jawab dari kamu tentang pengharapan yang ada padamu, tetapi haruslah dengan lemah lembut dan hormat,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="16" />
      <text>Have a good conscience; that, while you are spoken against as evildoers, they may be disappointed who curse your good way of life in Christ.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>dan dengan hati nurani yang murni, supaya mereka, yang memfitnah kamu karena hidupmu yang saleh dalam Kristus, menjadi malu karena fitnahan mereka itu.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="17" />
      <text>For it is better, if it is God's will, that you suffer for doing well than for doing evil.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>Sebab lebih baik menderita karena berbuat baik, jika hal itu dikehendaki Allah, dari pada menderita karena berbuat jahat.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="18" />
      <text>Because Christ also suffered for sins once, the righteous for the unrighteous, that he might bring you to God; being put to death in the flesh, but made alive in the spirit.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>Sebab juga Kristus telah mati sekali untuk segala dosa kita, Ia yang benar untuk orang-orang yang tidak benar, supaya Ia membawa kita kepada Allah; Ia, yang telah dibunuh dalam keadaan-Nya sebagai manusia, tetapi yang telah dibangkitkan menurut Roh,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="19" />
      <text>He also went and preached to the spirits in prison.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>dan di dalam Roh itu juga Ia pergi memberitakan Injil kepada roh-roh yang di dalam penjara,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="20" />
      <text>Those were the spirits of the people who were disobedient in the days of Noah. God waited patiently while the ship was being built. But only eight people were saved when the earth was flooded with water.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>yaitu kepada roh-roh mereka yang dahulu pada waktu Nuh tidak taat kepada Allah, ketika Allah tetap menanti dengan sabar waktu Nuh sedang mempersiapkan bahteranya, di mana hanya sedikit, yaitu delapan orang, yang diselamatkan oleh air bah itu.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="21" />
      <text>This water is a symbol of baptism, which now saves you-- not the putting away of the filth of the flesh, but the answer of a good conscience toward God, through the resurrection of Jesus Christ.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>Juga kamu sekarang diselamatkan oleh kiasannya, yaitu baptisan— maksudnya bukan untuk membersihkan kenajisan jasmani, melainkan untuk memohonkan hati nurani yang baik kepada Allah—oleh kebangkitan Yesus Kristus,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="22" />
      <text>He has gone into heaven and is at the right hand of God. Having gone into heaven, angels, authorities, and powers have been made subject to him.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>yang duduk di sebelah kanan Allah, setelah Ia naik ke sorga sesudah segala malaikat, kuasa dan kekuatan ditaklukkan kepada-Nya.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" book="1PE" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="c" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="0">
      <text>1 PETER CHP 4</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <text>4</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="1" />
      <text>Forasmuch then as Christ suffered for us in the flesh, arm yourselves also with the same mind; for suffering in the flesh puts an end to sin.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Jadi, karena Kristus telah menderita penderitaan badani, kamupun harus juga mempersenjatai dirimu dengan pikiran yang demikian, —karena barangsiapa telah menderita penderitaan badani, ia telah berhenti berbuat dosa—,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="2" />
      <text>You should no longer live the rest of your time in the flesh for the lusts of men, but for the will of God.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>supaya waktu yang sisa jangan kamu pergunakan menurut keinginan manusia, tetapi menurut kehendak Allah.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="3" />
      <text>For we have spent enough of our past time doing the desire of the Gentiles. Having walked in lewdness, lusts, drunken binges, orgies, carousings, and abominable idolatries.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>Sebab telah cukup banyak waktu kamu pergunakan untuk melakukan kehendak orang-orang yang tidak mengenal Allah. Kamu telah hidup dalam rupa-rupa hawa nafsu, keinginan, kemabukan, pesta pora, perjamuan minum dan penyembahan berhala yang terlarang.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="4" />
      <text>They think it is strange that you don't run with them into the same excess of riot, blaspheming.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>Sebab itu mereka heran, bahwa kamu tidak turut mencemplungkan diri bersama-sama mereka di dalam kubangan ketidaksenonohan yang sama, dan mereka memfitnah kamu.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="5" />
      <text>They will give account to him who is ready to judge the living and the dead.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>Tetapi mereka harus memberi pertanggungan jawab kepada Dia, yang telah siap sedia menghakimi orang yang hidup dan yang mati.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="6" />
      <text>For to this end the Good News was preached even to the dead, that they might be judged indeed as men in the flesh, but live as to God in the spirit.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>Itulah sebabnya maka Injil telah diberitakan juga kepada orang-orang mati, supaya mereka, sama seperti semua manusia, dihakimi secara badani; tetapi oleh roh dapat hidup menurut kehendak Allah.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="7" />
      <text>But the end of all things is near. Therefore be of sound mind, self-controlled, and sober in prayer.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>Kesudahan segala sesuatu sudah dekat. Karena itu kuasailah dirimu dan jadilah tenang, supaya kamu dapat berdoa.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="8" />
      <text>And above all things be earnest in your love among yourselves, for love covers a multitude of sins.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>Tetapi yang terutama: kasihilah sungguh-sungguh seorang akan yang lain, sebab kasih menutupi banyak sekali dosa.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="9" />
      <text>Be hospitable to one another without grumbling.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>Berilah tumpangan seorang akan yang lain dengan tidak bersungut-sungut.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="10" />
      <text>As each has received a gift, employ it in serving one another, as good managers of the grace of God in its various forms.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>Layanilah seorang akan yang lain, sesuai dengan karunia yang telah diperoleh tiap-tiap orang sebagai pengurus yang baik dari kasih karunia Allah.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="11" />
      <text>If anyone speaks, let it be as it were the very words of God. If anyone serves, let it be as of the strength which God supplies. That in all things God may be glorified through Jesus Christ, to whom belong the glory and the dominion forever and ever. Amen.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>Jika ada orang yang berbicara, baiklah ia berbicara sebagai orang yang menyampaikan firman Allah; jika ada orang yang melayani, baiklah ia melakukannya dengan kekuatan yang dianugerahkan Allah, supaya Allah dimuliakan dalam segala sesuatu karena Yesus Kristus. Ialah yang empunya kemuliaan dan kuasa sampai selama-lamanya! Amin.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="12" />
      <text>Beloved, don't be astonished at the fiery trial which has come upon you, to test you, as though a strange thing happened to you.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>Saudara-saudara yang kekasih, janganlah kamu heran akan nyala api siksaan yang datang kepadamu sebagai ujian, seolah-olah ada sesuatu yang luar biasa terjadi atas kamu.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="13" />
      <text>But because you are partakers of Christ's sufferings, rejoice; that at the revelation of his glory you also may rejoice with exceeding joy.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>Sebaliknya, bersukacitalah, sesuai dengan bagian yang kamu dapat dalam penderitaan Kristus, supaya kamu juga boleh bergembira dan bersukacita pada waktu Ia menyatakan kemuliaan-Nya.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="14" />
      <text>If you are insulted for the name of Christ, you are blessed; because the Spirit of glory and of God rests on you. On their part he is blasphemed, but on your part he is glorified.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>Berbahagialah kamu, jika kamu dinista karena nama Kristus, sebab Roh kemuliaan, yaitu Roh Allah ada padamu.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="15" />
      <text>For let none of you suffer as a murderer, or a thief, or an evil doer, or a meddler in other men's matters.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>Janganlah ada di antara kamu yang harus menderita sebagai pembunuh atau pencuri atau penjahat, atau pengacau.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="16" />
      <text>But if one of you suffers for being a Christian, let him not be ashamed; but let him glorify God in this matter.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>Tetapi, jika ia menderita sebagai orang Kristen, maka janganlah ia malu, melainkan hendaklah ia memuliakan Allah dalam nama Kristus itu.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="17" />
      <text>For the time has come for judgment to begin with the household of God. If it begins first with us, what will happen to those who don't obey the Good News of God?</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>Karena sekarang telah tiba saatnya penghakiman dimulai, dan pada rumah Allah sendiri yang harus pertama-tama dihakimi. Dan jika penghakiman itu dimulai pada kita, bagaimanakah kesudahannya dengan mereka yang tidak percaya pada Injil Allah?</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-1PE" userConfirmed="true">
      <verse num="18" />
      <text>“If it is hard for the righteous to be saved, what will happen to the ungodly and the sinner?”</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>&lt;&lt;Dan jika orang benar hampir-hampir tidak diselamatkan, apakah yang akan terjadi dengan orang fasik dan orang berdosa?&gt;&gt;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="19" />
      <text>Therefore let them also who suffer according to the will of God in doing good entrust their souls to him, as to a faithful Creator.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>Karena itu baiklah juga mereka yang harus menderita karena kehendak Allah, menyerahkan jiwanya, dengan selalu berbuat baik, kepada Pencipta yang setia.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" book="1PE" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="c" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="0">
      <text>1 PETER CHP 5</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <text>5</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="1" />
      <text>I exhort the elders among you, as a fellow elder. As a witness of the sufferings of Christ, and as one who will also share in the glory that will be revealed.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Aku menasihatkan para penatua di antara kamu, aku sebagai teman penatua dan saksi penderitaan Kristus, yang juga akan mendapat bagian dalam kemuliaan yang akan dinyatakan kelak.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="2" />
      <text>Shepherd the flock of God which is among you. Exercise oversight, not under compulsion, but voluntarily, not for dishonest gain, but willingly.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>Gembalakanlah kawanan domba Allah yang ada padamu, jangan dengan paksa, tetapi dengan sukarela sesuai dengan kehendak Allah, dan jangan karena mau mencari keuntungan, tetapi dengan pengabdian diri.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="3" />
      <text>Do not lord it over those entrusted to you, but make yourselves examples to the flock.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>Janganlah kamu berbuat seolah-olah kamu mau memerintah atas mereka yang dipercayakan kepadamu, tetapi hendaklah kamu menjadi teladan bagi kawanan domba itu.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="4" />
      <text>When the chief Shepherd is revealed, you will receive the crown of glory that doesn't fade away.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>Maka kamu, apabila Gembala Agung datang, kamu akan menerima mahkota kemuliaan yang tidak dapat layu.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="5" />
      <text>Likewise, you younger ones, be subject to the elder. Yes, all of you clothe yourselves with humility, to subject yourselves to one another; for</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>Demikian jugalah kamu, hai orang-orang muda, tunduklah kepada orang-orang yang tua. Dan kamu semua, rendahkanlah dirimu seorang terhadap yang lain, sebab:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="scripture" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="scripture">
      <text>“God resists the proud, but gives grace to the humble.”</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <text>&lt;&lt;Allah menentang orang yang congkak, tetapi mengasihani orang yang rendah hati.&gt;&gt;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="6" />
      <text>Humble yourselves therefore under the mighty hand of God, that he may exalt you in due time.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>Karena itu rendahkanlah dirimu di bawah tangan Tuhan yang kuat, supaya kamu ditinggikan-Nya pada waktunya.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="7" />
      <text>Cast all your worries on him, because he cares for you.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>Serahkanlah segala kekuatiranmu kepada-Nya, sebab Ia yang memelihara kamu.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="8" />
      <text>Be sober and self-controlled. Be watchful. Your adversary, the devil, walks around like a roaring lion, seeking whom he may devour.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>Sadarlah dan berjaga-jagalah! Lawanmu, si Iblis, berjalan keliling sama seperti singa yang mengaum-aum dan mencari orang yang dapat ditelannya.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="9" />
      <text>Withstand him steadfast in your faith, knowing that your brothers who are in the world are undergoing the same sufferings.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>Lawanlah dia dengan iman yang teguh, sebab kamu tahu, bahwa semua saudaramu di seluruh dunia menanggung penderitaan yang sama.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="10" />
      <text>But may the God of all grace, who called you to his eternal glory by Christ Jesus, after you have suffered a little while, perfect, establish, strengthen, and settle you.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>Dan Allah, sumber segala kasih karunia, yang telah memanggil kamu dalam Kristus kepada kemuliaan-Nya yang kekal, akan melengkapi, meneguhkan, menguatkan dan mengokohkan kamu, sesudah kamu menderita seketika lamanya.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="11" />
      <text>To him be the glory and the power forever and ever. Amen.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>Ialah yang empunya kuasa sampai selama-lamanya! Amin.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="12" />
      <text>Through Silvanus, our faithful brother, as I consider him, I have written to you briefly, exhorting, and testifying that this is the true grace of God in which you stand.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>Dengan perantaraan Silwanus, yang kuanggap sebagai seorang saudara yang dapat dipercayai, aku menulis dengan singkat kepada kamu untuk menasihati dan meyakinkan kamu, bahwa ini adalah kasih karunia yang benar-benar dari Allah. Berdirilah dengan teguh di dalamnya!</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="13" />
      <text>She who is in Babylon, chosen together with you, greets you; and so does Mark, my son.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>Salam kepada kamu sekalian dari kawanmu yang terpilih yang di Babilon, dan juga dari Markus, anakku.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="14" />
      <text>Greet one another with a kiss of love. Peace be to you all who are in Christ Jesus. Amen.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>Berilah salam seorang kepada yang lain dengan cium yang kudus. Damai sejahtera menyertai kamu sekalian yang berada dalam Kristus. Amin.</text>
  </block>
  <UnappliedSplits />
</book>