<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<book id="JUD" singlevoice="false" pageheader="JUDE">
  <block style="mt" chapter="0" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-JUD" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="mt" chapter="0" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-JUD">
      <text>JUDE</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <text>JUDE</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" book="JUD" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-JUD" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="c" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="0">
      <text>JUDE 1</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <text>1</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-JUD" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-JUD">
      <verse num="1" />
      <text>Jude, a servant of Jesus Christ, and brother of James, to those who are called, sanctified by God the Father, and kept for Jesus Christ:</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Dari Yudas, hamba Yesus Kristus dan saudara Yakobus, kepada mereka, yang terpanggil, yang dikasihi dalam Allah Bapa, dan yang dipelihara untuk Yesus Kristus.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-JUD" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-JUD">
      <verse num="2" />
      <text>Mercy to you and peace and love be multiplied.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>Rahmat, damai sejahtera dan kasih kiranya melimpahi kamu.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-JUD" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-JUD">
      <verse num="3" />
      <text>Beloved, while I was very eager to write to you about our common salvation, I was constrained to write to you exhorting you to contend earnestly for the faith which was once for all delivered to the saints.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>Saudara-saudaraku yang kekasih, sementara aku bersungguh-sungguh berusaha menulis kepada kamu tentang keselamatan kita bersama, aku merasa terdorong untuk menulis ini kepada kamu dan menasihati kamu, supaya kamu tetap berjuang untuk mempertahankan iman yang telah disampaikan kepada orang-orang kudus.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-JUD" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-JUD">
      <verse num="4" />
      <text>For there are certain men who crept in secretly, even those who were long ago written about for this condemnation: ungodly men, turning the grace of our God into indecency, and denying our only Master, God, and Lord, Jesus Christ.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>Sebab ternyata ada orang tertentu yang telah masuk menyelusup di tengah-tengah kamu, yaitu orang-orang yang telah lama ditentukan untuk dihukum. Mereka adalah orang-orang yang fasik, yang menyalahgunakan kasih karunia Allah kita untuk melampiaskan hawa nafsu mereka, dan yang menyangkal satu-satunya Penguasa dan Tuhan kita, Yesus Kristus.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-JUD" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-JUD">
      <verse num="5" />
      <text>Now I desire to remind you, though you already know this, that the Lord, having saved a people out of the land of Egypt, afterward destroyed those who didn’t believe.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>Tetapi, sekalipun kamu telah mengetahui semuanya itu dan tidak meragukannya lagi, aku ingin mengingatkan kamu bahwa memang Tuhan menyelamatkan umat-Nya dari tanah Mesir, namun sekali lagi membinasakan mereka yang tidak percaya.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-JUD" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-JUD">
      <verse num="6" />
      <text>Angels who didn’t keep their first domain, but deserted their own dwelling place, he has kept in everlasting bonds under darkness for the judgment of the great day.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>Dan bahwa Ia menahan malaikat-malaikat yang tidak taat pada batas-batas kekuasaan mereka, tetapi yang meninggalkan tempat kediaman mereka, dengan belenggu abadi di dalam dunia kekelaman sampai penghakiman pada hari besar,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-JUD" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-JUD">
      <verse num="7" />
      <text>Even as Sodom and Gomorrah, and the cities around them, having, in the same way as these, given themselves over to sexual immorality and gone after strange flesh, are set forth as an example, suffering the punishment of eternal fire.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>sama seperti Sodom dan Gomora dan kota-kota sekitarnya, yang dengan cara yang sama melakukan percabulan dan mengejar kepuasan-kepuasan yang tak wajar, telah menanggung siksaan api kekal sebagai peringatan kepada semua orang.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-JUD" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-JUD">
      <verse num="8" />
      <text>Yet in the same way, these also in their dreaming defile the flesh, despise authority, and slander celestial beings.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>Namun demikian orang-orang yang bermimpi-mimpian ini juga mencemarkan tubuh mereka dan menghina kekuasaan Allah serta menghujat semua yang mulia di sorga.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-JUD" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-JUD">
      <verse num="9" />
      <text>But Michael, the archangel, when contending with the devil and arguing about the body of Moses, dared not bring against him an abusive condemnation, but said, </text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>Tetapi penghulu malaikat, Mikhael, ketika dalam suatu perselisihan bertengkar dengan Iblis mengenai mayat Musa, tidak berani menghakimi Iblis itu dengan kata-kata hujatan, tetapi berkata:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="Michael, archangel" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="Michael, archangel">
      <text>“May the Lord rebuke you!”</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <text>&lt;&lt;Kiranya Tuhan menghardik engkau!&gt;&gt;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-JUD" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-JUD">
      <verse num="10" />
      <text>But these speak evil of whatever things they don’t know. What they understand naturally, like the creatures without reason, they are destroyed in these things.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>Akan tetapi mereka menghujat segala sesuatu yang tidak mereka ketahui dan justru apa yang mereka ketahui dengan nalurinya seperti binatang yang tidak berakal, itulah yang mengakibatkan kebinasaan mereka.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-JUD" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-JUD">
      <verse num="11" />
      <text>Woe to them! For they went in the way of Cain, and ran riotously in the error of Balaam for hire, and perished in Korah’s rebellion.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>Celakalah mereka, karena mereka mengikuti jalan yang ditempuh Kain dan karena mereka, oleh sebab upah, menceburkan diri ke dalam kesesatan Bileam, dan mereka binasa karena kedurhakaan seperti Korah.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-JUD" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-JUD">
      <verse num="12" />
      <text>These men are hidden rocky reefs in your love feasts when they feast with you, shepherds who without fear feed themselves; clouds without water, carried along by winds. They are like autumn leaves without fruit, twice dead, plucked up by the roots.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>Mereka inilah noda dalam perjamuan kasihmu, di mana mereka tidak malu-malu melahap dan hanya mementingkan dirinya sendiri; mereka bagaikan awan yang tak berair, yang berlalu ditiup angin; mereka bagaikan pohon-pohon yang dalam musim gugur tidak menghasilkan buah, pohon-pohon yang terbantun dengan akar-akarnya dan yang mati sama sekali.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-JUD" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-JUD">
      <verse num="13" />
      <text>They are like wild waves of the sea, foaming out their own shame; wandering stars, for whom the blackness of darkness has been reserved forever.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>Mereka bagaikan ombak laut yang ganas, yang membuihkan keaiban mereka sendiri; mereka bagaikan bintang-bintang yang baginya telah tersedia tempat di dunia kekelaman untuk selama-lamanya.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-JUD" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-JUD">
      <verse num="14" />
      <text>About these also Enoch, the seventh from Adam, prophesied, saying,</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>Juga tentang mereka Henokh, keturunan ketujuh dari Adam, telah bernubuat, katanya:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="Enoch" multiBlockQuote="Start" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="Enoch" multiBlockQuote="Start">
      <text>“Behold, the Lord came with ten thousands of his holy ones,</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <text>&lt;&lt;Sesungguhnya Tuhan datang dengan beribu-ribu orang kudus-Nya,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="Enoch" multiBlockQuote="Continuation" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="Enoch" multiBlockQuote="Continuation">
      <verse num="15" />
      <text>to execute judgment on all, and to convict all the ungodly of all their works of ungodliness which they have done in an ungodly way, and of all the hard things which ungodly sinners have spoken against him.”</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>hendak menghakimi semua orang dan menjatuhkan hukuman atas orang-orang fasik karena semua perbuatan fasik, yang mereka lakukan dan karena semua kata-kata nista, yang diucapkan orang-orang berdosa yang fasik itu terhadap Tuhan.&gt;&gt;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-JUD" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-JUD">
      <verse num="16" />
      <text>These are murmurers and complainers, walking after their lusts (and their mouth speaks proud things), showing respect of persons to gain advantage.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>Mereka itu orang-orang yang menggerutu dan mengeluh tentang nasibnya, hidup menuruti hawa nafsunya, tetapi mulut mereka mengeluarkan perkataan-perkataan yang bukan-bukan dan mereka menjilat orang untuk mendapat keuntungan.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-JUD" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-JUD">
      <verse num="17" />
      <text>But you, beloved, remember the words which have been spoken before by the apostles of our Lord Jesus Christ.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>Tetapi kamu, saudara-saudaraku yang kekasih, ingatlah akan apa yang dahulu telah dikatakan kepada kamu oleh rasul-rasul Tuhan kita, Yesus Kristus.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-JUD" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-JUD">
      <verse num="18" />
      <text>They said to you that “In the last time there will be mockers, walking after their own ungodly lusts.”</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>Sebab mereka telah mengatakan kepada kamu: &lt;&lt;Menjelang akhir zaman akan tampil pengejek-pengejek yang akan hidup menuruti hawa nafsu kefasikan mereka.&gt;&gt;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-JUD" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-JUD">
      <verse num="19" />
      <text>These are they who cause divisions, and are sensual, not having the Spirit.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>Mereka adalah pemecah belah yang dikuasai hanya oleh keinginan-keinginan dunia ini dan yang hidup tanpa Roh Kudus.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-JUD" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-JUD">
      <verse num="20" />
      <text>But you, beloved, keep building up yourselves on your most holy faith, praying in the Holy Spirit.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>Akan tetapi kamu, saudara-saudaraku yang kekasih, bangunlah dirimu sendiri di atas dasar imanmu yang paling suci dan berdoalah dalam Roh Kudus.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-JUD" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-JUD">
      <verse num="21" />
      <text>Keep yourselves in the love of God, looking for the mercy of our Lord Jesus Christ to eternal life.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>Peliharalah dirimu demikian dalam kasih Allah sambil menantikan rahmat Tuhan kita, Yesus Kristus, untuk hidup yang kekal.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-JUD" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-JUD">
      <verse num="22" />
      <text>Be merciful to those who doubt.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>Tunjukkanlah belas kasihan kepada mereka yang ragu-ragu,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="narrator-JUD" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="narrator-JUD">
      <verse num="23" />
      <text>Snatch others from the fire and save them. To others show mercy mixed with fear, hating even the clothing stained by the flesh.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>selamatkanlah mereka dengan jalan merampas mereka dari api. Tetapi tunjukkanlah belas kasihan yang disertai ketakutan kepada orang-orang lain juga, dan bencilah pakaian mereka yang dicemarkan oleh keinginan-keinginan dosa.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="narrator-JUD" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="narrator-JUD">
      <verse num="24" />
      <text>Now to him who is able to keep them from stumbling, and to present you faultless before the presence of his glory in great joy --</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="24" />
    <text>Bagi Dia, yang berkuasa menjaga supaya jangan kamu tersandung dan yang membawa kamu dengan tak bernoda dan penuh kegembiraan di hadapan kemuliaan-Nya,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="narrator-JUD" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="narrator-JUD">
      <verse num="25" />
      <text>to God our Savior, who alone is wise, be glory and majesty, dominion and power, both now and forever. Amen.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="25" />
    <text>Allah yang esa, Juruselamat kita oleh Yesus Kristus, Tuhan kita, bagi Dia adalah kemuliaan, kebesaran, kekuatan dan kuasa sebelum segala abad dan sekarang dan sampai selama-lamanya. Amin.</text>
  </block>
  <UnappliedSplits />
</book>