<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<book id="1PE" singlevoice="false" pageheader="1 PEDRO">
  <block style="mt" chapter="0" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="mt" chapter="0" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1PE">
      <text>1 PETER</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <text>PRIMEIRA CARTA DE PEDRO</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" book="1PE" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="c" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="0">
      <text>1 PETER CHP 1</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <text>1</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="1" />
      <text>Peter, an apostle of Jesus Christ, to the chosen ones who are living as foreigners in the Dispersion in Pontus, Galatia, Cappadocia, Asia, and Bithynia,</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Eu, Pedro, * apóstolo de Jesus Cristo, escrevo esta carta ao povo de Deus que vive espalhado nas * províncias do Ponto, Galácia, Capadócia, Ásia e Bitínia a.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="2" />
      <text>according to the foreknowledge of God the Father, in sanctification of the Spirit, that you may obey Jesus Christ and be sprinkled with his blood: Grace to you and peace be multiplied.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>Vocês foram escolhidos de acordo com o propósito de Deus, o Pai. E pelo Espírito de Deus vocês foram feitos um povo dedicado a ele a fim de obedecerem a Jesus Cristo e ficarem purificados pelo seu sangue. Que vocês tenham, mais e mais, a graça e a paz de Deus!</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="3" />
      <text>Blessed be the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ. Who according to his great mercy became our father again to a living hope through the resurrection of Jesus Christ from the dead,</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>Louvemos ao Deus e Pai do nosso Senhor Jesus Cristo! Por causa da sua grande misericórdia, ele nos deu uma nova vida pela ressurreição de Jesus Cristo. Por isso o nosso coração está cheio de uma esperança viva.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="4" />
      <text>to an incorruptible and undefiled inheritance that doesn't fade away, reserved in Heaven for you.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>Assim esperamos possuir as ricas bênçãos que Deus guarda para o seu povo. Ele as guarda no céu, onde elas não perdem o valor e não podem se estragar, nem ser destruídas.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="5" />
      <text>By the power of God you are being guarded through faith for a salvation ready to be revealed in the last time.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>Essas bênçãos são para vocês que, por meio da fé, são guardados pelo poder de Deus para a salvação que está pronta para ser revelada no fim dos tempos.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="6" />
      <text>This is why you greatly rejoice, though now for a little while, if need be, you have been put to grief in various trials.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>Alegrem-se por isso, se bem que agora é possível que vocês fiquem tristes por algum tempo, por causa dos muitos tipos de provações que vocês estão sofrendo.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="7" />
      <text>These trials have come so that the proof of your faith, which is more precious than gold that perishes even though it is tested by fire, may be found to result in praise, glory, and honor at the revelation of Jesus Christ.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>Essas provações são para mostrar que a fé que vocês têm é verdadeira. Pois até o ouro, que pode ser destruído, é provado pelo fogo. Da mesma maneira, a fé que vocês têm, que vale muito mais do que o ouro, precisa ser provada para que continue firme. E assim vocês receberão aprovação, glória e honra, no dia b em que Jesus Cristo for revelado.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="8" />
      <text>Though you have not seen him, you love him; and even though you do not see him now, you believe in him and are filled with inexpressible and glorious joy.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>Vocês o amam, mesmo sem o terem visto, e crêem nele, mesmo que não o estejam vendo agora. Assim vocês se alegram com uma alegria tão grande e * gloriosa, que as palavras não podem descrever.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="9" />
      <text>For you are receiving the goal of your faith, the salvation of your souls.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>Vocês têm essa alegria porque estão recebendo a sua salvação, que é o resultado da fé que possuem.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="10" />
      <text>Concerning this salvation, the prophets sought and searched diligently. They prophesied of the grace that would come to you.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>Foi a respeito dessa salvação que os * profetas perguntaram e procuraram saber com muito cuidado. Eles profetizaram a respeito da salvação que Deus ia dar a vocês</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="11" />
      <text>They wondered who or what kind of time the Spirit of Christ, which was in them, pointed to, when he predicted the sufferings of Christ, and the glories that would follow them.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>e procuraram saber em que tempo e como essa salvação ia acontecer. O Espírito de Cristo, que estava neles, indicava esse tempo, ao predizer os sofrimentos que Cristo teria de suportar e a glória que viria depois.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="12" />
      <text>To them it was revealed, that not to themselves, but to you, they ministered these things, which now have been announced to you through those who preached the Good News to you by the Holy Spirit sent out from heaven; which things angels desire to look into.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>Quando os profetas falaram a respeito das verdades que vocês têm ouvido agora, Deus revelou a eles que o trabalho que faziam não era para o benefício deles, mas para o bem de vocês. Os mensageiros do evangelho, que falaram pelo poder do Espírito Santo, mandado do céu, anunciaram a vocês essas verdades. Essas são coisas que até os anjos gostariam de entender.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="13" />
      <text>Therefore prepare your minds for action! Be sober and set your hope fully on the grace that will be brought to you at the revelation of Jesus Christ.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>Portanto, estejam prontos para agir. Continuem alertas e ponham toda a sua esperança na bênção que será dada a vocês quando Jesus Cristo for revelado.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="14" />
      <text>Be as children of obedience, not conforming yourselves according to your former lusts as in your ignorance.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>Sejam obedientes a Deus e não deixem que a vida de vocês seja dominada por aqueles desejos que vocês tinham quando ainda eram ignorantes.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="15" />
      <text>But just as he who called you is holy, you yourselves also be holy in all of your behavior; </text>
      <verse num="16" />
      <text>because it is written,</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>Pelo contrário, sejam santos c em tudo o que fizerem, assim como Deus, que os * chamou, é santo d. </text>
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>Porque as * Escrituras Sagradas dizem:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="scripture" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="scripture">
      <text>“You shall be holy; for I am holy.”</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <text>“Sejam santos porque eu sou santo.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="17" />
      <text>If you call on him as Father, who without respect of persons judges according to each man's work, pass the time of your living as foreigners here in reverent fear.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>Quando oram a Deus, vocês o chamam de Pai, ele que julga com igualdade as pessoas, de acordo com o que cada uma tem feito. Portanto, durante o resto da vida de vocês aqui na terra tenham respeito a ele.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="18" />
      <text>Know that you were redeemed, and not with corruptible things, with silver or gold, from the useless way of life handed down from your fathers.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>Pois vocês sabem o preço que foi pago para livrá-los da vida inútil que herdaram dos seus antepassados. Esse preço não foi uma coisa que perde o seu valor como o ouro ou a prata.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="19" />
      <text>You were redeemed with precious blood, as of a faultless and pure lamb, the blood of Christ.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>Vocês foram libertados pelo precioso sangue de Cristo, que era como um cordeiro sem defeito nem mancha.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="20" />
      <text>Christ was foreknown indeed before the foundation of the world, but was revealed at the end of times for your sake.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>Ele foi escolhido por Deus antes da criação do mundo e foi revelado nestes últimos tempos em benefício de vocês.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="21" />
      <text>Through him you are believers in God, who raised him from the dead, and gave him glory; so that your faith and hope might be in God.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>Por meio dele vocês crêem em Deus, que o ressuscitou e lhe deu * glória. Assim a fé e a esperança que vocês têm estão firmadas em Deus.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="22" />
      <text>Now that you have purified your souls in your obedience to the truth through the Spirit in sincere brotherly affection, love one another from the heart fervently.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>Agora que vocês já se purificaram pela obediência à verdade e agora que já têm um amor sincero pelos irmãos na fé, amem uns aos outros com todas as forças e com um coração puro.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="23" />
      <text>For you have been born again, not of corruptible seed, but of incorruptible, through the word of God, which lives and remains forever. </text>
      <verse num="24" />
      <text>For,</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>Pois vocês, pela viva e eterna palavra de Deus, nasceram de novo como filhos de um Pai que é * imortal e não de pais mortais. </text>
    <verse num="24" />
    <text>Como dizem as Escrituras Sagradas:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="scripture" multiBlockQuote="Start" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="scripture" multiBlockQuote="Start">
      <text>“All flesh is like grass, and all of man's glory like the flower in the grass. The grass withers, and its flower falls;</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <text>“Todos os seres humanos são como a erva do campo, e a grandeza deles é como a flor da erva. A erva seca, e a flor cai,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="scripture" multiBlockQuote="Continuation" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="scripture" multiBlockQuote="Continuation">
      <verse num="25" />
      <text>but the Lord's word endures forever.”</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="25" />
    <text>mas a palavra do Senhor dura para sempre.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <text>This is the word of Good News which was preached to you.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <text>Esta é a palavra que o * evangelho trouxe para vocês.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" book="1PE" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="c" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="0">
      <text>1 PETER CHP 2</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <text>2</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="1" />
      <text>Put away therefore all wickedness, all deceit, hypocrisies, envies, and all evil speaking.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Portanto, abandonem tudo o que é mau, toda mentira, fingimento, inveja e críticas injustas.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="2" />
      <text>Be like newborn babes, desiring always the pure spiritual milk, so that drinking it, you can grow and be saved.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>Sejam como criancinhas recém-nascidas, desejando sempre o puro leite espiritual, para que, bebendo dele, vocês possam crescer e ser salvos.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="3" />
      <text>For as the Scriptures say: “You have discovered for yourself that the Lord is good.”</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>Pois, como dizem as * Escrituras Sagradas: “Vocês já descobriram por vocês mesmos que o Senhor é bom.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="4" />
      <text>Come to him as a living stone, rejected indeed by men, but chosen by God and precious to him.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>Cheguem perto dele, a pedra viva que os seres humanos rejeitaram como inútil, mas que Deus escolheu como de grande valor.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="5" />
      <text>You also, as living stones, are built up as a spiritual house, to be a holy priesthood, to offer up spiritual sacrifices, acceptable to God through Jesus Christ.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>Vocês, também, como pedras vivas, deixem que Deus os use na construção de um templo espiritual onde vocês servirão como sacerdotes dedicados a Deus. E isso para que, por meio de Jesus Cristo, ofereçam sacrifícios que Deus aceite.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="6" />
      <text>Because it is contained in Scripture,</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>Pois as Escrituras Sagradas dizem:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="scripture" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="scripture">
      <text>“Behold, I lay in Zion a chief cornerstone, chosen, and precious: He who believes in him will not be disappointed.”</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <text>“Eu escolhi uma pedra de muito valor, que agora ponho em * Sião e como a pedra principal do alicerce. Quem crer nela não ficará desiludido.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="7" />
      <text>For you who believe therefore is the honor, but for those who are disobedient,</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>Essa pedra é de muito valor para vocês, os que crêem. Mas, para os que não crêem,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="scripture" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="scripture">
      <text>“The stone which the builders rejected, has become the chief cornerstone,”</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <text>“A pedra que os construtores rejeitaram veio a ser a mais importante de todas.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="8" />
      <text>and,</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>E,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="scripture" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="scripture">
      <text>“a stone of stumbling, and a rock of offense.”</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <text>“Esta é a pedra em que as pessoas vão tropeçar, a rocha que vai fazê-las cair.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <text>For they stumble at the word, being disobedient, to which also they were appointed.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <text>Essas pessoas tropeçaram porque não creram na mensagem, de acordo com a vontade de Deus para elas.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="9" />
      <text>But you are a chosen race, a royal priesthood, a holy nation. A people for God's own possession, that you may proclaim the excellence of him who called you out of darkness into his marvelous light.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>Mas vocês são a raça escolhida, os sacerdotes do Rei, a nação completamente dedicada a Deus, o povo que pertence a ele. Vocês foram escolhidos para anunciar os atos poderosos de Deus, que os * chamou da escuridão para a sua maravilhosa luz.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="10" />
      <text>In times past, you were no people, but now you are God's people. At one time you did not have God's mercy, but now you have obtained his mercy.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>Antes, vocês não eram o povo de Deus, mas agora são o seu povo; antes, não conheciam a misericórdia de Deus, mas agora já receberam a sua misericórdia.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="11" />
      <text>Beloved, I beg you as foreigners and pilgrims, to abstain from fleshly lusts, which war against the soul.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>Queridos amigos, lembrem que vocês são estrangeiros de passagem por este mundo. Peço, portanto, que evitem as paixões carnais que estão sempre em guerra contra a alma.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="12" />
      <text>Have such good behavior among the nations, that when they speak against you as evildoers, they may, by your good works which they see, glorify God in the day of visitation.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>A conduta de vocês entre os pagãos deve ser boa, para que, quando eles os acusarem de criminosos, tenham de reconhecer que vocês praticam boas ações, e assim louvem a Deus no dia f da sua vinda.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="13" />
      <text>Therefore subject yourselves to every ordinance of man for the Lord's sake: whether to the king, as supreme;</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>Por causa do Senhor, sejam obedientes a toda autoridade humana: ao Imperador g, que é a mais alta autoridade;</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="14" />
      <text>or to governors, as sent by him for vengeance on evildoers and for praise to those who do well.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>e aos governadores h, que são escolhidos por ele para castigar os criminosos e elogiar os que fazem o bem.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="15" />
      <text>For this is the will of God, that by well-doing you should put to silence the ignorance of foolish men:</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>Pois Deus quer que vocês façam o bem para que os ignorantes e tolos não tenham nada que dizer contra vocês.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="16" />
      <text>Live as free men, but do not use your freedom for a cloak of wickedness. Live as bondservants of God.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>Vivam como pessoas livres. Não usem a liberdade para encobrir o mal, mas vivam como escravos de Deus.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="17" />
      <text>Honor all men. Love the brotherhood. Fear God. Honor the king.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>Respeitem todas as pessoas, amem os seus irmãos na fé, * temam a Deus e respeitem o Imperador.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="18" />
      <text>Servants, be in subjection to your masters with all fear; not only to the good and gentle, but also to the wicked.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>Vocês, empregados, sejam obedientes aos seus patrões e os respeitem, não somente os que são bons e compreensivos, mas também aqueles que os tratam mal.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="19" />
      <text>For it is commendable if someone endures pain, suffering unjustly, because of conscience toward God.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>Se vocês suportarem sofrimentos injustos, sabendo que esta é a vontade de Deus, ele abençoará vocês por causa disso.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="20" />
      <text>For what glory is it if, when you sin, you patiently endure beating? But if, when you do well, you patiently endure suffering, this is commendable with God.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>Pois, se vocês fazem o mal e são castigados, qual é o merecimento de suportarem com paciência o castigo? Mas, se vocês sofrem por terem feito o bem e suportam esse sofrimento com paciência, Deus os abençoará por causa disso,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="21" />
      <text>For to this you were called, because Christ also suffered for us, leaving you an example, that you should follow his steps,</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>pois foi para isso que ele os * chamou. O próprio Cristo sofreu por vocês e deixou o exemplo, para que sigam os seus passos.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="22" />
      <text>who did not sin, “neither was deceit found in his mouth.”</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>Ele não cometeu nenhum pecado, e nunca disse uma só mentira.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="23" />
      <text>When he was cursed, he didn't curse back. When he suffered, he didn't threaten, but committed himself to him who judges righteously.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>Quando foi insultado, não respondeu com insultos. Quando sofreu, não ameaçou, mas pôs a sua esperança em Deus, o justo Juiz.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="24" />
      <text>He himself bore our sins in his body on the tree, that we, having died to sins, might live to righteousness; by whose stripes you were healed.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="24" />
    <text>O próprio Cristo levou os nossos pecados no seu corpo sobre a cruz a fim de que morrêssemos para o pecado e vivêssemos uma vida correta. Por meio dos ferimentos dele vocês foram curados.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="25" />
      <text>For you were going astray like sheep; but now have returned to the Shepherd and Overseer of your souls.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="25" />
    <text>Vocês eram como ovelhas que haviam perdido o caminho, mas agora foram trazidos de volta para seguir o Pastor, que cuida da vida espiritual de vocês.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" book="1PE" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="c" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="0">
      <text>1 PETER CHP 3</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <text>3</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="1" />
      <text>In the same way, wives, be in subjection to your own husbands; so that, even if any don't obey the Word, they may be won by the behavior of their wives without a word;</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Assim também você, esposa, deve obedecer ao seu marido a fim de que, se ele não crê na mensagem de Deus, seja levado a crer pelo modo de você agir. Não será preciso dizer nada</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="2" />
      <text>seeing your pure behavior in fear.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>porque ele verá como a conduta de você é honesta e respeitosa.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="3" />
      <text>Let your beauty be not just the outward adorning of braiding the hair, and of wearing jewels of gold, or of putting on fine clothing;</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>Não procure ficar bonita usando enfeites, penteados exagerados, jóias ou vestidos caros.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="4" />
      <text>but in the hidden person of the heart, in the incorruptible adornment of a gentle and quiet spirit, which is very precious in the sight of God.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>Pelo contrário, a beleza de você deve estar no coração, pois ela não se perde; ela é a beleza de um espírito calmo e delicado, que tem muito valor para Deus.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="5" />
      <text>For this is how the holy women before, who hoped in God also adorned themselves, being in subjection to their own husbands.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>Porque era assim que costumavam se enfeitar as mulheres do passado, as mulheres que eram dedicadas a Deus e que punham a sua esperança nele. Elas eram obedientes ao seu marido.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="6" />
      <text>Sarah obeyed Abraham, calling him lord. You are her children if you do well, and are not put in fear by any terror.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>Sara foi assim; ela obedecia a Abraão e o chamava de “meu senhor”. Você será agora sua filha se praticar o bem e não tiver medo de nada.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="7" />
      <text>You husbands, in the same way, live with your wives according to knowledge. Give honor to the woman, as to the weaker vessel, as being also joint heirs of the grace of life; that your prayers may not be hindered.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>Também você, marido, na vida em comum com a esposa, reconheça que a mulher é o sexo mais fraco e que por isso deve ser tratada com respeito. Porque a esposa também vai receber, junto com você, o dom da vida, que é dado por Deus. Aja assim para que nada atrapalhe as orações de vocês.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="8" />
      <text>Finally, be all like-minded, compassionate, loving as brothers, tenderhearted, courteous.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>Finalmente, que todos vocês tenham o mesmo modo de pensar e de sentir. Amem uns aos outros e sejam educados e humildes uns com os outros.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="9" />
      <text>Do not render evil for evil, or insult for insult; but instead blessing. Know that to this were you called, that you may inherit a blessing. </text>
      <verse num="10" />
      <text>For,</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>Não paguem mal com mal, nem ofensa com ofensa. Pelo contrário, paguem a ofensa com uma bênção porque, quando Deus os chamou, ele prometeu dar uma bênção a vocês. </text>
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>Como dizem as Escrituras Sagradas:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="scripture" multiBlockQuote="Start" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="scripture" multiBlockQuote="Start">
      <text>“He who would love life, and see good days, let him keep his tongue from evil, and his lips from speaking deceit.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <text>“Quem quiser gozar a vida e ter dias felizes não fale coisas más e não conte mentiras.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="scripture" multiBlockQuote="Continuation" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="scripture" multiBlockQuote="Continuation">
      <verse num="11" />
      <text>Let him turn away from evil, and do good. Let him seek peace, and pursue it.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>Afaste-se do mal e faça o bem; procure a paz e faça tudo para alcançá-la.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="scripture" multiBlockQuote="Continuation" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="scripture" multiBlockQuote="Continuation">
      <verse num="12" />
      <text>For the eyes of the Lord are on the righteous, and his ears open to their prayer; but the face of the Lord is against those who do evil.”</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>Pois o Senhor olha com atenção as pessoas honestas e ouve os seus pedidos, porém é contra os que fazem o mal.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="13" />
      <text>Now who is he who will harm you, if you become imitators of that which is good?</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>Se, de fato, vocês quiserem fazer o bem, quem lhes fará o mal?</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="14" />
      <text>But even if you should suffer for righteousness’ sake, you are blessed. “Don't fear what they fear, neither be troubled.”</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>Como vocês serão felizes se tiverem de sofrer por fazerem o que é certo! Não tenham medo de ninguém, nem fiquem preocupados.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="15" />
      <text>But sanctify the Lord God in your hearts. Always be ready to give an answer to everyone who asks you a reason concerning the hope that is in you, with humility and fear.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>Tenham no coração de vocês respeito por Cristo e o tratem como Senhor. Estejam sempre prontos para responder a qualquer pessoa que pedir que expliquem a esperança que vocês têm.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="16" />
      <text>Have a good conscience; that, while you are spoken against as evildoers, they may be disappointed who curse your good way of life in Christ.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>Porém façam isso com educação e respeito. Tenham sempre a consciência limpa. Assim, quando vocês forem insultados, os que falarem mal da boa conduta de vocês como seguidores de Cristo ficarão envergonhados.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="17" />
      <text>For it is better, if it is God's will, that you suffer for doing well than for doing evil.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>Porque é melhor sofrer por fazer o bem, se for esta a vontade de Deus, do que por fazer o mal.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="18" />
      <text>Because Christ also suffered for sins once, the righteous for the unrighteous, that he might bring you to God; being put to death in the flesh, but made alive in the spirit.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>Pois o próprio Cristo sofreu uma vez por todas pelos pecados, um homem bom em favor dos maus, para levar vocês a Deus. Ele morreu no corpo, mas foi ressuscitado no espírito,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="19" />
      <text>He also went and preached to the spirits in prison.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>e no espírito foi e pregou aos espíritos que estavam presos i.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="20" />
      <text>Those were the spirits of the people who were disobedient in the days of Noah. God waited patiently while the ship was being built. But only eight people were saved when the earth was flooded with water.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>Estes eram os espíritos daqueles que não tinham obedecido a Deus, quando ele ficou esperando com paciência nos dias em que Noé estava construindo a barca. As poucas pessoas que estavam nela, oito ao todo, foram salvas pela água.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="21" />
      <text>This water is a symbol of baptism, which now saves you-- not the putting away of the filth of the flesh, but the answer of a good conscience toward God, through the resurrection of Jesus Christ.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>Aquela água representava o batismo, que agora salva vocês. Esse batismo não é lavar a sujeira do corpo, mas é o compromisso feito com Deus, o qual vem de uma consciência limpa. Essa salvação vem por meio da ressurreição de Jesus Cristo,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="22" />
      <text>He has gone into heaven and is at the right hand of God. Having gone into heaven, angels, authorities, and powers have been made subject to him.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>que foi para o céu e está do lado direito j de Deus, governando os anjos, as autoridades e os poderes do céu.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" book="1PE" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="c" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="0">
      <text>1 PETER CHP 4</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <text>4</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="1" />
      <text>Forasmuch then as Christ suffered for us in the flesh, arm yourselves also with the same mind; for suffering in the flesh puts an end to sin.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Por isso, assim como Cristo sofreu no corpo, vocês também devem estar prontos, como ele estava, para sofrer. Porque aquele que sofre no corpo deixa de ser dominado pelo pecado.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="2" />
      <text>You should no longer live the rest of your time in the flesh for the lusts of men, but for the will of God.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>Então, de agora em diante, vivam o resto da sua vida aqui na terra de acordo com a vontade de Deus e não se deixem dominar pelas paixões humanas.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="3" />
      <text>For we have spent enough of our past time doing the desire of the Gentiles. Having walked in lewdness, lusts, drunken binges, orgies, carousings, and abominable idolatries.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>No passado vocês já gastaram bastante tempo fazendo o que os pagãos gostam de fazer. Naquele tempo vocês viviam na imoralidade, nos desejos carnais, nas bebedeiras, nas orgias, na embriaguez e na nojenta adoração de ídolos.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="4" />
      <text>They think it is strange that you don't run with them into the same excess of riot, blaspheming.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>E agora os pagãos ficam admirados quando vocês não se juntam com eles nessa vida louca e imoral e por isso os insultam.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="5" />
      <text>They will give account to him who is ready to judge the living and the dead.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>Porém eles vão ter de prestar contas a Deus, que está pronto para julgar os vivos e os mortos.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="6" />
      <text>For to this end the Good News was preached even to the dead, that they might be judged indeed as men in the flesh, but live as to God in the spirit.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>Pois o * evangelho foi anunciado também aos mortos, os quais morreram por causa do julgamento de Deus, como morrem todos os seres humanos. O evangelho foi anunciado a eles a fim de que pudessem viver a vida espiritual como Deus quer que eles vivam.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="7" />
      <text>But the end of all things is near. Therefore be of sound mind, self-controlled, and sober in prayer.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>O fim de todas as coisas está perto. Sejam prudentes e estejam alertas para poder orar.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="8" />
      <text>And above all things be earnest in your love among yourselves, for love covers a multitude of sins.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>Acima de tudo, amem sinceramente uns aos outros, pois o amor perdoa muitos pecados.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="9" />
      <text>Be hospitable to one another without grumbling.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>Hospedem uns aos outros, sem reclamar.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="10" />
      <text>As each has received a gift, employ it in serving one another, as good managers of the grace of God in its various forms.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>Sejam bons administradores dos diferentes * dons que receberam de Deus. Que cada um use o seu próprio dom para o bem dos outros!</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="11" />
      <text>If anyone speaks, let it be as it were the very words of God. If anyone serves, let it be as of the strength which God supplies. That in all things God may be glorified through Jesus Christ, to whom belong the glory and the dominion forever and ever. Amen.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>Quem prega pregue a palavra de Deus; quem serve sirva com a força que Deus dá. Façam assim para que em tudo Deus seja louvado por meio de Jesus Cristo, a quem pertencem a * glória e o poder para todo o sempre! * Amém!</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="12" />
      <text>Beloved, don't be astonished at the fiery trial which has come upon you, to test you, as though a strange thing happened to you.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>Meus queridos amigos, não fiquem admirados com a dura prova de aflição pela qual vocês estão passando, como se alguma coisa fora do comum estivesse acontecendo a vocês.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="13" />
      <text>But because you are partakers of Christ's sufferings, rejoice; that at the revelation of his glory you also may rejoice with exceeding joy.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>Pelo contrário, alegrem-se por estarem tomando parte nos sofrimentos de Cristo, para que fiquem cheios de alegria quando a * glória dele for revelada.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="14" />
      <text>If you are insulted for the name of Christ, you are blessed; because the Spirit of glory and of God rests on you. On their part he is blasphemed, but on your part he is glorified.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>Vocês serão felizes se forem insultados por serem seguidores de Cristo, porque isso quer dizer que o glorioso Espírito de Deus veio sobre vocês.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="15" />
      <text>For let none of you suffer as a murderer, or a thief, or an evil doer, or a meddler in other men's matters.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>Se algum de vocês tiver de sofrer, que não seja por ser assassino, ladrão, criminoso ou por se meter na vida dos outros.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="16" />
      <text>But if one of you suffers for being a Christian, let him not be ashamed; but let him glorify God in this matter.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>Mas, se alguém sofrer por ser cristão, não fique envergonhado, mas agradeça a Deus o fato de ser chamado por esse nome.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="17" />
      <text>For the time has come for judgment to begin with the household of God. If it begins first with us, what will happen to those who don't obey the Good News of God?</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>Pois o tempo de começar o julgamento já chegou, e os que pertencem ao povo de Deus serão os primeiros a serem julgados. Se esse julgamento vai começar conosco, qual será o fim daqueles que não crêem no evangelho de Deus? Como dizem as Escrituras Sagradas:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-1PE" userConfirmed="true">
      <verse num="18" />
      <text>“If it is hard for the righteous to be saved, what will happen to the ungodly and the sinner?”</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>“Se é difícil os bons serem salvos, o que será daqueles pecadores que não querem saber de Deus?”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="19" />
      <text>Therefore let them also who suffer according to the will of God in doing good entrust their souls to him, as to a faithful Creator.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>Por isso os que sofrem porque esta é a vontade de Deus para eles devem, por meio das suas boas ações, entregar-se completamente aos cuidados do Criador, que sempre cumpre as suas promessas.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" book="1PE" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="c" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="0">
      <text>1 PETER CHP 5</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <text>5</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="1" />
      <text>I exhort the elders among you, as a fellow elder. As a witness of the sufferings of Christ, and as one who will also share in the glory that will be revealed.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Eu, que também sou presbítero, dou agora conselhos aos outros presbíteros que estão entre vocês. Sou uma testemunha dos sofrimentos de Cristo e vou tomar parte na glória que será revelada.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="2" />
      <text>Shepherd the flock of God which is among you. Exercise oversight, not under compulsion, but voluntarily, not for dishonest gain, but willingly.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>Aconselho que cuidem bem do rebanho que Deus lhes deu e façam isso de boa vontade, como Deus quer, e não de má vontade. Não façam o seu trabalho para ganhar dinheiro, mas com o verdadeiro desejo de servir.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="3" />
      <text>Do not lord it over those entrusted to you, but make yourselves examples to the flock.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>Não procurem dominar os que foram entregues aos cuidados de vocês, mas sejam um exemplo para o rebanho.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="4" />
      <text>When the chief Shepherd is revealed, you will receive the crown of glory that doesn't fade away.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>E, quando o Grande Pastor m aparecer, vocês receberão a coroa * gloriosa, que nunca perde o seu brilho.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="5" />
      <text>Likewise, you younger ones, be subject to the elder. Yes, all of you clothe yourselves with humility, to subject yourselves to one another; for</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>E vocês, jovens, sejam obedientes aos mais velhos. Que todos prestem serviços uns aos outros com humildade, pois as Escrituras Sagradas dizem:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="scripture" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="scripture">
      <text>“God resists the proud, but gives grace to the humble.”</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <text>“Deus é contra os orgulhosos, mas é bondoso com os humildes!”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="6" />
      <text>Humble yourselves therefore under the mighty hand of God, that he may exalt you in due time.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>Portanto, sejam humildes debaixo da poderosa mão de Deus para que ele os honre no tempo certo.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="7" />
      <text>Cast all your worries on him, because he cares for you.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>Entreguem todas as suas preocupações a Deus, pois ele cuida de vocês.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="8" />
      <text>Be sober and self-controlled. Be watchful. Your adversary, the devil, walks around like a roaring lion, seeking whom he may devour.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>Estejam alertas e fiquem vigiando porque o inimigo de vocês, o Diabo, anda por aí como um leão que ruge, procurando alguém para devorar.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="9" />
      <text>Withstand him steadfast in your faith, knowing that your brothers who are in the world are undergoing the same sufferings.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>Fiquem firmes na fé e enfrentem o Diabo porque vocês sabem que no mundo inteiro os seus irmãos na fé estão passando pelos mesmos sofrimentos.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="10" />
      <text>But may the God of all grace, who called you to his eternal glory by Christ Jesus, after you have suffered a little while, perfect, establish, strengthen, and settle you.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>Mas, depois de sofrerem por um pouco de tempo, o Deus que tem por nós um amor sem limites e que chamou vocês para tomarem parte na sua eterna glória, por estarem unidos com Cristo, ele mesmo os aperfeiçoará e dará firmeza, força e verdadeira segurança.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="11" />
      <text>To him be the glory and the power forever and ever. Amen.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>A ele seja o poder para sempre! * Amém!</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="12" />
      <text>Through Silvanus, our faithful brother, as I consider him, I have written to you briefly, exhorting, and testifying that this is the true grace of God in which you stand.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>Escrevo para vocês esta pequena carta com a ajuda de Silas, a quem eu considero um fiel irmão na fé. Quero animá-los e dar o meu testemunho de que as bênçãos que vocês têm recebido são uma prova verdadeira da * graça de Deus. Continuem firmes, pois, nessa graça.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="13" />
      <text>She who is in Babylon, chosen together with you, greets you; and so does Mark, my son.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>A igreja que está em Babilônia n, escolhida também por Deus, manda saudações. O meu filho Marcos o também manda saudações.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1PE" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1PE">
      <verse num="14" />
      <text>Greet one another with a kiss of love. Peace be to you all who are in Christ Jesus. Amen.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>Cumprimentem uns aos outros com um beijo de irmão. Que a paz esteja com todos vocês que pertencem a Cristo!</text>
  </block>
  <UnappliedSplits />
</book>