<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<book id="1TI" singlevoice="false" pageheader="1 TIMOTHY">
  <block style="mt" chapter="0" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="mt" chapter="0" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1TI">
      <text>1 TIMOTHY</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <text>1 TIMOTHY</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" book="1TI" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="c" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="0">
      <text>1 TIMOTHY 1</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <text>1</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="1" />
      <text>Paul, an apostle of Christ Jesus according to the commandment of God our Savior, and Lord Christ Jesus our hope;</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Eu, Paulo, * apóstolo de Cristo Jesus por ordem de Deus, o nosso Salvador, e de Cristo Jesus, a nossa esperança,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="2" />
      <text>to Timothy, my true child in faith: Grace, mercy, and peace, from God our Father and Christ Jesus our Lord.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>escrevo a você, Timóteo, meu verdadeiro filho na fé. Que a * graça, a misericórdia e a paz de Deus, o Pai, e de Cristo Jesus, o nosso Senhor, estejam com você!</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="3" />
      <text>As I urged you when I was going into Macedonia, stay at Ephesus that you might command certain men not to teach a different doctrine,</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>Peço que você continue na cidade de Éfeso, como já pedi quando estava indo para a * província da Macedônia. Existem aí nessa cidade alguns que estão ensinando doutrinas falsas, e você precisa fazer com que eles parem com isso.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="4" />
      <text>neither to pay attention to myths and endless genealogies, which cause disputes, rather than God’s stewardship, which is in faith.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>Diga a essa gente que deixe de lado as lendas e as longas listas de nomes de antepassados a, pois essas coisas só produzem discussões. Elas não têm nada a ver com o plano de Deus, que é conhecido somente por meio da fé.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="5" />
      <text>The goal of this command is love, out of a pure heart and a good conscience and sincere faith.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>Essa ordem está sendo dada a fim de que amemos uns aos outros com um amor que vem de um coração puro, de uma consciência limpa e de uma fé verdadeira.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="6" />
      <text>Some have wandered away from these things and have turned aside to vain talking.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>Alguns abandonaram essas coisas e se perderam em discussões inúteis.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="7" />
      <text>They want to be teachers of the law, though they understand neither what they say, nor about what they strongly affirm.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>Eles querem ser * mestres da Lei de Deus, mas não entendem nem o que eles mesmos dizem, nem aquilo que falam com tanta certeza.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="8" />
      <text>But we know that the law is good, if a man uses it lawfully.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>Sabemos que a lei de Deus é boa, se for usada como se deve.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="9" />
      <text>We also know that law is not made for a righteous man, but for the lawless and insubordinate, for the ungodly and sinners, for the unholy and profane, for murderers of fathers and murderers of mothers, for manslayers,</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>Devemos lembrar, é claro, que as leis são feitas não para as pessoas corretas, mas para os marginais e os criminosos, os ateus e os que praticam o mal e para os que não respeitam a Deus nem a religião. São feitas também para os que matam os seus pais e para outros assassinos.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="10" />
      <text>for the sexually immoral, for homosexuals, for slave-traders, for liars, for perjurers, and for any other thing contrary to the sound doctrine.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>E para os imorais, os homossexuais, os seqüestradores, os mentirosos, os que dão falso testemunho e para os que fazem qualquer outra coisa que é contra o verdadeiro ensinamento.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="11" />
      <text>This sound doctrine conforms to the Good News of the glory of the blessed God, and it was entrusted to me.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>Esse ensinamento se encontra no * evangelho que Deus me encarregou de anunciar, isto é, na boa notícia que vem do Deus bendito e * glorioso.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="12" />
      <text>And I thank him who enabled me, Christ Jesus our Lord, because he counted me faithful, appointing me to service;</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>Agradeço a Cristo Jesus, o nosso Senhor, que me tem dado forças para cumprir a minha missão. Eu lhe agradeço porque ele achou que eu era merecedor e porque me escolheu para servi-lo.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="13" />
      <text>Even though before I was a a blasphemer, a persecutor, and insolent, I was shown mercy because I did it ignorantly, in unbelief.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>Ele fez isso apesar de eu ter dito * blasfêmias contra ele no passado e de o ter perseguido e insultado. Mas Deus teve misericórdia de mim, pois eu não tinha fé e por isso não sabia o que estava fazendo.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="14" />
      <text>The grace of our Lord abounded exceedingly with faith and love which is in Christ Jesus.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>E o nosso Senhor derramou a sua imensa * graça sobre mim e me deu a fé e o amor que temos por estarmos unidos com Cristo Jesus.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="15" />
      <text>The saying is faithful and worthy of all acceptance, that Christ Jesus came into the world to save sinners; of whom I am chief.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>O ensinamento verdadeiro e que deve ser crido e aceito de todo o coração é este: Cristo Jesus veio ao mundo para salvar os pecadores, dos quais eu sou o pior.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="16" />
      <text>However, for this cause I obtained mercy, that in me first, Jesus Christ might display all his patience, for an example of those who were going to believe in him for eternal life.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>Mas foi por esse mesmo motivo que Deus teve misericórdia de mim, para que Cristo Jesus pudesse mostrar toda a sua paciência comigo. E isso ficará como exemplo para todos os que, no futuro, vão crer nele e receber a vida eterna.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="17" />
      <text>Now to the King eternal, immortal, invisible, to God who alone is wise, be honor and glory forever and ever. Amen.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>Ao Rei eterno, * imortal e invisível, o único Deus — a ele sejam dadas a honra e a * glória, para todo o sempre! * Amém!</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="18" />
      <text>This instruction I commit to you, my child Timothy, according to the prophecies which were once made about you. So that by following them you may fight the good fight.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>Timóteo, meu filho, eu entrego essa ordem a você. Ela está de acordo com as palavras da profecia b, ditas há muito tempo a respeito de você. Que essas palavras sejam as suas armas para que você possa combater bem!</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="19" />
      <text>Keep hold of faith and a good conscience. Some, having thrust these away, have shipwrecked their faith.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>Conserve a sua fé e mantenha a sua consciência limpa. Algumas pessoas não têm escutado a sua própria consciência, e isso tem causado a destruição da sua fé.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="20" />
      <text>This happened to Hymenaeus and Alexander; whom I delivered to Satan, that they might be taught not to blaspheme.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>Entre elas estão Himeneu e Alexandre, que eu já entreguei a Satanás c para que aprendessem a não * blasfemar mais.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" book="1TI" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="c" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="0">
      <text>1 TIMOTHY 2</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <text>2</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="1" />
      <text>I exhort therefore, first of all, that petitions, prayers, intercessions, and givings of thanks, be made for all men:</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Em primeiro lugar peço que sejam feitos orações, pedidos, súplicas e ações de graças a Deus em favor de todas as pessoas.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="2" />
      <text>for kings and all who are in high places; that we may lead a tranquil and quiet life in all godliness and reverence.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>Orem pelos reis e por todos os outros que têm autoridade, para que possamos viver uma vida calma e pacífica, com dedicação a Deus e respeito aos outros.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="3" />
      <text>For this is good and acceptable in the sight of God our Savior;</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>Isso é bom, e Deus, o nosso Salvador, gosta disso.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="4" />
      <text>who desires all people to be saved and come to full knowledge of the truth.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>Ele quer que todos sejam salvos e venham a conhecer a verdade.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="5" />
      <text>For there is one God, and one mediator between God and men, the man Christ Jesus.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>Pois existe um só Deus e uma só pessoa que une Deus com os seres humanos — o ser humano Cristo Jesus,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="6" />
      <text>He gave himself as a ransom for all. God made this known to the world at the right time.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>que deu a sua vida para que todos fiquem livres dos seus pecados. Esta foi a prova, dada no tempo certo, de que Deus quer que todos sejam salvos.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="7" />
      <text>For this purpose, I was appointed a preacher and an apostle. (I am telling the truth in Christ, not lying), a teacher of the Gentiles in faith and truth.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>E eu fui escolhido como * apóstolo e mestre dos não-judeus para anunciar a mensagem da fé e da verdade. Eu não estou mentindo; estou dizendo a verdade.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="8" />
      <text>I desire therefore that the men in every place pray, lifting up holy hands without anger and doubting.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>Quero que em todos os lugares os homens orem, homens dedicados a Deus; e que, ao orarem, eles levantem as mãos, sem ódio e sem brigas.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="9" />
      <text>In the same way, that women also adorn themselves in decent clothing, with modesty and propriety; not just with braided hair, gold, pearls, or expensive clothing;</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>Quero também que as mulheres sejam sensatas e usem roupas decentes e simples. Que elas se enfeitem, mas não com penteados complicados, nem com jóias de ouro ou de pérolas, nem com roupas caras!</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="10" />
      <text>but with good works appropriate for women who profess to worship God.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>Que se enfeitem com boas ações, como devem fazer as mulheres que dizem que são dedicadas a Deus!</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="11" />
      <text>Let a woman learn in quietness with all subjection.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>As mulheres devem aprender em silêncio e com toda a humildade.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="12" />
      <text>I don’t permit a woman to teach, nor to exercise authority over a man, but to be in quietness.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>Não permito que as mulheres ensinem ou tenham autoridade sobre os homens; elas devem ficar em silêncio.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="13" />
      <text>For Adam was first formed, then Eve.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>Pois Adão foi criado primeiro, e depois Eva.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="14" />
      <text>Adam wasn’t deceived, but the woman, being deceived, has fallen into disobedience.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>E não foi Adão quem foi enganado; a mulher é que foi enganada e desobedeceu à * lei de Deus.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="15" />
      <text>But she will be saved through her childbearing, if they continue in faith, love, and sanctification with sobriety.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>Mas a mulher será salva tendo filhos se ela, com pureza, continuar na fé, no amor e na dedicação a Deus.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" book="1TI" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="c" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="0">
      <text>1 TIMOTHY 3</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <text>3</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="1" />
      <text>This is a faithful saying: if a man seeks the office of an overseer, he desires a good work.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Este ensinamento é verdadeiro: se alguém quer muito ser * bispo na Igreja, está desejando um trabalho excelente.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="2" />
      <text>The overseer therefore must be without reproach, the husband of one wife, temperate, sensible, modest, hospitable, good at teaching;</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>O bispo deve ser um homem que ninguém possa culpar de nada. Deve ter somente uma esposa, ser moderado, prudente e simples. Deve estar disposto a hospedar pessoas na sua casa e ter capacidade para ensinar.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="3" />
      <text>not a drinker, not violent, not greedy for money, but gentle, not quarrelsome, not covetous;</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>Não pode ser chegado ao vinho nem briguento, mas deve ser pacífico e calmo. Não deve amar o dinheiro.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="4" />
      <text>one who rules his own house well, having children in subjection with all reverence;</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>Deve ser um bom chefe da sua própria família e saber educar os seus filhos de maneira que eles lhe obedeçam com todo o respeito.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="5" />
      <text>(If a man doesn’t know how to rule his own house, how will he take care of the assembly of God?)</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>Pois, se alguém não sabe governar a sua própria família, como poderá cuidar da Igreja de Deus?</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="6" />
      <text>He must not be a new convert, lest being puffed up he fall into the same condemnation as the devil.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>O bispo não deve ser alguém * convertido há pouco tempo; se for, ele ficará cheio de orgulho e será condenado como o Diabo foi.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="7" />
      <text>Moreover he must have good testimony from those who are outside, to avoid falling into reproach and the snare of the devil.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>É preciso que o bispo seja respeitado pelos de fora da Igreja, para que não fique desmoralizado e não caia na armadilha do Diabo.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="8" />
      <text>Servants, in the same way, must be reverent, not double-tongued, not addicted to much wine, not greedy for money;</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>Do mesmo modo, os * diáconos devem ser homens de palavra e sérios. Não devem beber muito vinho, nem ser gananciosos.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="9" />
      <text>They must hold the mystery of the faith in a pure conscience.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>Eles devem se apegar à verdade revelada da fé e ter sempre a consciência limpa.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="10" />
      <text>Let them also first be tested; then let them serve if they are blameless.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>Primeiro devem ser provados e depois, se forem aprovados, que sirvam a Igreja.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="11" />
      <text>Their wives in the same way must be reverent, not slanderers, temperate, faithful in all things.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>A esposa do diácono também deve ser respeitável e não deve ser faladeira. Ela precisa ser moderada e fiel em tudo.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="12" />
      <text>Let servants be husbands of one wife, ruling their children and their own houses well.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>O diácono deve ter somente uma esposa e ser capaz de governar bem os seus filhos e toda a sua família.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="13" />
      <text>For those who have served well gain for themselves a good standing, and great boldness in the faith which is in Christ Jesus.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>Pois os diáconos que fazem um bom trabalho conquistam o respeito dos irmãos na fé e são capazes de falar com coragem sobre a sua fé em Cristo Jesus.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="14" />
      <text>These things I write to you, hoping to come to you shortly;</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>Escrevo essas coisas a você, esperando ir vê-lo logo.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="15" />
      <text>but if I wait long, I want you to know how men ought to behave themselves in God’s house. It is the assembly of the living God, the pillar and ground of the truth.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>Mas, se eu demorar, esta carta vai lhe dizer como devemos agir na família de Deus, que é a Igreja do Deus vivo, a qual é a coluna e o alicerce da verdade.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="16" />
      <text>Without controversy, the mystery of godliness is great: God was revealed in the flesh, justified in the spirit, seen by angels, preached among the nations, believed on in the world, and received up in glory.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>Sem nenhuma dúvida, é grandiosa a verdade revelada da nossa religião. Essa verdade é a seguinte: “Ele se tornou um ser humano, foi aprovado pelo Espírito de Deus, foi visto pelos anjos, foi anunciado entre as nações, foi aceito com fé por muitos no mundo inteiro e foi levado para a * glória.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" book="1TI" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="c" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="0">
      <text>1 TIMOTHY 4</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <text>4</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="1" />
      <text>But the Spirit says expressly that in later times some will fall away from the faith, paying attention to seducing spirits and doctrines of demons.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>O Espírito de Deus diz claramente que, nos últimos tempos, alguns abandonarão a fé. Eles darão atenção a espíritos enganadores e a ensinamentos que vêm de demônios.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="2" />
      <text>Such teachings come through hypocritical liars, whose consciences have been seared as with a hot iron.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>Esses ensinamentos são espalhados por pessoas hipócritas e mentirosas, pessoas cuja consciência está morta como se tivesse sido queimada com ferro em brasa.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="3" />
      <text>They will forbid marriage and command you to abstain from foods. Things which God created to be received with thanksgiving by those who believe and know the truth.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>Essas pessoas ensinam que é errado casar e que é errado comer certos alimentos. Mas Deus criou esses alimentos para que aqueles que crêem e conhecem a verdade os comam depois de terem feito uma oração de agradecimento.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="4" />
      <text>For every creature of God is good, and nothing is to be rejected, if it is received with thanksgiving.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>Tudo o que Deus criou é bom, e, portanto, nada deve ser rejeitado. Que tudo seja recebido com uma oração de agradecimento</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="5" />
      <text>For it is sanctified through the word of God and prayer.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>porque a palavra de Deus d e a oração tornam todos os alimentos aceitáveis a ele!</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="6" />
      <text>If you instruct the brothers of these things, you will be a good servant of Christ Jesus. You will be nourished in the words of the faith, and of the good doctrine which you have followed.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>Se der esses conselhos aos irmãos na fé, você será um bom servo de Cristo Jesus, alimentando-se espiritualmente com as doutrinas da fé e com o verdadeiro ensinamento que você tem seguido.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="7" />
      <text>But refuse profane and old wives’ fables. Exercise yourself toward godliness.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>Mas não tenha nada a ver com as lendas pagãs e tolas. Para progredir na vida cristã, faça sempre exercícios espirituais.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="8" />
      <text>For bodily exercise has some value, but godliness has value in all things, having the promise of the life which is now, and of that which is to come.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>Pois os exercícios físicos têm alguma utilidade, mas o exercício espiritual tem valor para tudo porque o seu resultado é a vida, tanto agora como no futuro.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="9" />
      <text>This saying is faithful and worthy of all acceptance.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>Esse ensinamento é verdadeiro e deve ser crido e aceito de todo o coração.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="10" />
      <text>For to this end we both labor and suffer reproach, because we have set our trust in the living God. He is the Savior of all men, especially of those who believe.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>É por isso que lutamos e trabalhamos muito, pois temos posto a nossa esperança no Deus vivo, que é o Salvador de todos, especialmente dos que crêem.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="11" />
      <text>Command and teach these things.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>Recomende e ensine estas coisas.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="12" />
      <text>Let no man despise your youth; but be an example to those who believe, in word, in your way of life, in love, in spirit, in faith, and in purity.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>Não deixe que ninguém o despreze por você ser jovem. Mas, para os que crêem, seja um exemplo na maneira de falar, na maneira de agir, no amor, na fé e na pureza.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="13" />
      <text>Until I come, pay attention to reading, to exhortation, and to teaching.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>Enquanto você espera a minha chegada, dedique-se à leitura em público das * Escrituras Sagradas, à pregação do * evangelho e ao ensino cristão.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="14" />
      <text>Don’t neglect the gift that is in you, which was given to you by prophecy, with the laying on of the hands of the elders.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>Não se descuide do * dom que você tem, que Deus lhe deu quando os * profetas da Igreja falaram, e o grupo de * presbíteros pôs as mãos sobre a sua cabeça para dedicá-lo ao serviço do Senhor.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="15" />
      <text>Be diligent in these things. Give yourself wholly to them, that your progress may be revealed to all.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>Pratique essas coisas e se dedique a elas a fim de que o seu progresso seja visto por todos.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="4" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="16" />
      <text>Pay attention to yourself, and to your teaching. Continue in these things, for in doing this you will save both yourself and those who hear you.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>Cuide de você mesmo e tenha cuidado com o que ensina. Continue fazendo isso, pois assim você salvará tanto você mesmo como os que o escutam.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" book="1TI" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="c" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="0">
      <text>1 TIMOTHY 5</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <text>5</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="1" />
      <text>Don’t rebuke an older man, but exhort him as a father; the younger men as brothers;</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Não repreenda um homem mais velho, mas o aconselhe como se ele fosse o seu pai. Trate os homens mais jovens como irmãos,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="2" />
      <text>the elder women as mothers; the younger as sisters, in all purity.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>as mulheres idosas, como mães e as mulheres jovens, como irmãs, com toda a pureza.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="3" />
      <text>Honor widows who are widows indeed.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>Cuide das viúvas que não tenham ninguém para ajudá-las.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="4" />
      <text>But if any widow has children or grandchildren, let them learn first to show piety towards their own family. They should first repay their parents, for this is acceptable in the sight of God.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>Mas, se alguma viúva tem filhos ou netos, são eles que devem primeiro aprender a cumprir os seus deveres religiosos, cuidando da sua própria família. Assim eles pagarão o que receberam dos seus pais e avós, pois Deus gosta disso.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="5" />
      <text>Now she who is a widow indeed, and desolate, has her hope set on God, and continues in petitions and prayers night and day.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>A verdadeira viúva, aquela que não tem ninguém para cuidar dela, põe a sua esperança em Deus e ora, de dia e de noite, pedindo a ajuda dele.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="6" />
      <text>But she who gives herself to pleasure is dead while she lives.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>Porém a viúva que se entrega ao prazer está morta em vida.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="7" />
      <text>Also command these things, that they may be without reproach.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>Timóteo, mande que as viúvas façam o que eu aconselho para que ninguém possa culpá-las de nada.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="8" />
      <text>But if anyone doesn’t provide for his own, and especially his own household, he has denied the faith, and is worse than an unbeliever.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>Porém aquele que não cuida dos seus parentes, especialmente dos da sua própria família, negou a fé e é pior do que os que não crêem.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="9" />
      <text>Let no one be enrolled as a widow under sixty years old, having been the wife of one man.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>Coloque na lista das viúvas somente a que tiver mais de sessenta anos e que tiver casado uma vez só.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="10" />
      <text>She must be known for doing good works, if she has brought up children, if she has been hospitable to strangers, if she has washed the saints’ feet, if she has relieved the afflicted, and if she has diligently followed every good work.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>Ela deve ser conhecida como uma mulher que sempre praticou boas ações, criou bem os filhos, hospedou pessoas na sua casa, prestou serviços humildes aos que pertencem ao povo de Deus, ajudou os necessitados, enfim, fez todo tipo de coisas boas.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="11" />
      <text>But refuse younger widows, for when they have grown wanton against Christ, they desire to marry.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>Mas não ponha na lista as viúvas mais jovens; porque, quando os seus desejos fazem com que queiram casar de novo, elas abandonam a Cristo.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="12" />
      <text>Thus they bring judgement on themselves because they have rejected their first pledge.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>E assim elas se tornam culpadas de quebrar a primeira promessa que fizeram a ele e.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="13" />
      <text>Besides, they also learn to be idle, going about from house to house. Not only idle, but also gossips and busybodies, saying things which they ought not.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>Além disso, elas se acostumam a não fazer nada e a andar de casa em casa; e, pior ainda, aprendem a ser mexeriqueiras, metendo-se em tudo e falando coisas que não devem.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="14" />
      <text>I desire therefore that the younger widows marry, bear children, rule the household, and give no occasion to the adversary for insulting.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>Por isso, eu quero que as viúvas mais novas casem, tenham filhos e cuidem da sua casa, para que os nossos inimigos não tenham motivos para falar mal de nós.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="15" />
      <text>For already some have turned aside after Satan.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>Pois algumas viúvas já se desviaram e seguiram Satanás.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="16" />
      <text>If any man or woman who believes has widows, let them relieve them. Don’t let the assembly be burdened; that it might relieve those who are widows indeed.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>Se alguma mulher cristã tem viúvas na sua família, ela deve ajudá-las. Que ela não ponha essa carga sobre a igreja, para que a igreja possa cuidar das viúvas que não tenham ninguém que as ajude!</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="17" />
      <text>Let the elders who rule well be counted worthy of double honor, especially those who labor in the word and in teaching. </text>
      <verse num="18" />
      <text>For the Scripture says,</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>Os * presbíteros que fazem um bom trabalho na igreja merecem pagamento em dobro, especialmente os que se esforçam na pregação do * evangelho e no ensino cristão. </text>
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>Pois as Escrituras Sagradas dizem:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="scripture" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="scripture">
      <text>“You shall not muzzle the ox when it treads out the grain.”</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <text>“Não amarre a boca do boi quando ele estiver pisando o trigo.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <text>And,</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <text>E dizem ainda:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="scripture" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="scripture">
      <text>“The laborer is worthy of his wages.”</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <text>“O trabalhador merece o seu salário.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="19" />
      <text>Don’t receive an accusation against an elder, except at the word of two or three witnesses.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>Não aceite nenhuma acusação contra qualquer presbítero, a não ser que ela seja feita por duas testemunhas, pelo menos.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="20" />
      <text>Those who sin, reprove in the sight of all, that the rest also may be in fear.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>Repreenda publicamente os presbíteros que cometem pecados, para que os outros fiquem com medo.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="21" />
      <text>I command you in the sight of God, and Lord Christ Jesus, and the chosen angels. Observe these things without prejudice, doing nothing by partiality.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>Na presença de Deus, de Cristo Jesus e dos santos anjos, eu peço e insisto no seguinte: em tudo o que você fizer, obedeça a estas instruções, sem preconceito contra ninguém e sem favorecer nenhuma pessoa.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="22" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="22" />
      <text>Lay hands hastily on no one, neither be a participant in other men’s sins. Keep yourself pure.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="22" />
    <text>Não tenha pressa de colocar as mãos sobre alguém para dedicá-lo ao serviço do Senhor. Não tome parte nos pecados dos outros. Conserve-se puro.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="23" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="23" />
      <text>Be no longer a drinker of water only, but use a little wine for your stomach’s sake and your frequent infirmities.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="23" />
    <text>Já que muitas vezes você tem ficado doente do estômago, não beba somente água, mas beba também um pouco de vinho.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="24" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="24" />
      <text>Some men’s sins are evident, preceding them to judgment, and some also follow later.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="24" />
    <text>Os pecados de algumas pessoas podem ser vistos claramente, antes mesmo de elas serem julgadas. Mas os pecados de outras pessoas só são vistos depois.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="5" initialStartVerse="25" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="25" />
      <text>In the same way also there are good works that are obvious, and those that are otherwise can’t be hidden.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="25" />
    <text>Assim também as boas ações são vistas claramente e mesmo aquelas que são difíceis de ver não poderão ficar escondidas para sempre.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="6" book="1TI" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="c" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="0">
      <text>1 TIMOTHY 6</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <text>6</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="1" />
      <text>Let as many as are bondservants under the yoke count their own masters worthy of all honor, that the name of God and the doctrine not be blasphemed.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Aqueles que são escravos devem tratar o seu dono com todo o respeito, para que ninguém fale mal do nome de Deus e dos nossos ensinamentos.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="2" />
      <text>Those who have believing masters, let them not despise them, because they are brothers, but rather let them serve them. Those who partake of the benefit are believing and beloved. Teach and exhort these things.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>E os escravos que têm dono cristão não devem perder o respeito por ele por ser seu irmão na fé. Pelo contrário, devem trabalhar para ele melhor ainda, pois o dono, que recebe os seus serviços, é cristão e irmão amado. Ensine e recomende estas coisas:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="3" />
      <text>If anyone teaches a different doctrine, and doesn’t consent to sound words, the words of our Lord Jesus Christ, and to the doctrine which is according to godliness,</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>Se alguém ensina alguma doutrina diferente e não concorda com as verdadeiras palavras do nosso Senhor Jesus Cristo e com os ensinamentos da nossa religião,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="4" />
      <text>he is conceited, knowing nothing, but obsessed with arguments, disputes, and word battles, from which come envy, strife, insulting, evil suspicions,</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>essa pessoa está cheia de orgulho e não sabe nada. Discutir e brigar a respeito de palavras é como uma doença nessas pessoas. E daí vêm invejas, brigas, insultos, desconfianças maldosas</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="5" />
      <text>and constant friction of people of corrupt minds, and destitute of the truth, who suppose that gain is godliness. Withdraw yourself from such.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>e discussões sem fim, como costumam fazer as pessoas que perderam o juízo e não têm mais a verdade. Essa gente pensa que a religião é um meio de enriquecer.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="6" />
      <text>But godliness with contentment is great gain.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>É claro que a religião é uma fonte de muita riqueza, mas só para a pessoa que se contenta com o que tem.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="7" />
      <text>For we brought nothing into the world, and we certainly can’t carry anything out.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>O que foi que trouxemos para o mundo? Nada! E o que é que vamos levar do mundo? Nada!</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="8" />
      <text>But having food and clothing, we will be content with that.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>Portanto, se temos comida e roupas, fiquemos contentes com isso.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="9" />
      <text>But those who are determined to be rich fall into a temptation and a snare and many foolish and harmful lusts, such as drown men in ruin and destruction.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>Porém os que querem ficar ricos caem em pecado, ao serem tentados, e ficam presos na armadilha de muitos desejos tolos, que fazem mal e levam as pessoas a se afundarem na desgraça e na destruição.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="10" />
      <text>For the love of money is a root of all evil. Some have been led astray from the faith in their greed, and have pierced themselves through with many sorrows.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>Pois o amor ao dinheiro é uma fonte de todos os tipos de males. E algumas pessoas, por quererem tanto ter dinheiro, se desviaram da fé e encheram a sua vida de sofrimentos.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="11" />
      <text>But you, man of God, flee these things, and follow after righteousness, godliness, faith, love, patience, and gentleness.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>Mas você, homem de Deus, fuja de tudo isso. Viva uma vida correta, de dedicação a Deus, de fé, de amor, de perseverança e de respeito pelos outros.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="12" />
      <text>Fight the good fight of faith. Lay hold of the eternal life to which you were called, and you confessed the good confession in the sight of many witnesses.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>Corra a boa corrida da fé e ganhe a vida eterna. Pois foi para essa vida que Deus o chamou quando você deu o seu belo testemunho de fé na presença de muitas testemunhas f.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="13" />
      <text>I command you before God, who gives life to all things, and before Christ Jesus, who before Pontius Pilate testified the good confession.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>Agora, diante de Deus, que dá vida a todas as criaturas, e diante de Cristo Jesus, que deu o seu belo testemunho de fé em frente de Pôncio Pilatos, eu ordeno a você o seguinte:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="14" />
      <text>Keep the commandment without spot, blameless, until the appearing of our Lord Jesus Christ;</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>Cumpra a sua missão com fidelidade, para que ninguém possa culpá-lo de nada, e continue assim até o dia g em que o nosso Senhor Jesus Cristo aparecer.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="15" />
      <text>At the right time we will be shown that God is the blessed and only Ruler, the King of kings, and Lord of lords;</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>Quando chegar o tempo certo, Deus fará com que isso aconteça, o mesmo Deus que é o bendito e único Rei, o Rei dos reis e o Senhor dos senhores,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="16" />
      <text>He alone has immortality, dwelling in unapproachable light; whom no man has seen, nor can see: to whom be honor and eternal power. Amen.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>o único que é imortal. Ele vive na luz, e ninguém pode chegar perto dela. Ninguém nunca o viu, nem poderá ver. A ele pertence a honra e o poder eterno! Amém!</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="17" />
      <text>Charge those who are rich in this present world. They should not be haughty, nor have their hope set on the uncertainty of riches, but on the living God, who richly provides us with everything to enjoy.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>Aos que têm riquezas neste mundo ordene que não sejam orgulhosos e que não ponham a sua esperança nessas riquezas, pois elas não dão segurança nenhuma. Que eles ponham a sua esperança em Deus, que nos dá todas as coisas em grande quantidade, para o nosso prazer!</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="18" />
      <text>Tell them to do good and to be rich in good works, and to be generous and willing to share.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>Mande que façam o bem, que sejam ricos em boas ações, que sejam generosos e estejam prontos para repartir com os outros aquilo que eles têm.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="19" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="19" />
      <text>In this way they will lay up in store for themselves a good foundation against the time to come, that they may lay hold of eternal life.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="19" />
    <text>Desse modo eles juntarão para si mesmos um tesouro que será uma base firme para o futuro. E assim conseguirão receber a vida, a verdadeira vida</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="20" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="20" />
      <text>Timothy, guard that which is committed to you, turning away from the empty chatter and oppositions of science which is falsely so called;</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="20" />
    <text>Timóteo, guarde bem aquilo que foi entregue h aos seus cuidados. Evite os falatórios que ofendem a Deus e as discussões tolas a respeito daquilo que alguns, de modo errado, chamam de “conhecimento”.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-1TI" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="6" initialStartVerse="21" characterId="narrator-1TI">
      <verse num="21" />
      <text>Some people have gone after much learning and have erred concerning the faith. Grace be with you. Amen.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="21" />
    <text>Algumas pessoas, afirmando que tinham esse “conhecimento”, se desviaram do caminho da fé. Que a * graça de Deus esteja com vocês!</text>
  </block>
  <UnappliedSplits />
</book>