<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<book id="2TH" singlevoice="false" pageheader="2 TESSALONICENSES">
  <block style="mt" chapter="0" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="mt" chapter="0" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-2TH">
      <text>2 THESSALONIANS</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <text>SEGUNDA CARTA DE PAULO AOS TESSALONICENSES</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" book="2TH" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="c" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="0">
      <text>2 THESSALONIANS 1</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <text>1</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="1" />
      <text>Paul, Silvanus, and Timothy, to the assembly of the Thessalonians in God our Father, and the Lord Jesus Christ:</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Eu, Paulo, e Silas, e Timóteo escrevemos esta carta aos irmãos da igreja da cidade de Tessalônica, irmãos que estão unidos com Deus, o nosso Pai, e com o Senhor Jesus Cristo.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="2" />
      <text>Grace to you and peace from God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>Que a graça e a paz de Deus, o nosso Pai, e do Senhor Jesus Cristo estejam com vocês!</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="3" />
      <text>We are bound to always give thanks to God for you, brothers, even as it is appropriate, because your faith grows exceedingly, and the love of each and every one of you towards one another abounds.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>Irmãos, sempre temos de dar graças a Deus por vocês. Para nós é certo fazer isso porque a fé que vocês têm está crescendo cada vez mais, e o amor que vocês têm uns pelos outros está se tornando cada vez maior.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="4" />
      <text>Therefore we ourselves boast about you in the assemblies of God. We boast of your patience and faith in all your persecutions and in the afflictions which you endure.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>É por isso que nas igrejas de Deus falamos com orgulho sobre vocês. Nós temos orgulho de vocês por causa da paciência e da fé que vocês mostram no meio de todas as perseguições e sofrimentos.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="5" />
      <text>This is an obvious sign of the righteous judgment of God, to the end that you may be counted worthy of the Kingdom of God, for which you also suffer.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>Esta é uma prova de que Deus é justo na sua maneira de julgar. Como resultado disso, vocês se tornarão merecedores do seu Reino, pelo qual estão sofrendo.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="6" />
      <text>Since it is a righteous thing with God to repay affliction to those who afflict you,</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>Deus fará o que é justo: ele trará sofrimento para aqueles que fazem com que vocês sofram</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="7" />
      <text>and to give relief to you who are afflicted with us. This will happen when the Lord Jesus is revealed from heaven with his mighty angels in flaming fire:</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>e dará descanso a vocês e também a nós, que sofremos. Ele fará isso quando o Senhor Jesus vier do céu e aparecer junto com os seus anjos poderosos,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="8" />
      <text>He will give vengeance to those who don’t know God, and to those who don’t obey the Good News of our Lord Jesus Christ,</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>no meio de chamas de fogo, para castigar os que rejeitam a Deus e não obedecem ao evangelho do nosso Senhor Jesus.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="9" />
      <text>They will pay the penalty: eternal destruction from the face of the Lord and from the glory of his might.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>Eles serão castigados com a destruição eterna e ficarão longe da presença do Senhor e do seu * glorioso poder.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="10" />
      <text>When he comes, his glory will be seen in his saints. He will receive honor from all those who put their trust in him. This includes you because you believed our testimony to you.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>Isso acontecerá naquele dia a, o dia em que ele vier para ser louvado por todo o seu povo e para receber homenagens de todos os que crêem. Vocês também estarão entre eles, pois creram na mensagem que nós anunciamos.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="11" />
      <text>To this end we also pray always for you, that our God may count you worthy of your calling, and fulfill every desire of goodness and work of faith, with power.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>É por isso que sempre oramos por vocês, pedindo que o nosso Deus, que * chamou vocês para a nova vida, faça com que sejam merecedores dela. Pedimos também que ele, pelo seu poder, realize todos os desejos que vocês têm de fazer o bem e complete o trabalho que fazem com fé.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="1" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="12" />
      <text>In this way, the name of our Lord Jesus Christ may be glorified in you, and you in him. Aaccording to the grace of our God and the Lord Jesus Christ.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>Assim Jesus, o nosso Senhor, será louvado por causa do comportamento de vocês, e vocês serão elogiados por ele, por meio da graça do nosso Deus e do Senhor Jesus Cristo.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" book="2TH" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="c" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="0">
      <text>2 THESSALONIANS 2</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <text>2</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="1" />
      <text>Now, brothers, concerning the coming of our Lord Jesus Christ, and our gathering together to him, here is what we ask:</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Agora, irmãos, a respeito da vinda de Jesus Cristo, o nosso Senhor, e do nosso encontro com ele, pedimos a vocês o seguinte:</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="2" />
      <text>Do not be quickly shaken in your mind, nor yet be troubled, either by spirit, or by word. Nor by letter as from us, saying that the day of Christ had come.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>Não se perturbem facilmente, nem fiquem assustados se alguém afirmar que o Dia do Senhor b já chegou. Talvez alguém diga que nós tenhamos afirmado isso enquanto profetizávamos ou anunciávamos o evangelho ou que escrevemos isso em alguma carta.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="3" />
      <text>Let no one deceive you in any way. For it will not be, unless the departure comes first, and the man of sin is revealed. He is the son of destruction.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>Não deixem que ninguém os engane com nada disso. Pois, antes desse dia, terá de acontecer a Revolta contra Deus, e terá de aparecer o Perverso, que está condenado a ir para o inferno.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="4" />
      <text>He opposes and exalts himself against all that is called God or that is worshiped; so that he sits as God in the temple of God, setting himself up as God.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>Ele será contra tudo o que as pessoas adoram e contra tudo o que elas acham que é divino. Ele vai se colocar acima de todos e até mesmo vai entrar e sentar-se no Templo de Deus e afirmar que é Deus!</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="5" />
      <text>Don’t you remember that, when I was still with you, I told you these things?</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>Por acaso vocês não lembram que eu lhes disse tudo isso quando estava com vocês?</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="6" />
      <text>Now you know what is restraining him, to the end that he may be revealed in his own season.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>E vocês sabem também que existe alguma coisa que não deixa que isso aconteça agora; porém, no tempo certo, o Perverso aparecerá.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="7" />
      <text>For the mystery of lawlessness already works. Only there is one who restrains now, until he is taken out of the way.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>A Misteriosa Maldade já está agindo, mas o que está para acontecer acontecerá somente depois que for afastado aquele que não deixa que isso aconteça.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="8" />
      <text>Then the lawless one will be revealed, whom the Lord will kill with the breath of his mouth, and destroy by the manifestation of his coming.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>Então o Perverso aparecerá, e o Senhor Jesus, quando vier, o matará com um sopro e o destruirá com a sua * gloriosa presença.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="9" />
      <text>The coming of the lawless one will be in accordance with the working of Satan with all power and signs and lying wonders.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>O Perverso chegará com o poder de Satanás e fará todo tipo de falsos milagres e maravilhas.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="10" />
      <text>Those who are lost in sin will be deceived by the things he can do because they didn’t receive the love of the truth, that they might be saved.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>E enganará com todo tipo de maldade os que vão ser destruídos. Eles vão ser destruídos porque não aceitaram nem amaram a verdade que os poderia salvar.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="11" />
      <text>Because of this, God sends them a working of error, that they should believe a lie.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>Por isso Deus envia o poder do erro para agir neles a fim de que acreditem naquilo que é falso.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="12" />
      <text>They will all be judged because they didn’t believe the truth, but had pleasure in unrighteousness.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>O resultado disso é que serão condenados todos os que não crêem na verdade, mas têm prazer no pecado.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="13" />
      <text>But we are bound to always give thanks to God for you, brothers loved by the Lord, because God chose you from the beginning for salvation through sanctification of the Spirit and belief in the truth.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>Irmãos, sempre devemos dar graças a Deus por vocês, a quem o Senhor ama. Pois Deus os escolheu como os primeiros a serem salvos pelo poder do Espírito Santo e pela fé que vocês têm na verdade, a fim de tornar vocês o seu povo dedicado a ele.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="14" />
      <text>He called you to this through our Good News, for the obtaining of the glory of our Lord Jesus Christ.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>Foi para isso que Deus os * chamou, por meio do * evangelho que anunciamos, a fim de que vocês tomem parte na * glória do nosso Senhor Jesus Cristo.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="15" />
      <text>So then, brothers, stand firm, and hold the traditions which you were taught by us, whether by word, or by letter.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>Portanto, irmãos, fiquem firmes e guardem aquelas verdades que ensinamos a vocês tanto nas nossas mensagens como na nossa carta</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="16" />
      <text>Now our Lord Jesus Christ himself, and God our Father, who loved us and gave us eternal comfort and good hope through grace,</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>Que o próprio Jesus Cristo, o nosso Senhor, e Deus, o nosso Pai, que nos ama e que na sua bondade nos dá uma coragem que não acaba e uma esperança firme,</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="2" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="17" />
      <text>comfort your hearts and establish you in every good work and word.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>encham o coração de vocês de ânimo e os tornem fortes para fazerem e dizerem tudo o que é bom!</text>
  </block>
  <block style="c" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" book="2TH" initialStartVerse="0" characterId="BC-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="c" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="0">
      <text>2 THESSALONIANS 3</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <text>3</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="1" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="1" />
      <text>Finally, brothers, pray for us, that the word of the Lord may spread rapidly and be glorified, even as also with you;</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="1" />
    <text>Finalmente, irmãos, orem por nós para que a mensagem do Senhor continue a se espalhar rapidamente e seja bem aceita, como aconteceu entre vocês.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="2" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="2" />
      <text>and that we may be delivered from unreasonable and evil men; for not all have faith.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="2" />
    <text>Orem também para que Deus nos livre das pessoas más e perversas, pois nem todos crêem na mensagem.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="3" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="3" />
      <text>But the Lord is faithful, who will establish you, and guard you from the evil one.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="3" />
    <text>Mas o Senhor Jesus é fiel. Ele lhes dará forças e os livrará do Maligno c.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="4" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="4" />
      <text>We have confidence in the Lord concerning you, that you both do and will do the things we command.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="4" />
    <text>E o Senhor faz com que confiemos em vocês; temos a certeza de que estão fazendo e continuarão a fazer o que lhes recomendamos.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="5" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="5" />
      <text>May the Lord direct your hearts into the love of God, and into the patience of Christ.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="5" />
    <text>Que o Senhor os faça compreender melhor o amor de Deus por vocês e a firmeza que ele, Cristo, dá!</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="6" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="6" />
      <text>Now we command you, brothers, in the name of our Lord Jesus Christ. Withdraw yourselves from every brother who walks in rebellion, and not after the tradition which they received from us.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="6" />
    <text>Irmãos, em nome do nosso Senhor Jesus Cristo, ordenamos a vocês que se afastem de todos os irmãos que vivem sem trabalhar e que não seguem os ensinamentos que demos a eles.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="7" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="7" />
      <text>For you know how you ought to imitate us. For we didn’t behave ourselves rebelliously among you,</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="7" />
    <text>Vocês sabem muito bem que devem seguir o nosso exemplo, pois não temos vivido entre vocês sem trabalhar.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="8" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="8" />
      <text>neither did we eat bread from anyone’s hand without paying for it. In labor and travail we worked night and day, that we might not burden any of you.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="8" />
    <text>Não temos recebido nada de ninguém, sem pagar; na verdade trabalhamos e nos cansamos. Trabalhamos sem parar, dia e noite, a fim de não sermos um peso para nenhum de vocês.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="9" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="9" />
      <text>We did this, not because we don’t have the right, but to make ourselves an example to you, that you should imitate us.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="9" />
    <text>É claro que temos o direito de receber sustento; mas não temos pedido nada a fim de que vocês seguissem o nosso exemplo.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="10" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="10" />
      <text>For even when we were with you, we commanded you this: “If anyone will not work, neither let him eat.”</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="10" />
    <text>Porque, quando estávamos aí, demos esta regra: “Quem não quer trabalhar que não coma.”</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="11" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="11" />
      <text>For we hear of some who walk among you in rebellion, who don’t work at all, but are busybodies.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="11" />
    <text>Estamos afirmando isso porque ouvimos dizer que há entre vocês algumas pessoas que vivem como os preguiçosos: não fazem nada e se metem na vida dos outros.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="12" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="12" />
      <text>Now those who are that way, we command and exhort in the Lord Jesus Christ, that with quietness they work, and eat their own bread.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="12" />
    <text>Em nome do Senhor Jesus Cristo, ordenamos com insistência a essas pessoas que vivam de um modo correto e trabalhem para se sustentar.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="13" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="13" />
      <text>But you, brothers, don’t be weary in doing well.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="13" />
    <text>Mas vocês, irmãos, não se cansem de fazer o bem.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="14" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="14" />
      <text>If any man doesn’t obey our word in this letter, note that man, that you have no company with him, to the end that he may be ashamed.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="14" />
    <text>Se alguém não quiser obedecer ao que estamos mandando nesta carta, vejam bem quem está fazendo isso e se afastem dele para que fique envergonhado</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="15" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="15" />
      <text>Don’t count him as an enemy, but admonish him as a brother.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="15" />
    <text>No entanto não o tratem como inimigo, mas o aconselhem como se aconselha um irmão.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="16" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="16" />
      <text>Now may the Lord of peace himself give you peace at all times in all ways. The Lord be with you all.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="16" />
    <text>Que o Senhor da paz dê a vocês a paz, sempre e de todas as maneiras! E que o Senhor esteja com todos vocês!</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="17" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="17" />
      <text>The greeting of me, Paul, with my own hand, which is the sign in every letter: this is how I write.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="17" />
    <text>Com a minha própria mão escrevo isto: Saudações de Paulo. É assim que assino todas as minhas cartas; é assim que escrevo.</text>
  </block>
  <block style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-2TH" matchesReferenceText="true">
    <ReferenceBlocks style="p" paragraphStart="true" chapter="3" initialStartVerse="18" characterId="narrator-2TH">
      <verse num="18" />
      <text>The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with you all. Amen.</text>
    </ReferenceBlocks>
    <verse num="18" />
    <text>Que a * graça do nosso Senhor Jesus Cristo esteja com todos vocês!</text>
  </block>
  <UnappliedSplits />
</book>